[
 {
  "id": 1,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the basic process whereby information is transmitted within the brain.",
  "answer": "The brain is made up of neurons, or nerve cells. Each neuron has extensions, or branches, called axons and dendrites. Dendrites are extensions that receive messages from another neuron. Axons are extensions that send messages to another neuron. The gap between one neuron’s axon and another’s dendrite is called a synapse. The synapse is the location where a chemical exchange takes place. This change in chemical secretions is how the brain conveys information. When a synapse occurs between neurons, the specific message being sent advances from one nerve cell to the next. Messages are transmitted from neuron to neuron along neural pathways until they reach their destinations."
 },
 {
  "id": 2,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Differentiate between sensation and perception. Summarize the general neuroanatomy involved in transforming sensations to perceptions.",
  "answer": "Sensations are the result of our senses collecting and registering input from our environment. Our eyes see images, our ears hear sounds, our skin is involved in our sense of touch, our noses smell, and our tongues taste. However, sensations by themselves do not mean anything to us without perception. Perception is how our brains interpret the signals received by our senses. Generally, after sensory signals enter the respective sensory organs, they are transmitted by nerves from these organs to the brain. Different nerves do this job, depending on the sense organ involved. Each organ is innervated with specific nerves. Each nerve carries different sensory information to a particular area of the brain that is responsible for processing that specific sense. Our brains interpret sensory signals to make sense of them. For example, an image seen by the eyes is interpreted as something recognizable, such as a person or a tree; sounds heard by the ears are interpreted as birdsong, human speech, music, or noise; etc."
 },
 {
  "id": 3,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the term prosopagnosia. Describe the demands the visual stimuli of faces make on our perceptual mechanisms. Explain how current neuroimaging technology can inform prosopagnosia research and treatment.",
  "answer": "Prosopagnosia is a neurological condition. A colloquial description for it is “face blindness.” Individuals with prosopagnosia cannot recognize faces, even ones that are extremely familiar—spouses, family members, best friends, pictures of their country’s president, etc. They know who the people are once they are told, but cannot identify them by their faces. According to neuropsychologists, faces make maximal demands on our visual perception systems. In fact, faces are some of the most “compelling” visual stimuli we see. With advances in technology, researchers have been able to look beyond one region of the brain. In doing so, they have discovered that multiple parts of the brain are involved in face recognition. The right fusiform region, for example, plays a key part. Additionally, information is distributed evenly among anterior temporal regions. These regions, which are part of a network, respond differently to identities in clear patterns. Scientists hope to develop treatments for prosopagnosia using this knowledge."
 },
 {
  "id": 4,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some recent discoveries by neuropsychologists that have changed beliefs about face recognition. Explain how these beliefs have changed and the implications for research and treatment.",
  "answer": "Until recently, scientists believed that face recognition—the ability to identify someone’s face as belonging to someone we know each time we see it—was governed by only a couple of areas of the brain. However, scientists at Carnegie Mellon University discovered that, actually, an entire network of different areas within the cerebral cortex interact and collaborate during the task of face recognition. This will change the types of research questions researchers ask in the future, because they will no longer focus their study on just one area of the brain. Instead, scientists will need to study the “system as a whole” to develop an understanding of how we individuate faces. In addition to these implications for research, this discovery may help in the development of treatments for prosopagnosia, or “face blindness.” Individuals with this disorder cannot recognize even the most familiar faces on sight."
 },
 {
  "id": 5,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how spatial maps function as neural correlates of attention, and include examples related to visual perception.",
  "answer": "Spatial maps increase or decrease neural activity in various brain areas that process different sensory information. They can stimulate orienting behaviors such as eye movements in the case of visual stimuli. They function at different levels in a hierarchy. In the dorsolateral frontal cortex, the frontal eye fields (the top of the hierarchy) have a spatial map revolving around the retina that enhances cortical responses to visual stimuli. The parietal cortex (the next level of the hierarchy) has various spatial maps. The lateral inter-parietal area has a map for saliency, and is interconnected with sensory brain areas and the frontal eye fields. At the sub-cortical level, the superior colliculi manage automatic responses related to attention, such as orienting to more prominent stimuli. At the level of neural networks, lateral inhibition and similar processes are believed to influence competitive selection, which is the way in which our working memory selects and pays attention to some information above other information."
 },
 {
  "id": 6,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify a neural correlate of attention. Summarize a recent general neural model of attention with four basic processes.",
  "answer": "A neural correlate of attention is the enhancement of neuronal firing. If a neuron fires in response to a stimulus even when the individual is not attending to it, it will fire more strongly when the individual is attending to it. The four basic processes of a recent general neural model of attention are: (1) working memory, which retains information momentarily to be analyzed; (2) competitive selection, wherein some information competes to access our working memory over other information; (3) “top-down sensitivity control,” whereby higher-order cognitive processes can control signal intensities; and (4) occasional stimuli or ones that are important from an instinctive or biological perspective (also known as “bottom-up saliency filters”), which automatically increase our neural responses. In information channels that compete for use of our working memory, working memory influences our voluntary control of attention by affecting which new information we select."
 },
 {
  "id": 7,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some recent discoveries regarding neural correlates of memory and the implications of these discoveries.",
  "answer": "Scientists traditionally assumed that we recall memories due to external stimuli that act as cues. Recently, however, researchers have found that brain activity levels before retrieval from storage are correlated with memory. By measuring theta brainwaves, scientists found that high rates of theta waves in human subjects before they were prompted to recall memorized words and their contexts were associated with better memory performance. Theta brainwaves (when produced along with other frequencies) are associated with the brain actively monitoring or exploring something. Rats, for example, display more theta waves when exploring mazes. Researchers concluded that this is an indication that the brain is mostly occupied with internal activities unrelated to external stimuli. The brain does not wait for external stimuli. Instead, external stimuli interact with the brain’s spontaneous internal activity patterns. Scientists wonder if we can voluntarily adjust our brains for better recall. If so, it could improve treatments for memory loss."
 },
 {
  "id": 8,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the frequencies of alpha, beta, gamma, delta, and theta brainwaves and their corresponding states of consciousness.",
  "answer": "Alpha brainwaves have a frequency of 8 to 14 Hertz, occur during relaxed states such as when people are daydreaming or fantasizing, and are stimulated by sensory input. They also serve as bridges to unconscious information (see theta brainwaves). Beta brainwaves have a frequency of 15 to 38 Hertz (higher than alpha waves) and are characteristic of “normal” waking states of consciousness. They are involved with outward attention and conscious, logical, and analytical thought. Gamma brainwaves, which have a frequency of 38 to 100 Hertz, are associated with peak performance states (“flow”), high attentional focus\/concentration, meditation, and transcendental and mystical experiences, but also with schizophrenia, hyperactivity, and anxiety. Gamma waves synchronize broad activity across brain regions. Recently discovered gamma waves involved in meditation specifically are the subject of much research. Theta brainwaves have a frequency of 4 to 7 Hertz, and are associated with dreaming\/REM sleep, meditation, creative states, and peak experiences. With theta waves alone, unconscious information cannot be accessed. Alpha brainwaves bridge theta waves to beta waves to make this content conscious and\/or commit it to memory. Delta brainwaves, which have a frequency of 0.5 to 3 Hertz, are associated with deep sleep when they occur in isolation. Combined with other frequencies, they are associated with intuition, hunches, or “radar”\/“feelings” for people and situations."
 },
 {
  "id": 9,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some deficiencies or imbalances in specific neurotransmitters that are implicated in certain mental and mood disorders",
  "answer": "The neurotransmitter (brain chemical) gamma amino butyric acid (GABA) is produced by a gene whose expression is decreased in individuals with schizophrenia. Many research studies have confirmed this. This deficiency could account not only for hallucinations and delusions, but also for the marked disruption of cognitive processes typical in those with schizophrenia. The neurotransmitter dopamine is also implicated in schizophrenia, as well as Parkinson’s disease (affecting motor control) and the brain’s reward circuits. The neurotransmitter serotonin is associated with calm, tranquil, and happy moods (and performs many other functions). Individuals with mood disorders involving depression, anxiety, or both have lower than normal levels of serotonin and\/or its precursors. Serotoninspecific reuptake inhibitor (SSRI) medications can treat anxiety and depression by preventing serotonin recycling, allowing more of it to remain in the brain to stabilize mood. The neurotransmitter glutamate’s receptors mostly excite action potentials; GABA’s receptors mostly inhibit them. The neurotransmitter acetylcholine’s receptors are both excitatory and inhibitory."
 },
 {
  "id": 10,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the primary neural effects of alcohol intoxication and the associated behaviors.",
  "answer": "Drinking alcohol affects the brain in two opposite ways: it both excites and depresses the central nervous system. Initially, alcohol has an intense depressive effect on the central nervous system, but this is temporary. After, it agitates the central nervous system. The effect is less intense but lasts about six times as long as the depressant effects of alcohol. The drinking environment and the drinker’s personality influence the drinker’s perception of these effects. In non-social, quiet environments, excitation of the nervous system can be impeded. This makes the drinker and others more aware of alcohol’s depressant, sedative effects. In social settings where there is more sensory stimulation, drinkers can mistake small amounts of alcohol as stimulating, but this is due to its ability to suppress inhibitions in some parts of the brain. Small losses in self-control manifest as increased talkativeness, liveliness, and self-confidence. With larger volumes of alcohol and\/or chronic drinking, disinhibition progresses to motor impairment, loss of control, stupor, coma, and death."
 },
 {
  "id": 11,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the four major neurotransmitter systems, their places of origin\/pathways, and the systems\/responses they affect.",
  "answer": "The norepinephrine (or noradrenaline) system originates in the locus ceruleus and the lateral tegmental field. It excites the brain’s systems of arousal and reward. The dopamine system travels the following pathways: mesocortical, mesolimbic, nigrostriatal, and tuberoinfundibular. Dopamine affects the motor system, reward circuits, cognitive functions, and endocrine functions. It is also related to feelings of nausea. The serotonin system originates in the caudal dorsal raphe nucleus and the rostral dorsal raphe nucleus. It enhances introversion, mood, satiety (sense of fullness), body temperature, and sleep. It reduces nociception (sense of pain and processing of noxious, or harmful, stimuli). The cholinergic system originates in the pontomesencephalotegmental complex, the basal optic nucleus of Meynert, and the medial septal nucleus. It has effects on learning, short-term memory, states of arousal, and the reward circuits. The sharing of effects by more than one system shows that all neural systems interact and coordinate."
 },
 {
  "id": 12,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the neurochemical mechanisms behind the immediate effects and addictive properties of cocaine.",
  "answer": "Cocaine functions as a local anesthetic, deadening pain impulses by preventing the brain’s sodium channels from generating action potentials. It also inhibits the reuptake of various neurotransmitters, including norepinephrine, dopamine, and serotonin. By binding to the dopamine transporter, cocaine increases dopamine levels in the brain, which results in longer-lasting and more intense dopamine signaling to neuroreceptors. Dopamine is involved with the brain’s reward circuits. Higher dopamine levels and signaling bring feelings of pleasure, accounting for the cocaine “high.” Not knowing the higher levels and signaling are caused artificially by the drug, the body’s natural affinity for homeostasis (balance) causes it to try to reduce dopamine levels. When the drug wears off, the chronic user experiences depleted dopamine levels and the accompanying depression and withdrawal symptoms. Chronic use also sensitizes the reward system to cocaine effects. The combination of withdrawal and sensitization motivates users to continue using the drug to relieve withdrawal symptoms and restore pleasure. Cocaine addiction and relapse may also be observed in frequent users."
 },
 {
  "id": 13,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain a recent change in the scientific hypotheses about the respective roles of tangles and plaques in the brains of Alzheimer’s patients.",
  "answer": "Neurofibrillary tangles are twisted fibers made of abnormal tau protein. Amyloid plaques are made of beta amyloid protein fragments that are not dissolved and eliminated as they are in healthy brains. These plaques and tangles were discovered in the brains of deceased Alzheimer’s patients through autopsy research. Once these were discovered, many neuroscientists believed for years that the plaques were the primary cause of destroyed and damaged neurons (brain nerve cells). However, more recently, some researchers have come to believe that the neurofibrillary tau tangles are mainly responsible for the neuron destruction, and that the plaques may be the brain’s attempt to protect itself against these tangles. An analogy used is the formation of pearls by oysters to protect their bodies from irritant particles. Traditionally, medications have been developed with a focus on inhibiting plaque formation. Due to the more recent hypothesis, some scientists suspect that overly inhibiting plaque growth could harm rather than help the patient. Researchers are investigating what causes tangles to form and how to prevent them."
 },
 {
  "id": 14,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some current information regarding the neural mechanisms of Alzheimer’s disease.",
  "answer": "Alzheimer’s disease is a progressive dementia primarily affecting aged people, though some patients (a minority) are also diagnosed with “early Alzheimer’s” in their fifties. Neurologists have identified two substances that form in the brains of Alzheimer’s patients. These are neurofibrillary tangles and amyloid plaques. The body normally produces amyloid proteins. Beta amyloid is a fragment that detaches from an amyloid precursor protein. In healthy brains, these fragments are broken down and eliminated. However, in Alzheimer’s disease, they are not eliminated but instead accumulate and form hard plaques between neurons that cannot be broken down or dissolved. Neurofibrillary tangles, twisted fibers that form in the brain cells of Alzheimer’s patients, are also insoluble. They are composed of a protein called tau. Normally, tau forms microtubules that transport nutrients and other substances within neurons. In Alzheimer’s tangles, the tau is abnormal, causing the microtubules to collapse. Plaques and tangles are believed to contribute to neuronal degradation."
 },
 {
  "id": 15,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some common depressants, including some brand\/street names; indicate their medical uses, if any; describe their effects, including degrees of dependency and tolerance; and discuss overdose and withdrawal symptoms.",
  "answer": "Depressants, which inhibit or depress the central nervous system, include Gamma Hydroxybutyric Acid (Xyrem, Sodium Oxybate, and “Liquid Ecstasy”); benzodiazepines (Valium, Xanax, Halcion, Restoril, Ativan, Klonopin, Rohypnol, and “roofies”); Methaqualone (Quaalude); Ambien; Sonata; Chloral Hydrate; Meprobamate; and various barbiturates. Gamma Hydroxybutyric Acid is not used medically in the USA; elsewhere, it is used as an anesthetic. Benzodiazepines are used medically as anti-anxiety treatments, sedatives, anti-convulsive treatments, hypnotics, and muscle relaxants. The others mentioned above are used as anti-anxiety, sedative, and hypnotic medications. All of these drugs induce moderate degrees of physical and psychological dependency. Tolerance develops to all these drugs. Depressant effects include disorientation, slurred speech, “drunken” behavior when no alcohol is consumed, impaired memory, and interaction with alcohol. Overdose symptoms include clammy skin, shallow breathing, a weak and rapid pulse, dilated pupils, coma, and possible death. Withdrawal symptoms include insomnia, anxiety, tremors, delirium, convulsions, and possible death."
 },
 {
  "id": 16,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define narcotics; name some common narcotics, including some brand names; indicate their medical use(s), if any; describe their effects, including degrees of dependency and tolerance; and discuss overdose and withdrawal symptoms.",
  "answer": "Narcotics are opiates (derived from opium poppies) or opioids (synthetic narcotics). They include the opiates heroin, morphine, and codeine; the synthetic opioids hydrocodone (Vicodin, Lortab, and Tussionex), oxycodone (OxyContin, Percocet, Percodan, and Roxicet), and hydromorphone (Dilaudid); and others such as Paregoric, Demerol, Fentanyl, Darvon, and Methadone. Heroin has no medical use in the United States. Elsewhere, it may be used as a painkiller and\/or a cough suppressant. The others are used as painkillers and\/or cough suppressants in the United States. Paregoric is also used as an anti-spasmodic\/anti-diarrheal drug. Tolerance develops to all these drugs.\n\nCodeine causes moderate physical and psychological dependence; heroin, morphine, and the synthetics opioids cause high dependency. The other drugs identified above vary in terms of the level of dependency they typically cause.\n\nNarcotic effects include euphoria, drowsiness, depressed breathing, pupil contraction, and nausea. Overdose symptoms include slow, shallow breathing; clammy skin; convulsions; coma; and possible death. Withdrawal symptoms include irritability, tremors, cramps, nausea, chills, sweating, loss of appetite, runny nose, watery eyes, yawning, and panic."
 },
 {
  "id": 17,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some common hallucinogens, including some street\/brand names; indicate their medical uses, if any; describe their effects, including degrees of dependency and tolerance; and discuss symptoms of overdose and withdrawal.",
  "answer": "Hallucinogens cause illusions and\/or otherwise alter normal consciousness. Phencyclidine (PCP or “angel dust”) and its analogs include ketamine hydrochloride (Ketaset, Ketanest, and Ketalar), which is used medically as an anesthetic. MDMA (“Ecstasy”), LSD (“Acid”), and others have no medical uses. Other hallucinogens include psilocybin mushrooms, mescaline, peyote, ayahuasca, DMT, AMT, and Fory. Dependence is possible with phencyclidine. MDMA, LSD, and the drugs identified above as other hallucinogens do not induce dependency. Phencyclidine is associated with high physical and psychological need; MDMA is associated with moderate need; and LSD and the drugs described as other hallucinogens are associated with no physical and\/or psychological need. MDMA and its analogs, phencyclidine and its analogs, and LSD all induce tolerance, which is also possible with the other drugs identified above. MDMA causes euphoria, heightened sensations, disinhibition, dehydration, and teeth grinding. Overdose causes elevated temperature, electrolyte imbalance, and cardiac arrest. Withdrawal symptoms include drowsiness, depression, muscle aches, and acne. The other hallucinogens alter perceptions of time and distance and cause visions\/illusions. LSD overdose causes longer, more intense “trips.” Overdoses of the other drugs interfere with the user’s ability to feel pain, remember, or direct movement."
 },
 {
  "id": 18,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some common stimulants, including some brand\/street names; indicate their medical uses, if any; describe their effects, including degrees of dependency and tolerance; and discuss overdose and withdrawal symptoms.",
  "answer": "Stimulants, which excite the central nervous system, include cocaine (“coke,” “snow,” or “crack”); amphetamines and methamphetamines (“speed,” “crank,” “ice,” “crystal meth,” Adderall, Dexedrine, and Desoxyn); methylphenidates (Ritalin, Focalin, Concerta, and Metadate); and others (Provigil, Adipex P, Prelu-2, Didrex, and Ionamin). Cocaine is used medically as a local anesthetic. Amphetamines and methamphetamines are used medically for weight control and to alleviate the symptoms of attention deficit-hyperactivity disorder and narcolepsy. The brand names given for methylphenidates are typically prescribed for attention deficithyperactivity disorder. The other stimulants named are used medically to suppress appetite and control narcolepsy symptoms. All the stimulants identified above have the potential for dependency. Cocaine, amphetamines and methamphetamines, and methylphenidates pose a high risk for physical and\/or psychological dependence; the others identified pose a moderate risk. Tolerance can develop to all these drugs.\n\nEffects include excitation, enhanced alertness, euphoria, loss of appetite, insomnia, and elevated blood pressure and pulse. Overdose symptoms include elevated temperature, agitation, hallucinations, convulsions, and possible death. Withdrawal symptoms include irritability, apathy, prolonged sleep, disorientation, and depression."
 },
 {
  "id": 19,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Contrast common reasons for anabolic steroid abuse vs. abuse of most other drugs. Name some anabolic steroids; discuss their medical uses; describe what is known about dependency and tolerance; outline their effects; and identify any overdose and withdrawal symptoms.",
  "answer": "Other drugs such as narcotics, depressants, stimulants, and hallucinogens are commonly abused for recreational purposes. People may also selfmedicate with these drugs to relieve insomnia, anxiety, depression, or pain. However, anabolic steroids are commonly abused to enhance athletic performance. Testosterone, the primary male sex hormone, can be created in a synthetic form. When used to supplement normal\/naturally occurring levels, this increases male secondary sex characteristics, including muscular development, strength, and endurance. Brand names include Depo Testosterone, Sten, Sustanon, and Cypt. Other anabolic steroids include Parabolan, Winstrol, Anadrol, Dianabol (“Dbol”), Equipoise, and Primobolan Depot. Testosterone is used medically to treat hypogonadism (when male testes produce little or no natural testosterone), which has a variety of causes. The other steroids named above are used medically to treat anemia and breast cancer. It is unknown whether testosterone causes physical\/psychological dependency or tolerance. The other anabolic steroids mentioned have the potential to cause psychological dependence; the risks of physical dependency and tolerance are unknown. In addition to virilization, anabolic steroid effects include gynecomastia (breast growth), edema, testicular atrophy, acne, and aggression. Overdose symptoms are undetermined. Withdrawal may cause depression."
 },
 {
  "id": 20,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name the substances classified as cannabis; outline their medical uses, if any; describe their effects, including dependency and tolerance; and discuss symptoms of overdose and withdrawal.",
  "answer": "Substances classified as cannabis include marijuana (“pot,” “grass,” etc.); tetrahydrocannabinol (THC or Marinol), which is the active ingredient in marijuana; hashish; and hashish oil. THC\/Marinol is used medically to relieve nausea and stimulate appetite. Medicinal marijuana is used for these reasons and for pain relief. THC dependency is possible, but it still hasn’t been determined with certainty whether marijuana, hashish, and hashish oil pose a risk for dependency. All substances pose a moderate risk for psychological dependency. All substances classified as cannabis induce tolerance to their effects. Cannabis drugs cause euphoria, disinhibition, increased appetite, and disorientation. Overdoses can cause fatigue, sedation, sleep, paranoia, and possibly psychosis. Withdrawal symptoms occasionally reported are insomnia, hyperactivity, and decreased appetite. There are also some anecdotal reports by users of short-lived withdrawal symptoms such as mild absent-mindedness, clumsiness, and irritability."
 },
 {
  "id": 21,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some common substances that are also abused as inhalants; outline any medical uses; discuss dependency and tolerance; describe their effects; and identify symptoms of overdose and withdrawal.",
  "answer": "Aside from using the inhalant drugs amyl and butyl nitrate and nitrous oxide, some people abuse everyday substances by concentrating and inhaling their fumes. These include lighter fluid, dry cleaning fluid, spot remover, hairspray, adhesives, and spray paint. A street term for inhaling these chemicals is “huffing.” These substances have no medical uses. The risk of physical dependency is unknown, but their potential for psychological dependency is high. They do not cause tolerance. Their effects are the same as those induced by inhaling nitrous oxide or drinking alcohol: slurred speech; impaired motor control, coordination, and judgment; slow-onset vitamin deficiency; and eventual organ (kidney, liver, heart, and brain) failure.\n\nInhalants can also cause heart failure, death, or brain and body damage upon initial use. Teens often abuse inhalants to selfmedicate for depression.\n\nInhalant overdose symptoms are similar to the ones associated with alcohol, and include vomiting, depressed breathing, unconsciousness, and death. Withdrawal symptoms caused by inhaling nitrous oxide and everyday substances and abusing alcohol are similar, and include insomnia, anxiety, confusion, tremors, hallucinations, vitamin deficiencies, and convulsions."
 },
 {
  "id": 22,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some inhalant drugs; describe any medical uses; discuss dependency and tolerance; explain their effects; and discuss overdose and withdrawal symptoms.",
  "answer": "Amyl nitrate and butyl nitrate are used as recreational inhalants. Amyl nitrate is used medically to treat angina (cardiac chest pain).\n\nStreet names include “poppers,” “pearls,” “Locker Room,” and “Rush.” The risk of physical and\/or psychological dependency is unknown. Amyl nitrate and butyl nitrate do not cause tolerance. Their effects include flushing, low blood pressure, and headaches. Overdose can cause methemoglobinemia, a blood disorder characterized by abnormal, excessive amounts of hemoglobin building up in the blood. Agitation is a symptom of withdrawal from amyl or butyl nitrate. Nitrous oxide (“laughing gas”) is used medically as an anesthetic, often during dental procedures. In the form of aerosol charger cartridges (“whippets”), it is used recreationally. The risk of physical dependency is unknown, and the drug poses a low risk for psychological dependency. It does not create tolerance. Effects include slurred speech, drunken behavior, memory impairment, slow-onset vitamin deficiencies, and organ damage. Overdoses can cause respiratory depression, vomiting, unconsciousness, and possibly death. Withdrawal causes anxiety, insomnia, confusion, tremors, hallucinations, vitamin deficiencies, and convulsions."
 },
 {
  "id": 23,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how drug concentrations in a patient’s body are measured in clinical pharmacokinetics. Identify how “drug levels” in the body are defined in clinical pharmacokinetics. Identify two applications of determining drug levels through clinical pharmacokinetics.",
  "answer": "Scientists would ideally like to measure drug concentrations in a patient’s body at the site of the neuroreceptor, which is where the drug’s action occurs. However, scientists cannot yet access these within the living person’s brain for measurement, so drug concentrations are usually measured in whole blood, or sometimes in cerebrospinal fluid, urine, or saliva. The assumption is that concentrations in these fluids are similar to those at the receptor sites. Pharmacokinetic clinicians often use the term “drug levels” to refer to total drug concentration in blood plasma or serum. “Total” means both the amount of drug that is bound to receptors and the amount of drug that is circulating freely in the system. Normally, the respective amounts of bound and free drug are in balance. One application of determining drug levels is to ascertain the optimal therapeutic dosing regimen. Another is for monitoring. Certain drugs have very narrow therapeutic ranges, so their levels should be routinely monitored."
 },
 {
  "id": 24,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Give a basic definition of pharmacokinetics and its purposes. Identify four basic pharmacokinetic processes and how they are used.",
  "answer": "Pharmacokinetics is the scientific discipline underlying the application of therapeutic drugs and drug interactions. It also informs the study and treatment of drug abuse. Whereas pharmacodynamics addresses the way drugs act on the body, pharmacokinetics addresses the way the body acts on various drugs. It gives scientists a mathematical foundation for evaluating the durations of drugs’ effects and their actions in the body. Pharmacokinetics is divided into four basic and quantifiable pharmacokinetic processes: absorption, distribution, metabolism, and excretion, often represented with the acronym ADME. These processes determine the amounts of prescription drugs that are concentrated in the body when they are taken. Physicians and pharmacists must understand the parameters indicated by the processes of ADME in order to know the effectiveness of particular drug dosages in specific patients, which is determined by drug concentrations in patients’ bodies. This allows health professionals to design suitable drug regimens for patients."
 },
 {
  "id": 25,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define zero-order and first-order drug elimination. Differentiate between them and give examples of drugs that are eliminated in each way.",
  "answer": "In clinical pharmacokinetics, the rate or speed of a process [absorption, distribution, metabolism, or elimination (ADME)] must be known. Process speed or velocity is either zero-order or first-order. A zero-order drug reaction is one wherein the drug is eliminated by the body at a constant rate, independently of the drug’s concentration in the body. This represents nonlinear pharmacokinetics, and the drug can accumulate in the blood. Alcohol is a drug with zero-order elimination. When a drug is eliminated in proportion to the amount of it remaining in the body, this is first-order elimination. With first-order elimination, residual amounts of the drug do not accumulate in the user’s system. The majority of drugs are eliminated in this way. High-dose salicylates and phenytoin are two exceptions. With all drugs, though, if the amount given is increased enough, ADME processes will change from first-order to zero-order elimination; this happens with accidental and intentional overdoses."
 },
 {
  "id": 26,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name some examples of therapeutic drugs whose levels in patients’ bodies must be closely monitored, and explain why.",
  "answer": "Some drugs have very narrow therapeutic ranges. If drug levels fall below this range, they will not help the patient. If drug levels exceed the therapeutic range, they can become toxic. For example, aminoglycosides such as gentamicin, tobramycin, or amikacin are the primary treatments for serious and systemic gram-negative infections. However, they can also cause kidney damage and failure. Ototoxicity, damage to the auditory system, is another risk. These drugs can adversely affect hearing by damaging the outer, middle, and\/or inner ear. They can also interfere with an individual’s sense of balance by damaging the vestibular system in the inner ear. The cardioactive drug digitalis regulates the heartbeat, but toxic levels cause arrhythmias, nausea and\/or vomiting, fatigue, diarrhea, anorexia, hypersalivation, and changes in color vision. The respiratory drug theophylline improves breathing in those with pneumonia, tracheitis, and asthma, but can cause seizures, nausea,vomiting, insomnia, agitation, and life-threatening heart arrhythmias at toxic levels. The anticonvulsant drug phenobarbital, which is used for sedation and control of seizures, can depress the central nervous system and cause ataxia, hypothermia, low blood pressure, tachycardia, irregular breathing, kidney damage, and coma if levels in the body become toxic."
 },
 {
  "id": 27,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Briefly define signal transduction as it relates to pharmacodynamics. Describe five basic molecular mechanisms of signal transduction.",
  "answer": "Signal transduction in pharmacodynamics is the process wherein interactions between drugs and receptors result in messages between cells that alter cell physiology. There are five basic molecular mechanisms of signal transduction. First, a drug crosses a cell membrane, activating an intracellular receptor. Second, transmembrane receptor proteins are involved when a drug binds to a location on an enzyme, changing its intracellular action. Third, a combination of drug and transmembrane receptor protein binds to another protein such as a protein tyrosine kinase, stimulating it. At the amino acid tyrosine site, a tyrosine kinase enzyme stimulates protein phosphorylation. Fourth, a drug binds to a transmembrane ion channel and alters its conduction properties, changing the membrane potential. Finally, an agonist drug binds to a transmembrane receptor, stimulating a G protein [a GTP (guanosine triphosphate)-binding signal transducer protein], resulting in an increase in many intracellular second messenger responses."
 },
 {
  "id": 28,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some of the main roles and molecular characteristics of receptors important in pharmacodynamics, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Typically, drugs accomplish their actions through interaction with a macromolecule (a receptor). Interactions between drugs and receptors inform treatment decisions and play a role in the development of new drugs. Receptors play a role in the following: ascertaining measurable relationships between drug doses and their effects; determining selective drug effects; and mediating agonist (or activating) and antagonist (or blocking) drug effects. Regarding molecular characteristics, receptors are usually regulatory proteins, mediating the effects of hormones, neurotransmitters, and autacoids (biological substances, including hormones, with local physiological effects) such as histamines, prostaglandins, or serotonin. Other receptors are transport proteins. One example is Na\/K ATPase (Sodium-Potassium Adenosine Triphosphatase), the receptor for digoxin and digitoxin, which are digitalis glycosides. Some receptors are structural proteins. For example, tubulin is a receptor for certain anti-inflammatory and anti-cancer drugs. Some receptors are enzymes, which are affected by drugs. For example, the dehydrate folate receptor is inhibited by the drug methotrexate."
 },
 {
  "id": 29,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define second messengers and their role in pharmacodynamic signal transduction, and give four examples.",
  "answer": "Second messengers are molecules that transmit messages from receptors on the surface of a cell to certain molecules within the cell. These molecules may be in the nucleus or the cytoplasm. Hormones such as epinephrine (adrenaline), growth hormone, and others send messages. Second messengers greatly magnify the strength of these signals and relay them along, changing the cell’s activity in some way. Second messengers are parts of signal transduction cascades. One example of their action was observed by Earl W. Sutherland, Jr., who won the 1971 Physiology\/Medicine Nobel Prize for discovering second messengers. The observed action was that epinephrine stimulates the liver to convert glycogen to glucose within liver cells; but alone, epinephrine will not convert glycogen to glucose. Sutherland found that epinephrine activates a second messenger [cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP)], which signals the liver to convert glycogen to glucose. In another example, cyclase enzymes produce and activate cyclic nucleotides. In a third example, enzymes can also open ion channels to admit metal\/mineral ions, as is observed in calcium (Ca2+ ) signaling. Additionally, second messengers bind to and activate proteins, perpetuating the signaling cascade."
 },
 {
  "id": 30,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Give one example of an intracellular receptor related to pharmacodynamic signal transduction and describe its role. Identify several drugs and substances that bind to sites on enzymes and influence intracellular activity.",
  "answer": "Lipid-soluble drugs (drugs that are attracted to fatty tissue) cross the cell membrane and then interact with intracellular receptors. For example, nitric oxide (NO) stimulates the enzyme guanylyl cyclase. This raises the levels of cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP), a cyclic nucleotide derived from guanosine triphosphate (GTP). The cGMP functions as a second messenger to activate intracellular protein kinases as a response when membrane-impermeable peptide hormones bind to the outer surface of a cell. A number of substances bind to response elements of DNA that regulate transcription, the process of producing a complementary RNA copy of a sequence of DNA. For example, testosterone and other sex steroids, thyroid hormone, corticosteroids, mineralocorticoids, and vitamin D all bind to these DNA response elements, influencing the transcription process."
 },
 {
  "id": 31,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify three properties that all second messenger molecules share.",
  "answer": "Second messenger molecules, which are essentially intermediaries that amplify and relay messages or signals that affect cellular activity, can be water soluble, water insoluble, or gaseous in nature. Three common properties shared by all three types of second messenger molecules are: (1) specific reactions in ion channels, or in enzymes, can produce and release these second messenger molecules, and then break them down again; (2) some second messenger molecules, such as calcium, can be stored in specialized organelles to allow them to be released rapidly when necessary; (3) cells can restrict the duration of an area affected by message actions by localizing the synthesis, release, and breakdown of second messenger molecules."
 },
 {
  "id": 32,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify three main kinds of second messenger molecules, describe their characteristics, and name some examples.",
  "answer": "One kind of second messenger molecule is hydrophobic (water insoluble). These molecules are membrane associated. They diffuse from the plasma membrane into the intermembrane space, where they access and control membrane-associated effector proteins. Examples of these molecules are diacylglycerol and phosphatidylinositols. Another kind of second messenger molecule is hydrophilic (water soluble). These molecules are found within the intracellular fluid, or cytosol. Examples are calcium (Ca2+ ), cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP), cyclic guanosine monophosphate (cGMP), and inositol triphosphate (IP3 ). A third kind of second messenger molecule is a gas. Gases can diffuse through the intracellular fluid (cytosol) and also across cell membranes. Examples of these second messenger molecules include nitric oxide (NO), carbon monoxide (CO), and hydrogen sulfide (H2 S)."
 },
 {
  "id": 33,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of the relationship between drug concentration and drug effect. Include an equation for drug potency.",
  "answer": "When it is assumed that a drug’s interaction with a receptor is reversible, the effect of the drug is believed to be proportional to the number of pertinent receptors that are occupied. Chemically, the drug (D) and the receptor (R) to which it binds create a drug-receptor complex. This complex, or DR, leads to a drug effect. Drug potency is the relationship between a drug’s effect and its concentration. The following equation can be used to calculate drug potency: Observed drug effect = (maximal drug effect) * [D] \/ K d + [D]. The concentration of free drug in the body is represented by [D], and the dissociation constant for the drug-receptor complex (DR) is represented by Kd ."
 },
 {
  "id": 34,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some common mechanisms related to the function of second messenger systems.",
  "answer": "Different substances are involved in different secondary messenger systems, such as the arachidonic acid, phosphoinositol, and cyclic adenosine monophosphate (cAMP) systems, but their general mechanisms are similar. First, a neurotransmitter—the first messenger—binds to a receptor protein molecule that crosses membranes. The neurotransmitter’s binding alters the receptor so that it uncovers a site to which a G-protein can bind. That G-protein is called the transducer. By binding to the receptor, the G-protein can exchange a guanosine diphosphate (GDP) molecule for a guanosine triphosphate (GTP) molecule. The G-protein consists of alpha, beta, and gamma subunits. The GDP-GTP exchange occurs on the alpha subunit, causing it to break away from the gamma and beta subunits. All three subunits remain membrane bound. The separated alpha subunit is freed to move along the inner membrane, reaching another membranebound protein called the primary effector, which produces a signal—a second messenger—that diffuses to the inside of the cell. This secondary messenger may activate a secondary effector, the effects of which depend on the particular second messenger system."
 },
 {
  "id": 35,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify six factors that can cause variations in how individual patients respond to drugs.",
  "answer": "Drug responses generally depend on the concentration of drug in the patient’s body and the number of receptors being used. However, there are several factors that can cause variations in drug responses among individual patients. In the “pharmacokinetic effect,” the concentration of drug that actually reaches its corresponding receptor can vary. Second, the concentration of endogenous (naturally occurring) receptor ligands can vary, causing variations in drug responses among individual patients. Ligands are molecules, molecular complexes, or ions that bind with other chemical entities to form larger complexes. Third, if the number and\/or function of the receptors change, this changes drug response. Fourth, some individuals have hypersensitive responses to drugs, meaning they react much more than expected when given a specific dose. Fifth, some patients have idiosyncratic drug responses, which are reactions that are unique, atypical, and unpredictable. Finally, some patients have tachyphylactic responses. These patients exhibit desensitization (reduced response or no response) much faster than normal, either after the initial dose or a series of small doses."
 },
 {
  "id": 36,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the acronym cAMP stands for and identify what type of molecule it is. Identify some of the activities that are mediated by cAMP.",
  "answer": "The acronym cAMP stands for cyclic adenosine monophosphate. It is a second messenger molecule. Basically, second messengers greatly amplify and relay messages that effect changes in cellular activity. Second messengers are produced through specialized reactions in proteins, enzymes, or ion channels. The cAMP molecule mediates various hormonal responses. These include the liver’s breakdown of carbohydrates; the breakdown of triglycerides (fats that are typically measured in the blood along with cholesterol); the renal hormone vasopressin, which controls the kidneys’ conservation of water; the balance (homeostasis) of calcium levels; the heart rate (chronotropic rate) and heart contractions (inotropic state); the regulation of the adrenal and sex steroids, which are produced in response to follicle stimulating hormone and the hormone corticotropin; smooth muscle relaxation; and additional effects related to the endocrine system and the central nervous system."
 },
 {
  "id": 37,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Provide a general summary of how psychotropic medications are used to treat mental disorders, including differential treatment durations and factors that can influence how individual patients respond to these drugs.",
  "answer": "Psychotropic medications do not cure mental disorders. However, they can relieve or control their symptoms to improve the patient’s mood, wellbeing, and ability to function. Some people may have a depressive episode and feel so much better after taking an anti-depressant medication for a few months that they can discontinue it. Others who suffer from severe and\/or long-term depression, bipolar disorder, or schizophrenia will need to take medication for many years. Included among factors that influence how individuals respond to psychoactive medications are: the specific type of mental disorder; the individual’s age, sex, and body size\/weight; physical illnesses; smoking and\/or drinking; the individual’s genetics; the patient’s liver and kidney function; other medications and\/or vitamin, mineral, and herbal supplements the patient is taking; the patient’s diet; and whether the patient takes the medication as prescribed."
 },
 {
  "id": 38,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe a third messenger role played by one type of second messenger molecule that was discovered by researchers.",
  "answer": "Cellular biologists generally assumed that intracellular calcium acting as a second messenger within cells was solely responsible for the stimulating effects of drugs or substances that are calcium-mobilizing agonists (activators). However, some researchers observed that calcium moves in and out of cells during calcium signaling events. This not only alters intracellular calcium, but also locally affects extracellular calcium (calcium located outside of the cells). Many different kinds of cells have “sensors” for extracellular calcium. Based on the existence of these sensors, scientists inferred that the dynamic changes they observed in extracellular calcium had a messaging function. They found that when intracellular calcium was increased by the drug carbachol in normal (intact) stomach mucosa, there were also secondary changes in extracellular calcium. These secondary changes caused alkaline and pepsinogen secretions, which occurred independently of the intracellular changes. The researchers concluded from this that extracellular calcium can function as a third messenger via calcium sensors to control tissue functions formerly believed to be controlled directly by intracellular calcium."
 },
 {
  "id": 39,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the first “atypical” antipsychotic medication developed for treating schizophrenia. Describe its primary benefits and its most serious side effect.",
  "answer": "The first “atypical” antipsychotic developed for schizophrenia was Clozaril (clozapine). Psychiatrists would prescribe it for patients whose schizophrenia symptoms were considered atypical, and for those whose illnesses had not responded well to typical antipsychotic medications. Clozaril is very effective for alleviating certain schizophrenia symptoms, including hallucinations, delusions, and psychotic breaks from reality. However, it has a serious side effect. It can cause agranulocytosis, a condition affecting the immune system wherein white blood cells (granulocytes) are depleted, compromising the patient’s ability to fight infections. Because of the risk of developing agranulocytosis, patients who are prescribed Clozaril should have their white blood cell counts checked every one to two weeks. The expense and inconvenience of such frequent blood work can make Clozaril treatment problematic for many patients, but it can be a helpful choice for patients who are not helped by other antipsychotic drugs."
 },
 {
  "id": 40,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Briefly describe schizophrenia. Identify the first wave of “typical” antipsychotic medications developed for treating schizophrenia, and describe some of their side effects.",
  "answer": "In schizophrenia, the client must have at least 2 of the following symptoms: hallucinations (a core positive symptom), delusions (a core positive symptom), disorganized speech (a core positive symptom), severely disorganized or catatonic behavior, negative symptoms (such as avolition or diminished expression). For diagnosis the client must have at least one of the 3 core positive symptoms. Client’s level of functioning is significantly below level prior to onset. Unless there is successful treatment there are continual signs of schizophrenia for more than six months. The first antipsychotic drugs developed for treating schizophrenia include Thorazine (chlorpromazine), Stelazine (trifluoperazine), Mellaril (thioridazine), Haldol (haloperidol), perphenazine, and fluphenazine. Haldol is especially effective for controlling violent behavioral outbursts experienced by some schizophrenic patients. While these drugs relieve many symptoms, they also have side effects. These include: sedation, dizziness upon standing up\/changing position, blurred vision, tachycardia, photosensitivity, skin rashes, menstrual problems in women, physical rigidity, muscle spasms, tremors, and restlessness. Long-term use of typical antipsychotics (which is often necessary when treating schizophrenia) routinely causes tardive dyskinesia (involuntary muscular movements), particularly in the mouth area. This can be permanent, although some patients recover from it partially or completely upon discontinuing the medication."
 },
 {
  "id": 41,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the most popular medications for treating depression, and summarize how they work chemically in the brain.",
  "answer": "Depression is associated with deficits or imbalances of some of the neurotransmitter chemicals in the brain. Antidepressants work to restore the balance of neurotransmitters such as serotonin, dopamine, and norepinephrine. These chemical messengers in the brain regulate many processes, including emotional responses, affect, and mood. The most popular antidepressant medications are classified as selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs). They prevent too much serotonin from being eliminated from the brain, which causes depression, and allow more of it to remain, which elevates mood. Examples of SSRIs include Prozac (fluoxetine), Zoloft (sertraline), Paxil (paroxetine), Celexa (citalopram), and Lexapro (escitalopram). One advantage that makes these drugs so popular is that they have fewer side effects than older antidepressant medications. Wellbutrin (bupropion) is an antidepressant that affects the neurotransmitter dopamine. It is unique among antidepressants in that it does not fit into any drug class."
 },
 {
  "id": 42,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name several “atypical” antipsychotic medications developed after Clozaril, outline their main side effects, and describe the precautions doctors must take because of these side effects.",
  "answer": "The medication Clozaril (clozapine) is quite effective for treating the symptoms of schizophrenia, especially when it is prescribed to patients whose illnesses do not respond to other medications. However, because it can cause agranulocytosis in some patients (a loss of white blood cells that fight infection), scientists developed other atypical antipsychotics that do not have this side effect. These include Risperdal (risperidone), Zyprexa (olanzapine), Seroquel (quetiapine), Geodon (ziprasidone), Abilify (aripiprazole), and Invega (paliperidone). The risk of tardive dyskinesia (involuntary movements) caused by long-term use is lower with these drugs than with typical antipsychotics. These atypical antipsychotics can change the patient’s metabolism, causing significant weight gain and increasing the risks of hypercholesterolemia and diabetes. Therefore, doctors who prescribe these drugs should order regular monitoring of the patient’s weight and regular blood work to monitor levels of blood glucose (sugar) and lipids (fats such as cholesterol and triglycerides)."
 },
 {
  "id": 43,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "y a specific interaction patients taking monoamine oxidase inhibitors (MAOIs) should be aware of. Explain the consequences of the interaction and what patients can do to minimize their risk.",
  "answer": "Monoamine oxidase inhibitors, or MAOIs, are an older form of antidepressant medication than more recently developed selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors (SSRIs) such as Prozac and serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors (SNRIs) such as Cymbalta. These two medications are popular because they cause relatively few side effects. However, for some patients, MAOIs may be the most effective medication for treating depression symptoms. An important caution regarding MAOIs is that when they are combined with the chemical tyramine the combination can cause the patient’s blood pressure to skyrocket. The sudden, drastic increase in blood pressure can result in a stroke. Tyramine is found in certain foods, such as cheese, wine, and pickles. It is also found in some medications, such as over-the-counter cold medicines and decongestants. Patients prescribed MAOIs should ask their prescribing doctors for a complete list of substances to avoid. A recently developed MAOI skin patch may also reduce some of the interaction risk."
 },
 {
  "id": 44,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the acronyms SSRI and SNRI stand for. Name some brands and summarize their actions. Describe some of the side effects of commonly prescribed antidepressants, including SSRIs, SNRIs, and tricyclic antidepressants.",
  "answer": "SSRI is the acronym for selective serotonin reuptake inhibitors. SSRIs include such popular brand names as Prozac, Paxil, and Zoloft. SNRI stands for serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitors. SNRIs are similar to SSRIs, but they preserve levels of the neurotransmitters serotonin and norepinephrine in the brain rather than just serotonin levels. SNRIs include Effexor (venlafaxine) and Cymbalta (duloxetine). Side effects of SSRIs and SNRIs include initial headaches and nausea, which usually subside within a few days; drowsiness, which usually subsides within a few weeks (if not, the dose may need to be lowered and\/or the timing of the dosage may need to be changed); agitation or nervousness; diminished sex drive; and difficulties having and enjoying sex. Tricyclic antidepressants are older medications. Their side effects include constipation, dry mouth, bladder problems, sexual problems similar to the ones sometimes experienced with SSRIs and SNRIs, drowsiness, and blurred vision, which is usually shortterm. Despite their side effects, tricyclics may be the most effective treatment for some patients."
 },
 {
  "id": 45,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some of the side effects of the medication lithium, and describe the kinds of monitoring that are indicated for patients who are prescribed lithium for bipolar disorder.",
  "answer": "Lithium is derived from a mineral that occurs naturally in the body. It is used as a mood stabilizer to alleviate the symptoms of manic and depressed moods, which are associated with bipolar disorder. While often very effective, lithium has side effects. These include excessive thirst; frequent urination; loss of motor coordination; blackouts; seizures; slurred speech; hallucinations; altered heartbeat (faster, slower, irregular, or pounding); changes in eyesight; itching; rashes; and swelling of the eyes, face, lips, tongue, throat, hands, feet, ankles, or lower legs. Doctors prescribing lithium for bipolar disorder should regularly monitor the levels of lithium in patients’ blood, as both lithium levels and requirements can fluctuate. Lithium levels in the blood can increase to the point of toxicity, but if levels are too low the lithium will not provide effective relief or control of symptoms. Doctors should also monitor their patients’ kidney and thyroid function, which can be affected by taking lithium."
 },
 {
  "id": 46,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Briefly define bipolar I disorder. Identify three of the different kinds of medications prescribed to treat bipolar disorders.",
  "answer": "In bipolar I disorder the client has a manic episode that is usually either proceeded or followed by an episode of major depression or hypomania. Manic Episode Criteria: An episode of significantly elevated, irritable, or demonstrative mood. These symptoms are present for most of the day for at least 1 wk. During the period described as manic, the patient will experience at least 3 of the following: less need for sleep, excessive talking, inflated self-esteem, easily distracted, flight of ideas, engages in activities that have negative consequences, engages in either goal directed activity\/purposeless activity. There is social impairment and the symptoms are not due to a substance. Mood stabilizers are the most common treatment choice.\n\nLithium, a chemical salt of the mineral that occurs naturally in the body, is a very effective mood stabilizer if the correct dose is determined and administered. It is also the oldest mood stabilizer. Lithium was approved by the FDA in 1970 as a treatment for both mania and depression. When lithium is ineffective, anti-seizure medications are also prescribed as mood stabilizers since they have also been found to alleviate bipolar symptoms. Some of these antiseizure medications are Depakote (valproic acid\/divalproex sodium), Tegretol (carbamazepine), Lamictal (lamotrigine), and Trileptal (oxcarbazepine). When psychotic symptoms are also present, atypical antipsychotics such as Abilify, Clozaril, Risperdal, and other brands are sometimes prescribed, often in combination with other medications."
 },
 {
  "id": 47,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the warning given by the FDA for anti-seizure medications prescribed to treat bipolar disorder.",
  "answer": "When lithium, the original choice for treating bipolar disorder, does not help some patients, doctors may prescribe anti-seizure medications. These have also been found to alleviate manic and depressive symptoms in patients with bipolar disorder. However, in some patients, these drugs may increase rather than relieve depressive symptoms. The federal Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has issued a warning for all anticonvulsants, stating that they may increase suicidal ideations and behaviors. Thus, patients with bipolar disorder who are prescribed anti-seizure drugs must be monitored closely for exacerbated symptoms of depression, suicidal thoughts or actions, or any other unexpected changes in their moods and\/or behavior. Also, patients prescribed anticonvulsants for bipolar disorder should not make any changes to their medication (dosage, etc.) until they first consult with their doctors or health care practitioners."
 },
 {
  "id": 48,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some of the side effects of the medication Depakote (valproic acid), including ones that are of particular concern to female patients.",
  "answer": "Depakote (valproic acid) is an anticonvulsant that was originally used to control seizure disorders. It was subsequently also found to be an effective treatment for the symptoms of mania and depression associated with bipolar disorder when lithium, the usual treatment of choice for bipolar disorder, was ineffective. Depakote can cause changes in weight, nausea, vomiting, stomach pain, and loss of appetite or anorexia. It can also cause damage to the liver and the pancreas. Therefore, prescribing doctors should regularly monitor patients taking Depakote. In teenage girls, Depakote can sometimes raise levels of testosterone (the primary male sex hormone), causing polycystic ovarian syndrome. This makes menstrual periods irregular and can affect fertility. These symptoms abate upon discontinuing the medication. When taken by pregnant women, Depakote can also cause birth defects, so doctors must determine whether a female patient is pregnant before prescribing it."
 },
 {
  "id": 49,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name the different types of anxiety disorders. Identify some antidepressants used to treat anxiety disorders and indicate which drugs are used to treat specific disorders.",
  "answer": "The following are types of anxiety disorders: panic disorder, separation anxiety disorder, selective mutism, agoraphobia, generalized anxiety disorder (GAD), social anxiety disorder, and specific phobias. Although antidepressants were developed to treat depression, they can also alleviate symptoms of anxiety. The SSRI (selective serotonin reuptake inhibitor) drug brands Prozac, Zoloft, Paxil, Lexapro, and Celexa are common treatments for panic disorder and social anxiety disorder. The SNRI (serotonin and norepinephrine reuptake inhibitor) drug brand Effexor is a common treatment for GAD. Wellbutrin is also sometimes prescribed for anxiety disorders. Tricyclic antidepressants that can help anxiety include Tofranil (imipramine) for panic disorder and GAD. Monoamine oxidase inhibitor (MAOI) antidepressants, including Nardil (phenelzine), Parnate (tranylcypromine), and Marplan (isocarboxazid), are also sometimes prescribed for anxiety disorders."
 },
 {
  "id": 50,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe bipolar II disorder. Explain when and how antidepressant medications are prescribed for bipolar disorder, and explain why they should never be taken on their own to treat this condition.",
  "answer": "In bipolar II disorder, the client will experience the same symptoms as the client with bipolar I disorder, with the exception of experiencing hypomanic instead of manic episodes. Hypomanic episodes last at least four days, include the same symptoms as manic episodes, but do not cause social impairment, though depression or the alteration between depression and hypomania may cause impairment or be noticeable by others.\n\nBipolar disorders are characterized by alternating episodes of mania (or hypomania) and depression. Doctors sometimes prescribe antidepressant drugs for the depressive symptoms. Prozac, Paxil, and Zoloft are popular choices. However, because depression is not the only symptom of bipolar disorder, patients with this condition should never take an antidepressant by itself. This type of medication can stop the depression, but it may throw the patient into a manic state quite suddenly. This can be dangerous. Doctors usually prescribe an antidepressant along with a mood stabilizer (such as lithium) or one of the many antipsychotic medications available. It should be noted that, according to the National Institute of Mental Health (NIMH), research results regarding whether antidepressants are truly helpful for the depressive symptoms associated with bipolar disorder are mixed. Some studies, including one funded by the NIMH, have found them ineffective, even when they were used in combination with mood stabilizers."
 },
 {
  "id": 51,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the most common side effects of benzodiazepines, BuSpar, and beta blockers prescribed to treat anxiety disorders. Describe how these are usually given and discontinued, and explain the reasons why.",
  "answer": "The most frequent side effects of the benzodiazepines (Klonopin, Ativan, Xanax, etc.) are sleepiness and dizziness. They can also cause blurred vision, upset stomach, headaches, confusion, grogginess, and nightmares. BuSpar (buspirone) can cause side effects such as dizziness, headaches, nausea, lightheadedness, nervousness, excitement, and difficulty sleeping. The most frequent side effects caused by beta blockers are dizziness, fatigue, weakness, and cold hands. Additionally, beta blockers are not usually indicated for patients who have asthma or diabetes, as these drugs can make the symptoms of both of these diseases worse. These anti-anxiety drugs are usually given for short courses because patients can develop a tolerance to their effects and form a dependency on them. To discontinue these medications, their use is tapered off slowly and gradually. Sudden cessation can cause patients to have withdrawal symptoms and\/or recurring symptoms of anxiety."
 },
 {
  "id": 52,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some anti-anxiety drugs and other medications prescribed to treat anxiety disorders, and indicate which drugs are used to treat specific disorders.",
  "answer": "One class of drugs prescribed to relieve symptoms of anxiety is the benzodiazepines, known as anxiolytics or anti-anxiety medications. They tend to begin working more quickly than antidepressants that are used to treat anxiety disorders. The benzodiazepines include Klonopin (clonazepam), which is also an anti-seizure drug that is prescribed for generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) and social anxiety disorder; Ativan (lorazepam), which is also prescribed to some psychotic patients and is used to treat panic disorders; and Xanax (alprazolam), which is prescribed for panic disorders and GAD. In addition to benzodiazepines, the drug BuSpar (buspirone) is another anti-anxiety drug prescribed for GAD. It does not begin working as quickly as the\n\nbenzodiazepines; the effects will not be noticeable for at least two weeks.\n\nAnother type of drug, beta blockers such as Inderal (propranolol) that are used to treat glaucoma, migraines, hypertension, angina, arrhythmias, and other cardiovascular conditions, are also prescribed to relieve some physical symptoms of anxiety, including sweating and trembling. They can also be used to treat anxietyrelated physical problems, such as giving speeches or attending meetings for patients with social anxiety disorder."
 },
 {
  "id": 53,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the most common side effects of stimulant medications prescribed for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD). Outline some solutions for certain side effects.",
  "answer": "Stimulants such as Ritalin, Dexedrine, and Adderall are prescribed to help individuals with ADHD focus their attention better and sustain it longer, which enables them to learn and work more effectively. Most of the side effects of stimulants are minor, and most go away when the drug dose is reduced. The most common side effects are loss of appetite, which usually improves as each dose wears off; headaches; stomach aches; and difficulty sleeping. When patients cannot sleep, prescribing doctors may lower the dose, may advise taking the medication earlier in the day, or may discontinue the evening or afternoon dose. To help patients sleep when taking stimulants for ADHD, doctors may occasionally also prescribe a low dose of an antidepressant, or of clonidine, a medication used to lower high blood pressure. Less commonly, some children taking stimulants can develop tics (repetitive, involuntary movements or sounds). Changing the dose may resolve this problem. Some children may also develop “flat” (emotionless) affects. Parents should consult the prescribing doctor if they observe these side effects."
 },
 {
  "id": 54,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Name the most common medications prescribed for attention deficit hyperactivity disorder (ADHD).",
  "answer": "Both children and adults can suffer from ADHD. The common drug treatment for this disorder is stimulant medications. This is not because patients with ADHD are sleepy. Rather, they have difficulty focusing their attention on one thing at a time, concentrating, and sustaining their attention for a prolonged period of time. When ADHD sufferers are required to do complex, sequential mental tasks, such as reading and other similar activities, their brains slow down and brain activity is unfocused. In contrast, neurotypical brains show stronger, more focused activity during such tasks. Also, whenever we are stimulated—by drinking coffee or engaging in any stimulating activity—our subjective sense of time speeds up and our focus of attention narrows. Stimulant drugs have the same effects, and are therefore exactly what ADHD patients need. These stimulants include Adderall (amphetamine); Ritalin, Concerta, Metadate, or Daytrana (methylphenidates); and Dexedrine or Dextrostat (dextroamphetamines)."
 },
 {
  "id": 55,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the initials CT stand for. Describe what CT scans can detect and how they are conducted.",
  "answer": "CT stands for computed tomography. It is a painless, non-invasive procedure that quickly creates two-dimensional images of a patient’s tissues, bones, and organs. CTs scans are used in neurological examinations to image the brain and the spine. They can detect abnormalities in the blood vessels and bones, certain cysts and\/or tumors in the brain, encephalitis, epilepsy, intracranial bleeding and\/or blood clots secondary to strokes, brain damage caused by head injuries, spinal stenosis, and herniated disks. Because many neurological conditions can produce the same symptoms, CT scans are useful for localizing and correctly diagnosing problems. During a CT scan, the patient lies still in a narrow chamber. X-rays pass through his or her head (for neurological imaging) at various angles, and are detected by a computerized scanner. The data are converted to cross-sectional “slices” of brain images. Sometimes, contrast dye is injected into the bloodstream to give highlighted views of various brain tissues."
 },
 {
  "id": 56,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Employing the principles of behavioral genetics, use the example of alcoholism to describe how genetic and environmental factors can interact. Explain how this informs understanding of the disease.",
  "answer": "While some traits such as eye color have clear genetic sources and some behaviors are obviously learned, the majority of human behaviors are the result of interactions between biological and environmental factors. For example, there are genetic markers associated with increased susceptibility to the disease of alcoholism, which people can inherit. However, this does not mean an individual will always develop alcoholism. Rather, it predisposes someone to becoming addicted in the event that he or she uses alcohol. In one real-world example, only 1 of 11 siblings whose father had alcoholism also developed it. However, the other 10 avoided drinking. Therefore, any number of them could have inherited the father’s genetic vulnerability to alcoholism, but it was not expressed since they avoided drinking behaviors (environmental triggers of the disease). Awareness of genetic predisposition can help people avoid contributing behaviors. It can also inform individuals in advance that they cannot “take or leave” drinking as others can, but can easily become addicted from “normal”\/“social” drinking."
 },
 {
  "id": 57,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the initials MRI stand for, and describe how MRIs are used to conduct neurological testing.",
  "answer": "MRI stands for magnetic resonance imaging. It produces detailed images of tissues, bones, organs, and nerves without using radiation. In neurological testing, an MRI is used to diagnose tumors of the brain and spinal cord, eye diseases, inflammation, infections, vascular conditions that can result in strokes, degenerative disorders such as multiple sclerosis, and traumatic brain injuries. A huge cylindrical magnet surrounds a hollow tube. The patient must lie very still inside this tube during testing. Patients with metal hardware in their bodies and\/or implants such as pacemakers cannot have MRIs. The machine produces a strong magnetic field that realigns the tissues’ water molecules. It then sends radio waves through the body to detect the molecules’ return to random alignment. Resonance signals from various angles are computer processed into either three-dimensional images or two-dimensional “slices,” differentiating among soft tissue, bone, and fluid. For claustrophobic or obese patients, open MRI is available, but cannot replicate all tests or the image quality of standard MRI testing."
 },
 {
  "id": 58,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the initials EEG stand for. Explain what EEG is used for and how it is conducted.",
  "answer": "EEG stands for electroencephalography, which is an electrical method of monitoring brain activity through the skull. It helps doctors diagnose brain tumors, traumatic brain injuries, brain inflammation, certain seizure disorders, certain psychiatric disorders, and degenerative and metabolic disorders that have neurological effects. It is also useful for evaluating sleep disorders, monitoring brain activity in unconscious or anesthetized patients, and confirming brain death. A small electric current is sent through electrodes attached to the scalp, which then carry the brainwaves’ electrical energy to the machine, which reads it. At this point, a baseline reading is obtained. Patients are then asked to open and close their eyes and\/or change their breathing patterns. Additionally, they may be exposed to stimuli such as noise, specific drugs, and bright\/flashing lights while the machine records brainwave changes. Sometimes, electrodes are inserted into the brain through a surgical hole in the skull to eliminate bone interference and obtain more information about brainwave activity. EEGs can be done during sleep. These are necessary to evaluate some disorders, and take three times longer than EEGs done while the patient is awake."
 },
 {
  "id": 59,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize some examples of neuropsychological applications of fMRI that have been used successfully and\/or show promise for future use. Include an overview of currently accepted uses.",
  "answer": "Functional magnetic resonance imaging, or fMRI, is an accepted test for evaluating neurological damage and dysfunction and monitoring degenerative neurological conditions. Because it yields real-time images of blood flow to different brain areas, fMRI has also been applied to psychological research and therapy. For example, neuropsychologists found that some soldiers were more likely to discharge their weapons at black than white individuals. They gave behavioral training to voluntary subjects, measuring their neural activity before and after training. Psychological pretest and post-test results showed the soldiers’ responses were less racially differentiated after training. The researchers found through fMRI that neural plasticity allowed subjects’ brains to be “rewired” through behavioral training. Researchers have used fMRI to study the functional neuroanatomy and affective components of moral judgment. Some have found clear, lateralized activity in areas more strongly associated with motivation and reward than with sex drive in the brains of those in the early stages of romantic love. Finally, some feel fMRI could potentially be used for lie detection."
 },
 {
  "id": 60,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the initials fMRI stand for. Describe the imaging capabilities an fMRI machine has that an original MRI machine does not.",
  "answer": "The initials fMRI stand for functional magnetic resonance imaging. The original MRI uses a strong magnetic field instead of radiation to produce detailed pictures of organs, nerves, tissues, and bones. In addition to this, fMRI uses the magnetic properties of the patient’s blood to create real-time pictures of blood flow to specific regions in the brain. The areas of the brain that become more active and the duration of this increased activity can both be pinpointed by using fMRI scans. An fMRI can also determine whether activity in certain brain regions takes place simultaneously or in sequence. Neurological damage from head injuries or degenerative disorders such as Alzheimer’s or Parkinson’s disease can be assessed using fMRI. Brain tumors, strokes, multiple sclerosis, and other neurological disorders can also be diagnosed and\/or monitored through fMRI. Neuropsychologists are also using fMRI to track brain activity accompanying specific cognitive processes and affective states, and to identify neurological changes (“rewiring”) following behavioral training to modify certain mental and behavioral responses."
 },
 {
  "id": 61,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the acronym SPECT stands for, and describe how SPECT is used to conduct neurological testing.",
  "answer": "SPECT stands for single photon emission computed tomography. It uses nuclear imaging of blood flow to tissue to assess certain neurological functions. In the diagnosis of brain tumors, degenerative diseases, and infections, SPECT may be ordered as a follow-up to an MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) scan. Test practitioners inject a radioactive isotope into the patient’s bloodstream, which is also done during a PET (positron emission tomography) scan. The isotope binds to chemicals that flow to the brain. Brain areas with increased blood flow accumulate more of the isotope. A camera that detects gamma rays revolves around the patient’s head, recording the sites in the brain that are receiving more blood flow. The SPECT computer converts these data into “slice” images, and then stacks them up, achieving a detailed, three-dimensional picture of blood flow and brain activity."
 },
 {
  "id": 62,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what the acronym PET stands for. Describe how PET is used to conduct neurological testing.",
  "answer": "PET stands for positron emission tomography. PET brain scans have several neurological applications, including identifying and\/or highlighting diseased tissue or tumors, revealing blood flow in the brain, measuring cell and\/or tissue metabolism, evaluating patients with certain memory disorders, evaluating patients with seizure disorders that have been unresponsive to medication, ascertaining neurological changes after drug abuse or injuries, and others. The information obtained from CT (computed tomography) or MRI (magnetic resonance imaging) scans used to identify affected brain areas can be enhanced with the additional data obtained through follow-up PET scans. In PET scanning, a low-level radioactive isotope is injected into the patient’s bloodstream. As the patient’s brain performs various activities, the isotope’s concentrations in the tissues are traced via overhead sensors that detect gamma rays. A computer processes these data and displays and records two- and three-dimensional images. More than one neural function can be followed at the same time by injecting different isotope compounds."
 },
 {
  "id": 63,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe how thermography is used in neurological testing, and discuss its safety and applications.",
  "answer": "Thermography is safe—it does not use any radiation and is non-invasive. It is also called digital thermal infrared imaging. It uses sensors of infrared light, the lowest-frequency light waves. These are also used for photography\/video in night time and other dark settings. Neurologically, thermography is used to identify soft tissue injuries, vascular (blood vessel related) diseases of the head and neck, and neuromusculoskeletal disorders. It is also used to confirm or rule out compression of nerve roots. Infrared light recorders take thousands of pictures of the patient from five to eight feet away. These are converted to electrical signals, which are used by a computer to produce two-dimensional images. These images show areas that are hotter or colder than normal in different colors or different shades of black, white, and gray. Thermography can show small temperature differences between sides of the brain and\/or body, and\/or within specific organs."
 },
 {
  "id": 64,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what evoked potentials measure and how they are used in neurological examinations. Include a brief discussion of the use of visual, auditory, and somatosensory evoked potentials.",
  "answer": "Evoked potentials measure electrical signals sent to the brain as a result of sight, hearing, or touch. In addition to testing vision and hearing in infants and the profoundly developmentally disabled, confirming brain death, and monitoring brain activity in comatose patients, evoked potentials are used in neurological testing to confirm such conditions as multiple sclerosis, spinal cord injuries, brain tumors, and acoustic neuromas (inner ear tumors), and to evaluate problems with the sensory nerves. One set of needle electrodes attached to the patient’s scalp tests electrophysiological responses to stimuli. Another set is attached to the body part being tested. The time it takes for stimuli-generated impulses to reach the brain (which normally occurs instantly) is measured. Auditory evoked potentials test for sensorineural hearing loss, acoustic neuromas, acoustic nerve damage, and auditory pathway damage in the brainstem. Visual evoked potentials detect optic nerve damage, especially from multiple sclerosis. Somatosensory evoked potentials detect nerve damage or degeneration caused by progressive diseases."
 },
 {
  "id": 65,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "State what polysomnograms are used for, the procedures involved, and the specific conditions that can be diagnosed with polysomnograms.",
  "answer": "Polysomnograms are electrical measurements of the body’s and the brain’s activities during sleep. Sleep centers use them when conducting sleep studies. Over one or more nights, electrodes taped to the patient’s scalp, eyelids, and\/or chin record the patient’s brain waves, eye movements, breathing, activity of the leg and skeletal muscles, blood pressure, and heart rate. Video recordings of the sleeping patient may also be taken to document visible body movements. The findings from polysomnograms are helpful in diagnosing various sleep disorders because they can detect patterns of symptoms consistent with specific disorders in the patient. These sleep disorders include insomnia, obstructive sleep apnea (a breathing disorder wherein the patient stops breathing during sleep), restless leg syndrome, and periodic limb movement disorder. Polysomnograms do not use radiation, and are safe, non-invasive, and painless."
 },
 {
  "id": 66,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the use of ultrasound imaging in neurological testing, and discuss its safety and applications.",
  "answer": "Ultrasound imaging is safe and painless—it does not use any radiation and is non-invasive. Neurosonography, or ultrasound imaging of the brain and spinal column, analyzes blood flow in the brain. It is used to diagnose brain tumors, strokes, vascular (blood vessel) conditions, and hydrocephalus (wherein cerebrospinal fluid backs up and accumulates in the brain). It is also used to confirm or rule out inflammatory processes as causes of pain. It images soft tissue masses and any tears in them more effectively than Xrays, and does this without radiation. Transcranial Doppler is a specialized type of ultrasound used to image blood vessels in the neck to assess blood flow and the risk of a stroke. With the help of a lubricant gel, a transducer that sends and receives high-frequency sound waves is passed over the indicated area. A computer records the echoes of the sound waves and displays them as a real-time visual image of the tissue(s) and\/or structure(s) being tested."
 },
 {
  "id": 67,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some of the effects of chronic stress on health. Identify the reasons why individuals vary in terms of the illnesses they develop, and discuss some ways to prevent these illnesses.",
  "answer": "When psychological, emotional, and\/or physiological stressors are excessive and prolonged, the body is in a frequent, even constant, state of “fight or flight.” This response, originally developed for temporary, emergency situations, is not meant to exist continually for long durations. It elevates stress hormones and heart rate, and depresses pain sensitivity and immune response. When these effects recur too often and\/or continue for too long, our defenses against illness are compromised. Some people can withstand great stress without getting sick; others become ill with fewer, less severe stressors. This is because an individual’s ability to cope with stress matters more than the individual’s stress level. Some ways to avoid stress-related illnesses include pursuing enjoyable, fun leisure activities; practicing meditation; undergoing hypnosis; using biofeedback to control physical responses; undergoing behavior modification to decrease stress reactions and learn more effective coping behaviors; and taking part in cognitive therapy or rational-emotive behavior therapy to change counterproductive thought patterns, emotions, and behaviors."
 },
 {
  "id": 68,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how chronic stress affects the human immune system.",
  "answer": "The basic human stress response saved lives in prehistoric times, when imminent physical danger from wild animals, other humans, and environmental events was common. The “fight or flight” response induces a rush of adrenaline and an increase in cortisol. These are both stress-related hormones. This response provides a sudden burst of energy that would allow a person to run fast to escape a threat. The heart rate also increases, pumping blood to the muscles to help the individual fight or run. There is also a temporarily lowered sense of pain during the emergency. Nonessential body functions such as digestion are shut down. The immune system, which is not needed during a fight-or-flight emergency, is weakened. In modern society, we experience far fewer physical emergencies but encounter many more sources of chronic psychological and physical stress. When stress is ongoing, not temporary, it undermines the immune system. Over the short term, susceptibility to colds, the flu, and other illnesses increases. Over the long term, cardiovascular disease, allergies, hives\/rashes, asthma, constipation\/diarrhea, diabetes, and cancer can result."
 },
 {
  "id": 69,
  "topic": "Biological Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize some research findings about neurological activity that occurs in response to stress.",
  "answer": "Psychological researchers have found correlations between having greater psychosocial resources and showing fewer adverse psychological and biological reactions to stress. Neuropsychology researchers are interested in the hormonal and brain activity changes that might accompany such reactions to stress, and in how those changes differ among individuals with greater and lesser psychosocial resources. Some researchers have discovered that, as they hypothesized, people with greater psychosocial resources showed significantly lower cortisol reactivity. Cortisol is a hormone associated with the stress reaction following a stressful task. Functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) of study participants’ brains also showed increased activity in the right ventrolateral prefrontal cortex, which is associated with anxiety and vigilance for threats; and decreased activity in the amygdala, which plays a key role in processing emotional responses during threat regulation tasks. This decreased amygdala activity was not found during threat sensitivity tasks. Researchers believe that greater psychosocial resources reduce cortisol activation by improving the inhibition of threat responses during threat regulation tasks, not by decreasing actual threat sensitivity."
 },
 {
  "id": 70,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the processes of inflammation caused by chronic stress and explain what stress addiction is. Describe how exercise can address these issues.",
  "answer": "The chemical stress response is meant to occur temporarily in dangerous situations. When people experience chronic stress, their levels of the stress hormones adrenaline and cortisol are constantly elevated, triggering inflammatory reactions in the body. Inflammation is responsible for many autoimmune and other diseases, including cardiovascular disease, digestive diseases, fatigue, depression, and other conditions. Moreover, some people who experience repeated rushes of adrenaline get used to the “high” and crave it, perpetuating the stress response. At the same time, these individuals develop a tolerance for adrenaline surges, just as drug abusers develop tolerances, so they need increasing amounts of the chemical each time to experience its effects. When the adrenaline subsides, stress addicts “crash” just as other drug addicts do, continuing the cycle. Exercise helps by stimulating the production of endorphins, the body’s natural painkillers; replacing unpleasant moods\/feelings with pleasant ones; dissipating excess stress hormones; relieving anxiety; enhancing mental focus; and boosting one’s sense of empowerment."
 },
 {
  "id": 71,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the cognitive process of attention. Describe an advantage and a disadvantage of selective attention.",
  "answer": "Attention is a prerequisite for most other cognitive processes. We have to attend to an environmental stimulus before we can respond to it. Attention is defined as the cognitive process of selectively concentrating our consciousness on some aspects of the environment while ignoring others. One example of an advantage of selective attention is what is termed the “cocktail party effect.” This is the ability to attend to one person’s voice in a full room. We “tune out” the other voices, which enables us to have a conversation. An example of a disadvantage of selective attention is when motorists attend more to a conversation with their passenger(s) or to someone on the phone (even if it is hands-free) than to the surrounding traffic and the task of safely navigating it. The motorist may end up getting in an automobile accident as a result."
 },
 {
  "id": 72,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Differentially define human sensation and perception as elements of cognition.",
  "answer": "Humans do not think in a vacuum, but are influenced by external environmental stimuli and our responses to them. Sensation is the way we receive information from our environment through our senses of vision, hearing, touch, smell, and taste. This information is collected by our eyes, ears, skin, noses, and tongues, and is sent via the various nerves in these sense organs to the brain. Sensations alone would have no meaning or use to us if we didn’t interpret them. We would feel sensations, but not understand we were sensing anything without perception—the brain’s interpretation of sensation. Data sent from sensory organs by the associated nerves are analyzed by the brain, which then identifies the data as images, sounds, touches, odors, or tastes. It further classifies them as familiar\/novel, pleasant\/unpleasant, etc. As an element of cognition, the brain uses its perceptions of sensations to make sense of external stimuli, understand environmental events, and decide how to respond to them."
 },
 {
  "id": 73,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the load theory regarding selective attention. Include a discussion of relevant findings related to the stage of adulthood an individual is in.",
  "answer": "Load theory refers to the information processing theory of cognition. Specifically, it states that the load of information one’s brain needs to process affects attention differentially. Load theory posits that attention involves both perceptual and cognitive mechanisms. The perceptual mechanism is affected by one’s ability to perceive or ignore task-related and task-unrelated stimuli. Research finds that when many stimuli exist, it is easier to ignore the irrelevant ones. When fewer total stimuli exist, the individual will perceive both relevant and irrelevant ones. The cognitive mechanism involves one’s ability to process the stimuli perceived. Research studies have found that our ability to process stimuli declines with advancing age. However, research also finds that while younger people can perceive and fully process more stimuli, they are likely to process both relevant and irrelevant information. In addition, although older people can process fewer stimuli, they are more likely to process only the relevant ones."
 },
 {
  "id": 74,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define executive attention and summarize its development over the human lifespan.",
  "answer": "Executive attention, or executive function, is a set of higher-order cognitive processes used to solve problems; make decisions; and control our thoughts, emotions, and behaviors. Executive attention begins to develop in early childhood, typically around the age of 18 months, and continues to develop as we grow to adulthood. Research finds that the most significant changes in the development of executive function seem to take place around the age of three years. The ability to resolve conflicts is related to executive attention. Babies have very little of this ability; it develops along with other progressive abilities, such as reaching for something they want. Individual differences in executive function development contribute to individual differences in emotional control and behavior. Resolving larger conflicts requires higher attention levels, which are enabled by the contextually sensitive learning of sequences. Less developed executive attention makes this larger conflict resolution difficult for children but easier for adults, whose executive attention is more developed."
 },
 {
  "id": 75,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss the processes of habituation and sensitization as nonassociative types of learning, including examples of each.",
  "answer": "Learning that involves associating a stimulus and response with another stimulus is associative learning. Examples include classical and operant conditioning. Non-associative learning does not rely on this association. Two simple types of non-associative learning are habituation and sensitization. In habituation, the response to a stimulus diminishes with repeated exposure. For example, you might be sitting in a classroom where an overhead light fixture is always buzzing. Initially, you might find the noise distracting and annoying, but the longer you are exposed to it, you more you get used to it and the less you notice it. You may even stop noticing it completely after a while. Habituation occurs in all animals (even protozoa), and occurs as a response to both desirable and undesirable stimuli. Conversely, sensitization is an increased response to a stimulus with repeated exposure.\n\nFor example, if you keep rubbing your skin in the same spot, it will start to hurt. As another example, scratching the same place repeatedly can make it itch more. These responses result from stimulating peripheral nerves, magnifying their synapses. Adaptive and maladaptive learning may both involve sensitization."
 },
 {
  "id": 76,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize a popular, widely used, hierarchical, clinical model of attention. State how its levels were determined and give a brief definition of each level: focused, sustained, selective, alternating, and divided attention.",
  "answer": "A widely used clinical (not investigational) model of attention establishes a hierarchy of types of attention that are progressively more challenging. The authors of this model determined these levels based on the recoveries of patients with neurological damage from comas. These patients recovered each type of attentional ability in sequence, demonstrating their degrees of difficulty. Focused attention is the ability to respond separately to specific sensory stimuli. Sustained attention, or vigilance, is the ability to engage in continuous, repeating activity with a sustained, consistent behavioral response. Selective attention is the ability to avoid being distracted by competing stimuli, focus on the selected stimulus\/stimuli set, and sustain a cognitive or behavioral response set. Alternating attention is the ability to alternate attentional focus between\/among tasks with differing cognitive demands. Divided attention is the ability to respond to multiple demands or tasks at the same time (“multitasking”), and is the highest level of attention."
 },
 {
  "id": 77,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize John B. Watson’s “Little Albert” experiment and describe why it is an example of classical conditioning. Include an overview of what it added to Pavlov’s work with conditioning reflexive responses.",
  "answer": "John Watson, one of the pioneers of modern behavioral psychology, described a young child he called “Little Albert.” The child enjoyed petting a soft white rabbit. However, when he was suddenly frightened by a very loud noise while petting the rabbit, he was traumatized. Thereafter, he developed a phobia—an abnormal fear not just of rabbits, but of anything with white hair, even a Santa Claus beard. This later came to be called stimulus generalization by behaviorists. Ivan Pavlov’s earlier work in classical conditioning involved training that caused reflexive responses to occur on presentation of a stimulus that was not previously associated with those responses. Pavlov did this by repeatedly pairing the original, unconditioned stimulus and its natural, unconditioned response with a neutral, unrelated stimulus. Eventually, the unrelated stimulus produced the reflex without the original stimulus, becoming a conditioned stimulus producing a conditioned response. With Little Albert, Watson showed that classical conditioning applies not just to reflexes, but also to the learning of emotions."
 },
 {
  "id": 78,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the process of learning known as classical conditioning, and provide some examples.",
  "answer": "Classical conditioning involves learning to associate a stimulus and the normal response to it with another, previously unrelated stimulus. A “classic” example is Ivan Pavlov’s experiments with dogs, whereby he formulated the classical conditioning model. Dogs reflexively salivate when meat powder is placed in their mouths, but do not normally salivate when they hear a bell ring. Pavlov gave meat powder to his dog subjects, simultaneously ringing a bell. After pairing the meat powder and the bell many times, Pavlov rang the bell by itself; the dogs salivated without being given the meat powder. He termed the meat powder the unconditioned stimulus and salivation the unconditioned response. Initially a neutral stimulus, the bell became a conditioned stimulus, and salivation became a conditioned response to the bell. The same experiments have been replicated with humans. For example, experimenters can shine a light near a person, making the pupils of their eyes contract, and pair this with saying the word “contract.” After repetition, the person’s pupils will contract just from hearing the word. The individual does not need to be exposed to the light."
 },
 {
  "id": 79,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the learning process of imprinting, and provide some examples related to both animals and humans.",
  "answer": "Psychologists and ethologists define imprinting as a rapid learning process that is independent of behavioral consequences and occurs only during a critical or sensitive period. This period may be when the learner reaches a certain age or developmental stage. Amateur biologist Douglas Spalding first reported filial imprinting in chickens in the 19 th century. The ethologist Oskar Heinroth rediscovered it. Heinroth’s student, Konrad Lorenz, was most famous for popularizing the filial imprinting concept. Lorenz found that graylag geese imprinted on the first thing they saw after hatchingtypically their mother. This was a protective evolutionary adaptation. He then found that goslings hatched from incubators imprinted on him (or his boots) since he was the first thing they saw. Appealing photographs of Lorenz trailed by a single file of baby geese as he walked have become well-known. Imprinting in humans takes place even before birth, as fetuses learn to recognize their parents’ voices in the womb. This process continues after birth as babies learn to identify their parents through visual and other means."
 },
 {
  "id": 80,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the basic principles of operant conditioning, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Operant conditioning is a type of associative learning wherein the antecedents (what happens immediately before a stimulus is presented) and consequences (what happens immediately after stimulus presentation) are manipulated to affect response probability. Certain antecedent conditions are more likely to elicit certain responses; others are more likely to prevent them. Certain consequences for a behavioral response increase the probability that the behavior will recur. These consequences are called reinforcement because they increase the chances of repetition. Other consequences decrease the probability that a behavior will recur. These consequences are called punishment since they weaken the chances of repetition. For example, if an animal receives food every time it presses a lever, the animal will repeat this behavior to obtain more food. If a human receives money for doing a job, the human will repeat this work behavior to obtain more money."
 },
 {
  "id": 81,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the basic assumptions about learning that inform behavioral, cognitive, and social learning theories. Identify some psychologists whose work influenced Albert Bandura’s social learning theory. Identify and define the four requirements proposed by Albert Bandura for the social learning of behavior.",
  "answer": "Behavioral learning theory assumes that our behaviors are determined by environmental stimuli. Cognitive learning theory assumes that psychological factors influence our behaviors. Social learning assumes that a combination of environmental and psychological influences is responsible for our behavior. In developing his social learning theory, Albert Bandura was influenced by early (1941) research by Miller and Dollard into social learning and imitation, by Julian Rotter’s behavioral theory of social learning, and by Lev Vygotsky’s theory of cultural-historical psychology. Bandura proposed that to learn behaviors by emulating models, four things are required: (1) attention (the learner must first pay attention to the model); (2) retention (the learner must remember the observed behavior); (3) motor reproduction (the learner must have the physical ability and motor skills to reproduce the observed behavior, which may not be possible for young children and\/or those with disabilities); and (4) motivation (the learner must want to demonstrate the observed and learned behavior)."
 },
 {
  "id": 82,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss the principles of observational learning, provide some examples of this type of learning, and summarize the work of Albert Bandura.",
  "answer": "Animals are born with instincts, but they still learn skills by observing and imitating their parents. For example, cats, as predators, are born with the instinct to hunt, but only learn to hunt efficiently enough to survive through parental teaching. Humans are even more likely to learn through imitation. Assuming sufficient cognitive and motor skills development, children learn from adults and older children how to do things such as tie shoes, ascend and descend stairs, and perform the steps of a dance. Albert Bandura, a pioneer of social learning theory, demonstrated that children do not need to have their own behaviors directly rewarded or punished (according to behavioral principles) to learn. In his experiments, he found that children could observe another child’s behavior being rewarded or punished and learn through this observation to demonstrate behaviors they saw rewarded and avoid behaviors they saw punished. Moreover, Bandura proved that the behavior of children became more aggressive as the amount of violence they viewed in videos increased."
 },
 {
  "id": 83,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify and define Bloom’s three domains of learning. Give an example of learning that incorporates all three domains.",
  "answer": "Dr. Benjamin S. Bloom formulated Bloom’s Taxonomy of educational objectives, which is very popular in education and educational psychology. Bloom posited three domains of learning: cognitive, psychomotor, and affective. The cognitive domain involves learning processes such as calculating, analyzing, remembering, discussing, and problem solving. The psychomotor domain involves learning processes such as swimming, diving, dancing, riding a bicycle, and driving a car. The affective domain involves learning processes such as appreciating, liking, loving, hating, fearing, and worshiping things, ideas, and\/or people. These domains are not separate or exclusive. For example, a person who learns to play baseball uses the psychomotor domain to learn to pitch, catch, bat, field, and run. He or she uses the cognitive domain to learn and follow the rules of the game. Finally, he or she uses the affective domain when learning to love the sport, appreciate the history of baseball, and value the ways in which baseball applies and\/or relates to life."
 },
 {
  "id": 84,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss the role of play in animal and human learning. Provide an overview of two psychological theories that address the role of play in learning.",
  "answer": "A number of psychologists regard play as the earliest kind of learning. Many animals play, especially when young, which supports theories regarding the role of play in learning. Kittens’ play develops their hunting skills. Predators, such as orcas that catch seals and cats that catch rodents or birds, play with their prey. This is notable because playing expends energy, delays eating, and increases vulnerability, so its function must be valuable enough to be worth these costs. Regarding humans, Lev Vygotsky, the founder of cultural-historical psychology, found that play is essential to child development since children use play to make sense out of their environment. In formulating his theory of cognitive development, Jean Piaget observed young children at play and described them as little scientists interacting and experimenting with their environment. By trying out various actions, young children discover what happens, thereby learning the rules of the environment and how to interact with it."
 },
 {
  "id": 85,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the basic points of the multi-store model of memory (Atkinson-Schiffrin, 1968), including examples of each memory type.",
  "answer": "The multi-store memory model proposes that we have three types of memory: sensory memory, short-term memory, and long-term memory. Basically, sensory memory (also previously known as sensory register) lasts less than a second. It represents our immediate attention to a stimulus. If you are reading and hear a sudden loud noise outside, the time that passes while you notice this sound represents sensory memory. Its rapid decay cannot be changed through rehearsal. Short-term memory lasts from several seconds to a minute, but can be prolonged somewhat through rehearsal. When you remember or rehearse a phone number just until you can dial it, this is short-term memory. The number of items we can hold in short-term memory is limited, but can be increased somewhat by “chunking.” This involves grouping digits or letters in threes or fours, and can be done with phone numbers. Long-term memory, unlike the first two types, has virtually unlimited storage capacity and duration. With memorization, information is consolidated from short-term to long-term memory. This is the type of memory at work when we recognize familiar things, people, and places."
 },
 {
  "id": 86,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define incidental and tangential learning, and give examples of each.",
  "answer": "Incidental learning occurs when we happen to learn things that are included in another subject we are studying. The information learned through incidental learning is in addition to the information explicitly being taught. This type of learning occurs frequently, and enriches our knowledge. For example, a child who hates arithmetic but loves baseball may be able to learn arithmetic concepts easier by learning baseball statistics such as runs, outs, innings, double and triple plays, RBIs, etc. As another example, someone who has never studied a foreign language and takes ballet classes is going to pick up some French vocabulary words since all ballet steps have French names. They will also likely learn the general meaning of these words. Tangential learning is the self-education of learners after they are exposed to a topic or subject in a context they enjoy. For example, someone who plays Guitar Hero may be inspired to learn to play a real guitar. Someone who sees a movie based on a book may be inspired to read that book if they have not already done so."
 },
 {
  "id": 87,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the definition of the level-of-processing effect theory regarding memory. Identify four elements related to this theory that have been shown through various research studies to influence information recall.",
  "answer": "By depicting the strength of memory as relative and variable, the level-ofprocessing effect theory (Craik and Lockhart, 1972) opposes the multi-store theory of memory (Atkinson-Schiffrin, 1968). This theory proposes that it is not rehearsal that influences how experiences are saved in memory, but rather the depth and method of processing. Studies by various researchers have shown that the following elements influence information recall: (1) organization (people who organize information into more categories recall more of it); (2) distinctiveness (distinctive methods, such as spelling words aloud, enable better recall than just reading them from a list); (3) effort (people performing problem solving tasks such as unscrambling anagrams recall the more difficult ones better than the easier ones, presumably because they had to make more effort to solve the harder ones; and (4) elaboration (people given short paragraphs to read and longer paragraphs with the same information as the short ones plus additional sentences elaborating on the main point recalled the longer, elaborated paragraphs better than the shorter ones)."
 },
 {
  "id": 88,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how the model of working memory (Baddeley and Hitch, 1974 and 2000) is related to the model of short-term memory. Identify and describe the four components of working memory.",
  "answer": "The working memory model was formulated to replace the general model of short-term memory, one of the three main types of memory. The other two are sensory and long-term memory. The model of working memory consists of four components. The first is the central executive, which attends to information and routes it to one of the other three parts. The second is the phonological loop, which temporarily stores auditory information through mental rehearsal. An example is silently repeating a phone number continuously until you dial it. The third is the visuospatial sketchpad, which stores and manipulates visual information (such as the number of utility poles within a certain distance) and spatial information (such as the distance of an area as judged by the observer). The fourth is the multimodal episodic buffer, which connects information across visual, auditory, and spatial modalities. It is involved in chronological sequencing. This is the component of memory used when an individual recalls a book or movie. The episodic buffer is belie ved to be connected with semantic meanings and long-term memory. This model explains why doing visual and auditory tasks concurrently is easier than doing two visual or two auditory tasks simultaneously."
 },
 {
  "id": 89,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the classification of memory by information type (Anderson, 1976). Include the names for the two main types and several of the subtypes.",
  "answer": "Anderson divided memories into two main groups: declarative or explicit memory and procedural or implicit memory. Declarative memory requires conscious recall. Some subtypes include semantic memory, for abstract knowledge of facts, regardless of their context; episodic memory, for personal experiences (sensations, perceptions, emotions, associations, etc.) specific to a certain context, such as a time and\/or place; autobiographical memory, for events in one’s own life (considered either the same as or a subset of episodic memory); and visual memory, which uses mental imagery. Procedural memory does not require conscious recall. It is used in motor learning, and is governed by the cerebellum and basal ganglia. Improvement in a task through repetition alone, without any new explicit memory formation, is another example of this unconscious or implicit type of learning and remembering. Additionally, topographic memory involves spatial self-orientation, place recognition, and following itineraries. Alzheimer’s disease patients who get disoriented and lost when they are out alone demonstrate topographic memory deficits."
 },
 {
  "id": 90,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some of the roles the parietal and frontal lobes, the hippocampus, and sleep play in short-term and\/or long-term memory.",
  "answer": "The brain’s parietal lobe and frontal lobe, particularly the dorsolateral prefrontal cortex, have regions responsible for transient communications between neurons that support short-term memory. In contrast, long-term memory is associated with permanent, stable modifications in widespread neuronal connections throughout the brain. The hippocampus is a brain structure that is not believed to store memories itself, but it is vitally important to new learning because it mediates the consolidation of information from short-term to long-term memory. We would have extremely short attention spans and be unable to store any new memories in our long-term memory without a functioning hippocampus. The hippocampus may also alter synapses for several months after learning new information. Sleep seems to enhance information consolidation. Research has found that the brain activation patterns in people when they were asleep and when they were awake and learning new information the day before were the same. This is why learners recall new information better after they have “slept on it.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 91,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Differentially define the terms recognition and recall as they relate to memory processes. Include examples and identify which process is easier and which one is more difficult.",
  "answer": "Recognition is the type of memory that entails identifying something familiar after you see or hear it. For example, in multiple choice test questions, choices include one correct answer and several incorrect ones. You can pick out the correct choice when you recognize it from your previous learning related to the question. Recall is the type of memory wherein you retrieve information from your long-term memory storage (or from short-term memory when you are given new items to repeat and\/or manipulate immediately, as is the case with many IQ tests). Examples of test questions involving this type of memory are fill-in-the-blank and short answer questions. These require you to retrieve an answer on your own rather than simply recognize the right answer among several choices. The latter is more difficult because you are not given the information. With multiple choice questions, the right answer is provided; you identify it through recognition. With fill-in-the-blank and short answer questions, you have to find the right answer through recall."
 },
 {
  "id": 92,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the classification of memory by temporal direction, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Memory has been classified by storage capacity and duration (as in the multi-store model) and by information type (explicit or implicit, etc.). When classified by temporal direction, memory is either retrospective or prospective. Retrospective memory involves remembering information from the past, and includes the information-type classifications of episodic, semantic, and autobiographical memory. These are all subtypes of explicit memory. Prospective memory involves remembering things that will occur in the future, or “remembering to remember.” Reminders of future plans or events can be time-based or event-based. Time-based prospective memories are activated by time cues. For example, you might remember that your doctor’s appointment is at 3:00 p.m. Event-based prospective memories often rely on visual cues. These include tying a string around one’s finger, putting up Post-It notes, or seeing a mailbox and remembering to mail a letter. Cues may be unrelated to the action, as in the first two examples. Cues can also be related to the action, as in the latter example."
 },
 {
  "id": 93,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some general principles of social learning theory.",
  "answer": "Social learning theory can be regarded as combining and\/or connecting behaviorist and cognitive theories of learning, as it incorporates both behavioral and cognitive elements. Individuals can learn not only directly, but also through observing others’ behaviors and their consequences. Contrary to behaviorism’s definition of learning as a permanent change in behavior, social learning theory finds that learning can occur with or without behavior change. This is because people can learn through observation alone. Learning includes cognitive factors, which have gained increasing prominence in social learning theory over the past few decades. For example, an individual’s knowledge and expectations of the potential rewards and punishments for various future behaviors can have a major influence on which behaviors that individual demonstrates or does not demonstrate."
 },
 {
  "id": 94,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some regions and structures in the brain involved in the neuroanatomy of memory, and include details and research findings about some of them. Outline some additional processes involved in memory and learning.",
  "answer": "The striatum, the mammillary bodies, the hippocampus, and the amygdala are involved in the neuroanatomy of memory. The hippocampus is thought to play a role in spatial memory, explicit memory (conscious recall), and the consolidation of information from short-term to long-term memory. It is regarded as essential to the retention of new memories. The amygdala is part of the limbic system, sometimes called the “animal brain,” which processes the most primitive, basic emotions necessary to survival. The amygdala is associated with emotional memories. Research finds storage of recent memories is enhanced in the short term by direct injections of epinephrine and cortisol, which are also the body’s natural stress hormones. These hormones also influence the amygdala. Specifically, excitement that stimulates stress hormones affecting the amygdala enhances memory. However, long-term elevations in the levels of these hormones, which can be caused by chronic stress, can damage memory. In addition to alterations in brain regions and structures, memory involves synaptic changes. Researchers believe these are mediated by long-term potentiation and depression."
 },
 {
  "id": 95,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of the contemporary perspective on social learning theory.",
  "answer": "According to contemporary theorists, the consequences of reinforcement (reward) and punishment are both indirect influences on learning. Unlike behaviorism, contemporary social learning theory does not view consequences as the chief or only causes of learning. Also unlike behaviorism, which views behavior as actions that are observable and measurable, contemporary social learning theory posits that because learning can occur observationally or vicariously, it may or may not be demonstrated. The degree to which an individual demonstrates a learned behavior is influenced by the rewards and punishments he or she associates with it. Cognitive processes that enable learning, including attention, are influenced by expectations of reinforcement. For example, when a teacher announces that the material he or she is about to present will not be on the test, students are less likely to pay attention because they do not expect to be tested and graded on it."
 },
 {
  "id": 96,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "According to Albert Bandura’s social learning theory, the environment itself can reinforce modeling of behaviors. Identify four ways this can occur, and include examples.",
  "answer": "One way modeling is reinforced environmentally is when the observational learner is reinforced by the model. For example, if a student starts dressing like a group of other students to fit into the group, she is likely to be accepted by the group, which constitutes reinforcement. Another way is when a third person reinforces the observer-learner. For example, if a student imitates the behavior of the best student in class and the teacher praises such emulation, this reinforces the behavior. Thirdly, the emulated behavior itself can be reinforcing. For example, a student who observes another student having fun doing an extra project is more likely to do the extra project and enjoy it. Finally, vicarious reinforcement means that the consequences of the model’s behavior influence the observer-learner’s behavior. In Bandura’s “Bobo Doll” experiments, children watched video of a model receiving praise for hitting an inflatable pop-back-up clown doll. The children imitated the action of hitting the doll without receiving any direct reinforcement."
 },
 {
  "id": 97,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify and describe some behaviors that can be totally or partially learned through modeling.",
  "answer": "Albert Bandura showed that in addition to learning through direct experiences, we learn many behaviors by observing models. For example, children may watch adults and older children reading and imitate their behaviors. When this behavioral imitation is combined with the development of the necessary internal cognitive processes, they learn to read. Students who observe others solving math problems can learn and imitate the same problem solving behaviors and procedural steps. Again, when students possess the requisite cognitive development, they can learn to solve math problems through modeling. A child who observes another behaving bravely in frightening circumstances can imitate the modeled behavior when similarly challenged. Bandura proved that children who observe aggressive behavior in others will imitate it, increasing their own aggressive behavior. Observation of models has also been found to influence moral behavior and thinking. For example, the development of moral judgments about what is right and wrong can be influenced in part by modeling."
 },
 {
  "id": 98,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some of the cognitive factors included in Bandura’s social learning theory.",
  "answer": "Bandura differentiates between observational learning and actual behavioral imitation. Therefore, learning can exist without performance in his theory (unlike in behaviorist theory). According to Bandura, attention, a form of cognitive processing, is a critical component to learning. Regarding expectations, when people receive reinforcement or punishment for certain behaviors, they expect to be given the same consequences for future engagement in those behaviors. However, they must be aware of the connection between behaviors and consequences for consequences to affect their behavior. Learners’ responses are only increased by reinforcement when the learners recognize the relationship between their behaviors and associated outcomes. In Bandura’s concept of reciprocal determinism, the person, the behavior, and the environment can all influence one another. Bandura’s theory states that modeling may be done using live models (people) or symbolic models (an action or person depicted in another medium, such as computer programs, videos, or television)."
 },
 {
  "id": 99,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the person who developed the term and concept of selfefficacy, and describe the meaning of this term. Describe some ways in which self-efficacy affects behavior.",
  "answer": "Albert Bandura, who developed social learning theory, coined the term selfefficacy to describe our belief in our ability to succeed at a given behavior or activity. It is a learning-specific form of self-confidence. Some influences on an individual’s self-efficacy include the individual’s previous experiences with successes and failures at an activity, messages the individual receives from others, and the individual’s observations of the successes and failures of others at the activity. Self-efficacy affects behavior in several ways. Since people select activities at which they expect to succeed, self-efficacy can influence how much an individual enjoys his or her chosen activities. Self-efficacy affects effort and persistence, as people make more effort and are more persistent when they are taking part in activities at which they expect to be successful. Self-efficacy also affects learning and achievement. Students with high levels of self-efficacy usually perform better in school and have higher achievement levels."
 },
 {
  "id": 100,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Cite some of the effects social learning theory posits modeling has on behavior, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Modeling is one way in which new behaviors can be taught. Modeling can also increase the frequency of behaviors already learned. For example, a child may have learned to brush his teeth or make his bed, but may not perform these tasks regularly. If he observes a model he admires doing these things every day, he is more likely to start doing them daily as well. Modeling can sometimes encourage an individual to engage in behaviors formerly not allowed. It can also encourage behaviors formerly not customary for the individual. For example, a man who only drinks alcohol occasionally at parties might begin carpooling with a new next-door neighbor who makes a before-dinner drink every night. After sharing this experience with the new neighbor a few times, the first man might begin making a before-dinner drink for himself every night at home. Modeling can also increase the frequency of similar behaviors. For example, if a student’s friend excels in basketball but the student is too short for basketball, he may try to excel in another sport, such as track."
 },
 {
  "id": 101,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "State how self-instructions can benefit learners. Identify and briefly define five steps for teaching and learning self-instruction that are presented in social learning theory.",
  "answer": "Self-instruction is a useful strategy for guiding one’s own behavior. It aids autonomy and self-regulation, the process through which learners choose their behaviors based on their own concepts of what is appropriate and inappropriate. Social learning theory’s five progressive steps to selfinstruction are: (1) overt cognitive modeling, whereby the teacher performs the behavior for the student to observe and imitate; (2) overt external guidance, whereby the teacher guides the student as needed to perform the behavior independently once the learner has mastered observing and imitating the behavior; (3) overt self-guidance, whereby the student performs the behavior as the teacher did in the previous step, giving himself or herself guidance as needed; (4) faded overt self-guidance, whereby the student continues to guide herself or himself when needed, but gradually decreases this self-guidance (which has been visible and\/or audible up to this point) as proficiency increases and the need for overt self-guidance decreases; (5) covert self-instruction, whereby the student gives herself or himself mental instructions while performing tasks. By the time the student reaches the final step, he or she has internalized the learning and no longer needs to guide himself or herself visibly or audibly."
 },
 {
  "id": 102,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the term self-regulation as it relates to social learning theory, and identify several aspects of self-regulation.",
  "answer": "Self-regulation is related to an individual’s personally developed ideas regarding which behaviors are appropriate or inappropriate. The individual relies on those ideas when deciding how to act in certain situations. Aspects of self-regulation include setting standards and goals for oneself; selfobservation, which is observing one’s own behaviors; self-judgment, which is forming opinions about one’s behaviors, such as whether something one did was appropriate or not, and why; and self-reaction, which is feeling justified, proud, remorseful, or guilty about one’s behavior, and then making decisions about whether to repeat or change the behavior in the future based on these feelings. Educators, psychologists, and employers\/managers can foster self-regulation by teaching students and employees to reward themselves after engaging in a targeted behavior. For example, a student or employee may tell himself or herself that he or she can take a break after completing a certain amount of work or meeting a certain benchmark."
 },
 {
  "id": 103,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Review some research conclusions about differences in human cognitive development related to gender.",
  "answer": "Some major researchers in the 1970s came to the conclusion that males have better visuospatial and mathematical skills, while females have better verbal skills. One of these researchers, however, changed her conclusions in the late 1980s. By then, research findings had shown that gender differences in verbal skills had all but vanished. However, males were still found to have better math and visuospatial skills. Even in the 1990s and 2000s, the 10 finalists in National Geographic’s Geography Bee were usually all boys, even though equal numbers of boys and girls competed. As late as 2011, all finalists were males. Nevertheless, there are suggestions that cognitive gender differences have been exaggerated. Experts (cf. Hyde, 2005, 2007) find significant overlaps in math and visuospatial scores between genders. In the 2005 National Assessment of Educational Progress, boys performed slightly better in math and science. Girls, however, were superior students overall, and scored significantly better in reading. In another nationwide study in 2001, females in elementary, middle school, and high school were found to have superior writing skills."
 },
 {
  "id": 104,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize some research findings about differences in neurological structures and functions related to gender.",
  "answer": "Male and female human brains are quite similar, but some gender differences have been found. While female brains are smaller than male brains, they have more convolutions (folds), resulting in a greater total surface area of brain tissue. One portion of the hypothalamus that governs sexual behavior is larger in male brains than in female brains. In the female brain, parts of the corpus callosum, which connects the left and right hemispheres of the brain, are larger and more developed. The blood supply to these regions is also greater. Some people infer from this that the communication between the two hemispheres is better in female brains than in male brains. A part of the parietal lobe that plays a role in visuospatial skills is larger in male brains than in female brains. This may explain why many males have better visuospatial skills than many females. Finally, the regions of the brain that are involved in processes related to emotional expression display more metabolic activity in female brains than in male brains."
 },
 {
  "id": 105,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the term reinforcement and describe schedules of reinforcement used in operant conditioning as these concepts relate to Skinnerian radical behaviorism. Define the terms continuous, ratio, interval, and fixed vs. variable as they relate to reinforcement schedules.",
  "answer": "Reinforcement of a behavior increases the probability the behavior will be repeated. A reinforcer is any stimulus the individual (animal or human) likes. Reinforcers may be food, contact, a toy, praise, etc. Reinforcement schedules are rules regarding the conditions that must be met for a behavior to be reinforced. They specify when, how often, how long, and\/or under what conditions reinforcers will be presented. Different schedules produce different effects. With continuous reinforcement, every instance of a behavior is reinforced. Ratio schedules present reinforcement according to a required number of behaviors (every 10 or 20 instances of the behavior, for example).\n\nInterval schedules present reinforcement on the basis of time intervals (every 10 or 20 minutes, for example). Fixed schedules present reinforcement according to fixed rules. In this approach, the number of responses or time intervals required for reinforcement to be presented is always the same. Variable schedules present reinforcement randomly. The number of responses or time intervals required for reinforcement varies, so the reinforcement is unpredictable. The intermittent reinforcement given as a result of implementing variable schedules produces more lasting behavior that is more resistant to extinction."
 },
 {
  "id": 106,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some research findings related to gender differences in socioemotional development.",
  "answer": "The most extensively researched areas of gender similarities and differences in socioemotional development are aggression, emotion, and prosocial behavior. Research has found greater physical aggression appears at early ages in boys across all cultures. However, when social, verbal, and relational (non-physical) types of aggression are counted, girls display these types of aggression just as much or more than boys display physical aggression. Investigations into whether girls show more relational aggression than boys have yielded mixed, inconclusive results. Boys are more likely to hide negative emotions, such as sadness, beginning in elementary school. Girls are more likely to hide emotions that would hurt others’ feelings. Adolescent girls report more sadness, guilt, and shame; adolescent boys tend to deny experiencing these feelings. Males exhibit less emotional self-regulation than females. Females show more prosocial behavior through childhood and adolescence. Gender differences in sharing behaviors are relatively small, while gender differences in considerate, kind behavior are larger."
 },
 {
  "id": 107,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the characteristics of variable schedules of reinforcement and how they differ from fixed schedules. Outline their effects and provide an example.",
  "answer": "Variable schedules of reinforcement differ from fixed schedules in that the desired behavior is reinforced variably instead of regularly. Rather than reinforcing a behavior after a fixed number of occurrences or after a fixed time interval, these schedules reinforce the behavior after a random number of occurrences or a random interval of time. This way, the learner cannot predict when reinforcement will occur. Variable schedules usually produce more consistent response patterns. There are typically no pauses by the learner following reinforcement. Variable ratio schedules (ones based on varying numbers of responses) tend to result in higher rates of response, while variable interval schedules (ones based on varying times intervals) tend to result in lower rates of response. However, both types of variable schedules produce consistent response rates. For example, people continue to play slot machines in Las Vegas casinos because payouts occur randomly and unpredictably. A payout could occur after three plays or thirty, or after one minute or one hour, so players keep trying."
 },
 {
  "id": 108,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe fixed ratio and fixed interval schedules of reinforcement. Outline their effects and give an example of each.",
  "answer": "A fixed ratio schedule means reinforcement is presented after a fixed number of target responses. The fixed ratio schedule of reinforcement typically results in rapid rates of responses, with brief pauses following reinforcement. The duration of these pauses is directly proportional to the number of responses required for reinforcement. An example would be if you wanted a child to make eye contact when you say his name. When he does this four times in a row, you praise him. A fixed interval schedule means reinforcement is presented when the target response is observed, but only after a certain time interval. Responses observed during the interval are not reinforced; the first response after the interval is reinforced. Using the previous example, you might give the child reinforcement for making eye contact when you say his name every time five minutes have passed since the last reinforcement. This produces low response rates early in each time interval, but higher rates near the end of each interval. The overall response rate is low."
 },
 {
  "id": 109,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the term extinction as it relates to operant conditioning and schedules of reinforcement. Identify some advantages and characteristics of intermittent reinforcement vs. continuous reinforcement.",
  "answer": "After an individual has been conditioned to display a certain behavior or display a behavior more often through reinforcement (reward), the individual often continues to display that behavior without reinforcement. However, if the individual stops displaying the behavior once reinforcement is discontinued, this is known as extinction. When extinction occurs, the behavior has been extinguished by the absence of rewarding consequences. Some schedules of reinforcement produce behaviors that are more resistant to extinction. In other words, they are more likely to persist and less likely to stop. The less frequently and less consistently a behavior is reinforced, the more resistant it is to extinction. Behaviors reinforced on variable or random schedules are more resistant to extinction than those reinforced on fixed schedules. Intermittent reinforcement saves time and energy by delivering reinforcers less often than continuous reinforcement. It can save money if material reinforcers are being used. It also delays satiation, which is when the reinforcement loses its appeal because it is provided excessively."
 },
 {
  "id": 110,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe fixed and variable duration schedules of reinforcement and explain how they differ from fixed and variable interval schedules. Outline their effects and give an example.",
  "answer": "Interval schedules of reinforcement deliver the reinforcer after a time interval when the desired response is observed. Duration schedules of reinforcement are different in that they present reinforcement after the desired response has occurred continuously for a specified duration of time (five full minutes, a full hour, etc.). The effect of this reinforcement schedule is to produce a continuous rate of behavior; that is what is required for reinforcement. Fixed duration schedules reinforce the desired behavior after a specified length of time; variable duration schedules reinforce the desired behavior after variable lengths of time. To give an example of a fixed duration schedule of reinforcement, if you wanted a student to stay in his seat for an entire class period, you would give reinforcement immediately after he remained in his seat for the whole hour, the entire 50 minutes, etc. If there was a very high rate of out-of-seat behavior (every two to three minutes, for example), you would give reinforcement after a shorter time interval, perhaps five minutes. If this approach was successful, you would gradually increase the time the student would need to remain seated to receive reinforcement."
 },
 {
  "id": 111,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the limited hold variation of reinforcement schedules used in operant conditioning, and give an example.",
  "answer": "When using a fixed interval schedule of reinforcement, you reinforce the desired behavior only when it occurs after a specified interval of time. If the learner is responding, but at a slow rate, you can produce a faster response rate by using limited hold. If the learner does not respond soon after the end of the specified interval, this contributes to a slower response rate. This rate can be accelerated by limiting the length of time the reinforcement is available following the desired response. For example, if you specify that the learner must respond within 10 seconds after each specified time interval and the learner does not respond within 10 seconds, the learner loses the reinforcement for that instance of the behavior. Another reinforcer is not delivered until the next time interval ends, and only if the learner responds within 10 seconds of the end of the interval."
 },
 {
  "id": 112,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss reinforcer density as it relates to operant conditioning and reinforcement schedules. Explain how and when reinforcer density should be changed.",
  "answer": "When training an individual to display a desired behavior using reinforcement, many instances of the behavior can be elicited with intermittent schedules of reinforcement. To initially establish a behavior, reinforcement should be continuous, meaning it should be given every time the desired behavior is observed. This is a dense reinforcement schedule. As the behavior becomes stronger and the individual displays it more frequently and consistently, reinforcer density can be gradually decreased by delivering reinforcement less often. If reinforcer density is reduced too quickly, the individual may exhibit a slower response rate; may respond inconsistently; and\/or may increase other, undesired responses. This is called schedule strain. The solution is to increase the reinforcer density again, and subsequently decrease it more slowly. Another technique that can help with this process is introducing a conditioned reinforcer (one the individual has learned to associate specifically with the target response) in between the existing, generally rewarding reinforcements."
 },
 {
  "id": 113,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the matching law and the principle of maximizing, which are characteristics of concurrent schedules of reinforcement used in operant conditioning.",
  "answer": "When you are using two or more basic schedules of reinforcement concurrently to increase two or more different desired behaviors, the learner’s rate of response to each schedule will not be the same. The matching law states that the learner’s response rate will be proportional to the ratio of reinforcers given in each schedule. The target behavior that is reinforced most frequently, for example, will be displayed more frequently by the learner. The behavior that is reinforced the soonest will also be displayed more frequently. The principle of maximizing is demonstrated when the learner alternates between or among target behaviors to obtain the maximum numbers and types of reinforcers. When ratio schedules of reinforcement are used concurrently, learners do not switch between or among behaviors very often. If there are two concurrent interval schedules, learners can obtain nearly all of the reinforcements from both schedules."
 },
 {
  "id": 114,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the reinforcement schedule variation of concurrent schedules used in operant conditioning. Outline two advantages and describe the differential increases in response rates when similar reinforcements are used for each schedule.",
  "answer": "A simple or basic reinforcement schedule uses one type of reinforcer to increase the incidence of one desired behavior in an individual. In the variation known as concurrent schedules, two or more basic schedules of reinforcement are applied at the same time. They function independently of one another to increase two or more desired behaviors. One advantage of concurrent schedules of reinforcement is that the individual has a choice of behaviors and schedules. Another is that concurrent schedules are easier to generalize to real life, where reinforcement frequently comes from more than one source and\/or is given for more than one type of response. When using concurrent reinforcement schedules, the following rules apply if the reinforcers for each of the responses are similar: the rate of the response reinforced more frequently will increase, the rate of the response that requires the least effort will increase, and the rate of the response that receives the most immediate reinforcement will increase."
 },
 {
  "id": 115,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Differentially describe the reinforcement schedule variation of conjunctive schedules vs. concurrent and chained schedules. Identify some results of the interaction of tasks and time intervals in conjunctive schedules of reinforcement.",
  "answer": "Concurrent schedules of reinforcement apply more than one schedule to increase more than one target behavior at the same time. However, the learner can choose between or among schedules, behaviors, and reinforcers, and may alternate his or her choices. Chained schedules also apply more than one schedule. However, schedules are implemented consecutively in a designated sequence rather than concurrently. Conjunctive schedules of reinforcement apply more than one schedule to increase more than one behavior at the same time. However, the requirements for each schedule must be met at the same time, which is not a requirement of concurrent or chained schedules. Interactions of tasks and time intervals can be observed in concurrent schedules of reinforcement. For example, when a task has high requirements and the time interval is short, the learner is likely to work steadily throughout that interval. When the task has lower requirements and the time interval is longer, the learner is likely to demonstrate more off-task behaviors."
 },
 {
  "id": 116,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe how the reinforcement schedule variation known as chained schedules is implemented in operant conditioning, and include an example.",
  "answer": "The reinforcement schedule variation known as chained schedules uses more than one reinforcement schedule to increase more than one target behavior. However, unlike the concurrent schedules variation, which applies two or more schedules at the same time, chaining schedules involves applying one schedule at a time. Schedules are applied consecutively and in a specified order. Schedules are termed chained because the second one depends on the first, the third depends on the second, etc. The reinforcement the learner receives for displaying the desired response for the first schedule is presentation of the second schedule. Other reinforcement is given only when the learner gives the desired response for the second schedule (or for the last one if there are more than two). For example, the first schedule could target sitting down at a table. This behavior is reinforced by the second schedule, which involves eating lunch. Eating lunch is reinforced by receiving dessert. Typically, a cue is associated with a particular schedule, and is used for the duration of the schedule’s implementation."
 },
 {
  "id": 117,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some of the general characteristics of cognitive behavioral therapies (CBT). (continued)",
  "answer": "In some therapeutic approaches, the therapist is more in control. In others, the client is more responsible. CBT is a therapy that relies on clienttherapist collaboration. Therapists find out what their clients’ goals are in life, and then help them attain them. CBT therapists listen, teach, and encourage; CBT clients express their concerns, learn, and apply their learning. While CBT does not dictate how clients should feel, it does promote approaching problems calmly rather than overreacting to them and becoming excessively upset. When we are calm, we feel better and are better able to solve personal problems. When we are upset, we feel worse and cannot think rationally or employ good problem solving techniques. Moreover, when we are upset, we have two problems (the problem and the distress we feel over it) instead of one. CBT uses the Socratic method. Therapists often ask their clients questions, and also invite clients to ask themselves questions. Some examples of good questions are: “How do I know they are laughing at me? Could they be laughing at something else?”"
 },
 {
  "id": 118,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some of the general characteristics of cognitive behavioral therapies (CBT).",
  "answer": "CBT is not a single therapeutic approach but rather a genre that encompasses several forms and approaches. Generally, CBT is based on the cognitive model of emotional response. This model holds that our behaviors and feelings are caused by our internal thoughts, not by external influences such as people, events, or circumstances. An advantage of this belief is that we can change our thoughts and thus our responses, even when external factors do not change. CBT is a time-limited, brief therapy compared to many others, and produces rapid results. Its practice is highly instructional, and includes homework assignments. While some other therapies find the therapeutic relationship to be the main reason for client progress, CBT does not. CBT does believe the client-therapist relationship is important, but holds that it is not the cause of improvement. Progress is attributed more to the client’s learning different ways of thinking and acting upon this learning. Thus, CBT practitioners emphasize teaching rational selfcounseling skills to their clients."
 },
 {
  "id": 119,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss how cognitive behavioral therapies employ the inductive method and homework.",
  "answer": "Cognitive behavioral therapies (CBT) are brief and time-limited treatment methods. The overall average course of treatment is 16 sessions. Of all therapies, CBT produces some of the most rapid results. CBT’s philosophy is that our thoughts, rather than outside environmental factors, cause our feelings and behaviors. A strong component of CBT is rational thinking. CBT teaches clients to change their thinking to change their feelings and behaviors. Rational thought is fact-based, while most of our upset reactions are not. CBT uses the inductive method to teach clients to view their thoughts as hypotheses that can be tested. When new or previously ignored information is applied, these hypotheses may be refuted, and clients can change their thoughts to be more accurate and realistic. Homework accelerates progress in CBT. An hour a week in therapy is insufficient to learn new techniques, so homework such as reading assignments and practice applying techniques is assigned for more efficient learning."
 },
 {
  "id": 120,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some of the general characteristics of cognitive behavioral therapies (CBT). (continued 3)",
  "answer": "CBT is a type of therapy based on an educational model. It is founded on the assumption that most of our emotional and behavioral responses are learned. This assumption is supported by scientific research findings. Responses that have been learned can be unlearned and replaced by more desirable responses, which is the aim of CBT techniques. This educational orientation benefits clients by affording long-term results from short-term therapy. When clients understand how and why they are making progress, they know what to do to maintain those favorable outcomes. CBT is structured. There is a specific agenda for each session, during which specific concepts and techniques are taught. CBT therapists take on an instructional role, but don’t tell clients what they should do, what their goals should be, or what they should or should not tolerate. Rather, CBT therapists teach their clients how they can think, behave, and do things to accomplish their goals."
 },
 {
  "id": 121,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the A-B-C model used by Dr. Albert Ellis in rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT), and provide an example.",
  "answer": "According to Dr. Ellis, when we encounter obstacles to realizing our goals, our reactions are determined by our beliefs. To teach clients how their beliefs dictate their emotional and behavioral responses, Ellis created the AB-C model. The letters represent the following: (A) something occurs; (B) you have a belief about it; (C) you have an emotional reaction to that belief. Here is an example of different beliefs causing different feelings. In the first scenario: (A) Mary’s boss wrongly accuses her of falsifying data and threatens to fire her; (B) Mary believes, “She has no right to accuse me. What a witch!”; (C) Mary feels angry. Here is another scenario: (A) Mary’s boss wrongly accuses her of falsifying data and threatens to fire her; (B) Mary believes, “I can’t lose my job. That would be disastrous!”; (C) Mary feels anxious. This model shows that A does not cause C; B causes C in both instances. Mary’s anger and anxiety are caused by different beliefs (B), not by the boss’s incorrect accusation (A)."
 },
 {
  "id": 122,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the basic philosophy of Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT). Identify the ancient Greek philosopher who expressed the idea underlying this therapy and describe a realistic advantage of this perspective.",
  "answer": "Albert Ellis’s REBT is one type of cognitive behavioral therapy. Ellis emphasized the idea that we develop false beliefs and erroneous thoughts in response to life events, and that these mistaken ideas cause our emotional unhappiness. By challenging these wrong ideas, finding them false, and learning to replace them with more accurate ones, we can change our thinking. This enables us to change our behavioral responses. The basic REBT philosophy is that we are not made upset or unhappy by life events, but by our beliefs and our reactions to those events. The ancient Greek philosopher Epictetus expressed this more than 2,000 years ago when he said: “Men are disturbed not by events, but by the views which they take of them.” A distinct advantage of this perspective is that we often cannot do anything to change certain events, people, situations, and circumstances in real life, but it is within our power to change the way we think about and react to those events, people, situations, and circumstances."
 },
 {
  "id": 123,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss the technique of disputing that is part of Dr. Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT) and how it relates to his A-B-C model. Include some examples.",
  "answer": "In REBT, Ellis’s A-B-C model represents the process that: (A) something happens; (B) you have some belief about it; and (C) you have an emotional reaction based on your belief. Following A, B, and C is D, which stands for disputing. In REBT, disputing is the process of challenging our irrational beliefs and proving them wrong. REBT is based on the principle that our false beliefs about many things cause emotional unhappiness. The aim of REBT is to disprove these wrong ideas and replace them with more logical thoughts. In disputing, the REBT therapist asks the client questions, such as: “Why must you have that thing just because you want it?” “Who said everybody must treat you fairly?” and “Why must you get everybody’s approval?” The emphasis on “must” relates to Ellis’s “Three Basic Musts,” the three general false beliefs on which all irrational beliefs are based. When clients try to answer such questions, they realize there are no answers. Therefore, there is no reason to believe these things."
 },
 {
  "id": 124,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify and describe the “Three Basic Musts” proposed by Dr. Albert Ellis in his rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT) model. Discuss their respective effects and alternative beliefs to the “Three Basic Musts.”",
  "answer": "Ellis proposed that the things we believe that upset us are all variations of three common irrational beliefs, all involving a demand of ourselves, others, or the world. These are known as the “Three Basic Musts.” The first is: “I must do well and win the approval of others for my performances or else I am no good.” The second is: “Other people must treat me considerately, fairly and kindly, and in exactly the way I want them to treat me. If they don't, they are no good and they deserve to be condemned and punished.” The third is: “I must get what I want, when I want it; and I must not get what I don't want. It's terrible if I don't get what I want, and I can't stand it.” The first promotes anxiety, shame, guilt, and depression. The second is conducive to passive-aggression, rage, and violence. The third fosters procrastination and self-pity. These effects are due to the fact that these beliefs are too demanding. Healthier emotions and behaviors are afforded by more flexible, less demanding beliefs."
 },
 {
  "id": 125,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the three types of acceptance that practitioners of Dr. Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT) work to help their clients develop. Cite the three core beliefs that underlie the first type of acceptance.",
  "answer": "Part of REBT’s philosophy is that the ability to accept reality—including when it is unpleasant and seems unacceptable—is a characteristic of emotionally healthy human beings. REBT practitioners work to help their clients develop three types of acceptance: (1) unconditional self-acceptance, (2) unconditional other-acceptance, and (3) unconditional life-acceptance. Unconditional self-acceptance involves accepting yourself completely and without qualification. There are three core beliefs of unconditional selfacceptance. The first is: I am a human being; I am fallible; I have both good and bad qualities. The second is: there is no reason that I must be perfect or without any flaws. The third is: regardless of my good and bad qualities, I am not any more worthy or any less worthy than any other human being. Adopting and internalizing these core beliefs promotes self-acceptance rather than self-judgment, which can cause low self-esteem or denial of reality."
 },
 {
  "id": 126,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss Dr. Albert Ellis’s three insights, which are part of his rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT), and describe how developing these insights can modify our thinking.",
  "answer": "Ellis claimed in his REBT model that we cannot completely eradicate irrational beliefs, but we can minimize their intensity, frequency, and duration by developing three insights. These are: (1) we do not just “get upset,” but mostly upset ourselves by maintaining rigid beliefs; (2) regardless of how and\/or when we upset ourselves, we sustain our upset state by clinging to our illogical beliefs; (3) the only way we can get better is to work hard to change what we believe. This process takes a great deal of practice. With the first insight, instead of assuming various life events, circumstances, and people upset us, we shift our thinking and realize it is not what happens that upsets us, but rather what we believe about it, and the fact that we believe it inflexibly. By believing differently, we will feel differently. With the second insight, we realize we will not get over feeling upset as long as we assume what we believe is true. With the third insight, we understand it is not impossible to change our beliefs, but recognize that it takes time and effort. We also realize this effort will eventually yield results."
 },
 {
  "id": 127,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the three types of acceptance that practitioners of Dr. Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT) work to help their clients develop. Cite the three core beliefs that underlie the third type of acceptance",
  "answer": "REBT practitioners work to help their clients develop unconditional selfacceptance, unconditional other-acceptance, and unconditional lifeacceptance. With unconditional self-acceptance, clients can accept themselves as imperfect humans instead of blaming themselves for their woes. With unconditional other-acceptance, instead of blaming others and\/or their actions for their woes, clients realize their own beliefs about others and\/or their actions cause their own reactions. With unconditional life-acceptance, clients learn that instead of “life” in general, their own thinking is responsible for their woes, and this is something that can be changed. REBT seeks to assist clients in making this change. There are three core beliefs of unconditional life-acceptance. The first is: life does not always go the way I would want it to go. The second is: there is no reason that life has to go the way I want it to go. The third is: life is not always pleasant, but is never “awful” and is almost always bearable."
 },
 {
  "id": 128,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the three types of acceptance that practitioners of Dr. Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT) work to help their clients develop. Cite the three core beliefs that underlie the second type of acceptance.",
  "answer": "Therapists who practice Ellis’s REBT endeavor to help their clients develop unconditional self-acceptance, unconditional other-acceptance, and unconditional life-acceptance. Together, these three types of acceptance comprise an acceptance of reality, which is required for emotional health. Just as judging instead of accepting yourself causes guilt, shame, and feelings of inferiority, judging others can cause hostility, isolation, and feelings of false superiority. There are three core beliefs of unconditional other-acceptance. The first is: there will be some times when some other people will treat me unfairly. The second is: there is no reason that people must always treat me fairly. The third is: those people who treat me unfairly are no less worthy or any more worthy than any other human being. By unconditionally accepting others the way they are, we can avoid blaming them for our problems, including our hurt feelings. These are not caused by others, but by our incorrect beliefs. When we replace those faulty beliefs with the core beliefs outlined above, we can accept others."
 },
 {
  "id": 129,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the contributions of Dr. Aaron Beck to psychotherapy.",
  "answer": "Dr. Aaron Beck (born in 1921) was trained in psychoanalysis. However, he found in the 1960s that a big problem with psychotherapy in general was the absence of scientific data to prove the effectiveness of any particular psychotherapeutic approaches or techniques. Beck was a pioneer of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT). A number of specific variations of this approach exist today. As Beck developed CBT, he wanted a reliable, standardized way of scientifically measuring whether his new therapeutic techniques were effective, and to what degree. To do this, it was necessary to first measure the client’s subjective feelings, such as depression and anxiety. This allowed changes in these feelings during and after treatment to be measured so overall treatment effectiveness could be assessed. He developed the Beck Depression Inventory and the Beck Anxiety Inventory, now widely used in psychological evaluations. Beck not only developed a major approach to therapy that has widespread applications and a high degree of effectiveness, but he also developed scientific methods for testing and proving the effectiveness of CBT and other therapies."
 },
 {
  "id": 130,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Briefly summarize the history and development of Albert Ellis’s rational emotive behavior therapy (REBT), including early reactions and current status.",
  "answer": "When Dr. Albert Ellis formulated and began practicing REBT in the 1950s, many other theorists and practitioners in the field of mental health found his theory and methods radical and controversial. His ideas were met with a great deal of resistance, criticism, and attack. However, the clinical experiences of Dr. Ellis and other practitioners of REBT over the past several decades have shown that REBT’s methods have relieved many clients of their emotional pain. In addition, other psychological researchers have conducted experiments over this time period. Their results are part of an increasing body of scientific evidence that REBT is an effective approach that accomplishes its effects in an efficient manner. Despite early reactions, REBT is now one of the most widely practiced therapies in the world. Thanks to Ellis and other practitioners consistently applying the philosophical system underlying REBT, the extent of its impact on the psychotherapy field and the number of clients it has helped (which is in the millions) have far exceeded what even Dr. Ellis could have anticipated when he first started using it."
 },
 {
  "id": 131,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Classify Expectancy Theory as a type of motivational theory, describe what it seeks to explain, and identify and briefly define its three basic components.",
  "answer": "Expectancy Theory is a type of motivational theory that is considered a process theory (rather than a content theory or a behavioral theory). It seeks to explain how behaviors are directed to certain choices—not what motivates us, but how we make decisions to attain our goals. According to Expectancy Theory, the motivational force directing our choices has three components: expectancy, instrumentality, and valence. Expectancy is our belief and perception that effort will result in performance [E > P]. It is based on individual perceptions of self-efficacy (confidence), goal difficulty, and control. Instrumentality is our belief and perception that performance will result in rewards [P > R]. It is based on our perceptions of trust in our leaders, of our control, and policy. Formalized policies rewarding performance tend to augment instrumentality. Valence is the value of the expected rewards [V(R)] to the individual. It is based on our individual needs, values, goals, preferences, and sources of motivation."
 },
 {
  "id": 132,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss how motivation relates to and influences behavior. Describe the main classifications of theories of motivation.",
  "answer": "Because people do not have the same overall motivation in various situations, motivation is better studied in relation to particular behaviors. Psychologists regard performance as a function of ability, motivation, resources, and role perception. In ascertaining individual performance, motivational theories seek to explain motivation as one component of performance. Theorists state that motivation has three main influences on behavior: (1) to initiate, activate, or energize behavior, which includes the amount of effort expended; (2) to direct behavior, meaning it can help the individual choose among several competitive alternatives; and (3) to maintain behavior over time, which refers to whether an individual persists in a behavior or stops it. Theories of motivation can be classified as content theories, process theories, or behavioral theories. Theories explaining relative effort and how behavior is energized are content theories. Theories explaining how effort is directed are process theories. Theories explaining how behavior is continued are behavioral theories."
 },
 {
  "id": 133,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define instrumentality as it relates to the Expectancy Theory of motivation, and include some examples of this belief.",
  "answer": "In Expectancy Theory, instrumentality is the belief and perception that rewards will increase proportionately to one’s fulfillment of performance expectations. Rewards may be extrinsic and quantitative, such as higher grades, pay raises, or promotions; extrinsic and qualitative, such as recognition from leaders and\/or peers; or intrinsic and qualitative, such as a sense of accomplishment, satisfaction, and\/or pride. If rewards valued by the individual can be obtained regardless of performance levels, instrumentality is low. For example, if a professor gives everybody in his or her class an A regardless of their performance, instrumentality is lowered for individual students. Some examples of instrumentality perceptions and questions include: If I get a better grade on tomorrow’s exam, will I get an A in the course? If I produce more than other workers, will I get a larger pay increase or an earlier promotion? If I make more sales, will I get a bigger commission or a bonus? Will I be perceived by myself and\/or others as the best salesperson if I make more sales?"
 },
 {
  "id": 134,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify and explain three variables in the Expectancy Theory of motivation that influence an individual’s perception of expectancy. Give some examples of expectancy, which is defined as [E > P].",
  "answer": "According to Expectancy Theory, one variable affecting individual expectancy perceptions is self-efficacy: whether and to what degree the individual feels he or she has the ability and skills to perform the specific behavior or meet the goal in question successfully. Another variable is goal difficulty. If performance expectations or goals are so difficult or unrealistic that the individual perceives he or she cannot accomplish them, the individual has low expectancy and therefore low motivation. The third variable is control. If the individual perceives he or she has no control over performance and outcome, expectancy and thus motivation are low. For example, employees of very large corporations may perceive that they do not directly control corporate profits. Therefore, profit-sharing plans will not motivate them to work harder. Some examples of expectancy, the belief that effort leads to performance that is expressed as [E > P], include: If I study hard tonight, will I get a better grade on tomorrow’s test? If I work harder, will I produce more? If I make more sales calls, will I make more sales?"
 },
 {
  "id": 135,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how the valence component of Expectancy Theory influences motivation. Describe variables affecting valence, examples of outcomes an individual might value, and some general examples of individual valences for outcomes.",
  "answer": "In Expectancy Theory, valence represents the personal value an individual assigns to the rewards he or she can expect for performance. The individual’s valence is affected by several variables, including the individual’s personal values, individual needs, personal goals, personal preferences, and the individual’s particular sources of motivation. Outcomes that commonly occur and ones that individuals often value include good grades; pay raises; promotions; more time off; assignments or projects that are new and\/or engaging, challenging, or enjoyable; recognition from others; internal satisfaction from the validation of one’s accomplishments; and\/or internal satisfaction from knowing one’s performance efforts have helped somebody. Some general examples of individual valences for outcomes include: How badly do I want an A in this subject? Is getting a bigger raise worth the effort required? How important is it to me to be named the team’s MVP? Is the additional time needed to make more sales calls worth the additional commission? Is it important to me to be the best salesperson?"
 },
 {
  "id": 136,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how three variables in Expectancy Theory function to influence individual perceptions of instrumentality.",
  "answer": "According to Expectancy Theory, instrumentality is our belief or perception that we will receive greater or lesser rewards for greater or lesser performance, respectively. Three variables that influence this perception are trust, control, and policies. When we trust our leaders (e.g. teachers or bosses), we are more likely to believe them when they promise that we will receive rewards for our performance. Our perceptions of instrumentality increase in proportion to the amount of control we perceive we have. When individuals do not trust their leaders, they tend to try to negotiate a contract or some other mechanism of enabling control of the reward system. Individuals have higher perceptions of instrumentality when they perceive that they have some type of control over why, when, and how rewards are given. Instrumentality is also increased when a school, institution, organization, or company has formalized written policies for rewarding performance with pay and\/or perks."
 },
 {
  "id": 137,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Provide a general definition of Constructivism. Identify some prominent figures whose theories and work have been Constructivist in nature.",
  "answer": "The branch of philosophy concerned with the study of knowledge is epistemology. Among epistemological theories, Constructivism is one that regards knowledge as something that we generate through interactions between our experiences and our ideas. According to Constructivism, there is no knowledge other than the meaning that each learner constructs from his or her experiences. Thus, constructing meaning equals learning. This theory directs the focus onto the learner rather than the information or subject to be learned. Some proponents of Constructivism include John Dewey, whose philosophy of education emphasized learning through experience; Maria Montessori, who developed schools that focused on experiential learning; Jean Piaget, whose theory of cognitive development includes schemata or mental constructs that we use to represent, categorize, and understand aspects of our environment, and who identified children as miniature scientists whose interactions with and experiments upon the environment construct their knowledge; Lev Vygotsky, whose historical-cultural theory of learning is an example of Social Constructivism; and Jerome Bruner, who described how children cognitively represent the environment."
 },
 {
  "id": 138,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe how the Expectancy Theory of motivation explains the decision making process for behavioral choice. Explain the three expectancy perceptions and identify major influences on each. Include a discussion of related psychological theories and relevant terminology.",
  "answer": "Expectancy Theory explains not what motivates us, but how we choose among behavioral alternatives once we are motivated. This theory proposes that we choose the option with the greatest motivational force. Motivational force is comprised of expectancy, instrumentality, and valence. Expectancy is the perception of the probability that effort will result in successful performance. Instrumentality is the perception of the probability that performance will yield commensurate rewards. Valence is the personal value an individual places on particular rewards. Valence originates in the individual’s values system. Expectancy and instrumentality are cognitions, as they represent attitudes. They are individual, subjective perceptions of probabilities that may or may not reflect actual probabilities. They are influenced by the individual’s experiences, as in Learning Theory\/Behaviorism; others’ observations, as in Social Learning Theory; and self-perceptions. Valence equates to consequences in Behaviorism. High instrumentality equates to high probability\/likelihood of consequences in Behaviorism. A portion of expectancy equates to specificity of definitions in Behaviorism."
 },
 {
  "id": 139,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the origins and basic principles of the James-Lange theory of emotion.",
  "answer": "The James-Lange theory of emotion is one of the earliest theories of emotion ever developed. It was proposed independently around the same time by William James, the great philosopher and one of the fathers of modern psychology; and Carl Lange, the Danish physiologist. James published a journal article on it in 1884, and Lange did so in 1887. Because their two theories were so similar, nearly identical in fact, they were described using a single title: the James-Lange theory. Unlike many who believed that our emotions cause physical changes, such as crying from sadness, shaking from fear, hitting from anger, etc., James and Lange believed the reverse: that the physical changes cause the emotions. James proposed that without physical symptoms, our perceptions would be pure cognitions without emotion. For example, we would decide to run upon seeing a bear, but without the trembling and racing heart, we would not feel afraid. James stated our experience of these bodily changes is the emotion. Lange added that vasomotor changes are themselves the emotions."
 },
 {
  "id": 140,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the term mnemonics, identify some common types of mnemonic devices, and give some examples. Identify two characteristics of mnemonics that contribute to their effectiveness.",
  "answer": "Mnemonics are memory aids used as learning devices. One common type is first-letter\/acronym mnemonics that associate other words with the initials of the word sequence to learn. For example, we remember the order of the rainbow’s colors (red, orange, yellow, green, blue, indigo, and violet) using the acronym “Roy G. Biv.” We remember the order of the planets in our Solar System according to their distance from the sun (Mercury, Venus, Earth, Mars, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus, Neptune, and traditionally Pluto) using the sentence “My Valuable Elephant May Jump Suddenly Unless Natives Prevent” or many others. Numerical sequences can also be remembered using mnemonics. For example, in “How I need a drink, alcoholic of course, after the heavy lectures involving quantum mechanics” the number of letters in each word equals the number value of each of the first 15 digits of Pi: 3.14159265358979. Grouping information in chunks increases the effectiveness of mnemonics. For instance, “Roy G. Biv” chunks seven colors into three short pieces. Additionally, arbitrary, and especially bizarre, associations are often remembered better than logical ones."
 },
 {
  "id": 141,
  "topic": "Cognitive-Affective Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Contrast the Cannon-Bard theory of emotion with the James-Lange theory of emotion. Include a discussion of the sequence of events represented in each theory.",
  "answer": "William James and Carl Lange each proposed nearly identical theories of emotion in the 1880s (1884 and 1887). Combined, they became known as the James-Lange theory of emotion. Contrary to popular belief at the time, which held that physiological reactions follow aroused emotions, this theory proposed that physiological reactions come first, and our perceptions of emotional states follow. The sequence of events in the James-Lange theory is as follows: Event → arousal → interpretation → emotion. This sequence states that something (an environmental event or stimulus) arouses physiological responses that ready us for action, as in the “fight-orflight” stress response. We interpret those bodily symptoms as particular feelings, such as fear, anxiety, anger, etc. Cannon and Bard contradicted the James-Lange theory with their theory of emotion in 1927. They proposed that emotions and physiological signs occur together. The sequence of events in this theory is as follows: Event → Simultaneous arousal and emotion. Neurobiologically, the thalamus receives a message and simultaneously sends signals to the amygdala, which is associated with emotions; and the autonomic nervous system, which causes symptoms such as tensed muscles, dry mouth, racing heart, etc."
 },
 {
  "id": 142,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe some recent research findings about differential influences of the sociocultural factor of gender on cognitive perceptions.",
  "answer": "Recently, some researchers investigated how sexual harassment affects the mental well-being of women and men. They used data collected in a military survey. They found that women and men have different perceptions of harassment, and that these differing perceptions have differential influences on their psychological well-being. The investigators classified sexual harassment as either “bothersome,” meaning it was irritating and offensive, but did not provoke fear or harm the victim’s psychological wellbeing; or “frightening,” meaning it was threatening, “scary,” and harmful to the victim’s mental well-being. Men reported feeling distress due to both types of harassment. Women, however, only reported distress when they experienced “frightening” harassment. The researchers did not conclude based on these findings that harassment is less harmful to women. However, they speculate that due to women’s lifelong experiences with harassment, they have developed coping mechanisms to mitigate distress. Men, on the other hand, may not possess such strategies. Other researchers add that women may perceive “bothersome” sexist behaviors as the norm. Therefore, they avoid complaining to avoid being viewed as “weak” or “whiny.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 143,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize some elements of other psychological theories included in Attribution Theory. Explain the significant general assumption of Attribution Theory known as the self-serving bias.",
  "answer": "Attribution Theory greatly influences several contemporary psychological theories, particularly ones related to academic motivation. Attribution Theory incorporates Behaviorism by proposing that maintaining positive self-perceptions is a strong motivation for learning. Attribution Theory incorporates Cognitive Theory and the concept that Bandura termed selfefficacy (confidence in our ability to succeed in a certain behavior) by proposing that our self-perceptions influence how we interpret our successes and failures. Attribution Theory also posits that these interpretations will influence our likelihood of engaging in the same behaviors in the future. This likelihood depends on the relative success or failure of our behaviors and our explanations for these successes and failures. A significant assumption made by Attribution Theory is that to maintain the most positive self-image possible, we tend to attribute our successes to internal causes (our own ability and\/or effort), but usually attribute our failures to external causes (factors outside of ourselves and our control, such as a bad teacher, bad luck, etc.). This is known as the selfserving bias."
 },
 {
  "id": 144,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain some recent research results that may explain how cultural factors can influence our cognitions, beliefs, and behaviors related to social concern and sympathy for others.",
  "answer": "Some researchers found that when Americans were primed to think about decision-making, they were more against legislation for the common good, such as taxing “gas-guzzler” cars, affirmative action, etc. Social attitudes of participants in India, however, were not influenced by such priming. An Indian researcher working in America explains that choices are expected to be plentiful and accessible to all Americans. In India, however, choices are not associated with an individual’s identity. Even minor choices in America are important because of the control and individuality they confer, but Indians are not as interested in “…expressing personality through purchases.” When primed to consider decision-making, Americans assume others can control their actions and circumstances. Therefore, the consequences are “their problem.” Indians, who do not equate every choice with control, are less likely to feel that others decide their own fates, so they remain sympathetic to others’ plights. The Indian researcher suggests political rhetoric focused on choice, such as multiple healthcare options, could decrease Americans’ interest in bettering society."
 },
 {
  "id": 145,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify four factors described in Attribution Theory that influence academic achievement motivation. Describe the characteristics of each factor according to the theory’s three bipolar characteristics of attributes: internal\/external, stable\/unstable, and controllable\/uncontrollable. Identify the influence of individual perceptions on these characteristics and thus on motivation.",
  "answer": "According to Attribution Theory, the four factors influencing academic achievement motivation are ability, task difficulty, effort, and luck. Ability is a fairly internal, stable, and uncontrollable factor. Task difficulty is an external, stable, and mostly uncontrollable factor. Effort is an internal, unstable, and controllable factor. Luck is an external, unstable, and uncontrollable factor. However, despite these descriptions, individual perceptions determine a factor’s characteristics for each individual. For example, for someone who believes he or she is a “lucky person,” luck becomes ability in this paradigm. It is seen as internal and stable rather than external and unstable. It is uncontrollable in both cases. Someone who believes he or she made great effort but did not will regard the outcome as less controllable than it was. Someone who believes an objectively easy task was difficult will also perceive having less control over its outcome. Regarding motivation, the individual’s perceptions and attributions for success or failure determine how much effort he or she will expend on the same task or behavior in the future."
 },
 {
  "id": 146,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify three sets of bipolar characteristics of attributes described in Attribution Theory. Define the fundamental attribution error.",
  "answer": "According to Attribution Theory, we explain our successes and failures by attributing them to certain causes. The cause we attribute our success or failure to is (1) either internal or external—our ability and\/or effort vs. things outside us. Attributions are also (2) either stable or unstable. Stable causes are likely to produce the same outcome every time we engage in the same behavior. Unstable causes can produce different outcomes due to different instances of the same behavior. Our attributions of success and failure are also (3) either controllable or uncontrollable. We either believe we can change the causes of our successes and failures if we want to, or that we cannot readily change them. When we underestimate external attributes and overestimate internal attributes for others’ behaviors, especially with strangers, this is the fundamental attribution error. If a stranger is rude, we more likely think “What a jerk” than “He or she must be having a bad day.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 147,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify five factors that influence our attraction to others according to research findings in social psychology, and describe some examples.",
  "answer": "There are five factors that influence attraction. The first is proximity. We form the majority of our friendships with people who live close to us. For example, if there is assigned seating in classes and other groups, people are more likely to have friends whose last names start with the same letter. Association is another factor. We associate our opinions of people with our feelings about the situation. For instance, you may find somebody more likeable if you meet them during an activity you enjoy than during one you hate. The third factor is similarity. If you meet someone while participating in an activity you both hate, your agreement constitutes similarity, promoting attraction. You could become friends through a mutually despised activity. The fourth factor is reciprocal liking. We tend to feel more attracted to people who are attracted to us. Being liked enhances our self-esteem. Feeling good around someone promotes attraction to him or her. The final factor is physical attractiveness. We gravitate toward people we find attractive and those who we perceive as similar to us in terms of how attractive they are."
 },
 {
  "id": 148,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify the combinations of attribution characteristics associated with students’ greatest persistence in attempting academic tasks according to Attribution Theory, and describe some examples.",
  "answer": "According to Attribution Theory, the causes to which we attribute our successes or failures can be internal or external, stable or unstable, and controllable or uncontrollable. Students are most likely to be most persistent at an academic task when they attribute their success either to internal, unstable, controllable factors, such as the amount of effort they made; or to internal, stable, uncontrollable factors that are sometimes disrupted by other factors. An example of the latter is that a student may perceive herself or himself as having good ability, but also perceives that ability as being affected occasionally by bad luck. Students are most likely to persist at academic tasks when they attribute their failures to internal, unstable, controllable factors, such as the amount of effort they made. A student is more likely to keep trying when they think “I didn’t try hard enough; I’ll try harder next time” than when they think “I tried as hard as I could; I must not have the ability” or “I did my best; the task was too hard.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 149,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how the primacy effect can lead to the actor-observer effect during the process of person perception, and define each term. Define the process of social categorization and state its effects on our person perception. Include two examples.",
  "answer": "The primacy effect is our tendency to form opinions and judgments about people based on our first impressions. The actor-observer effect is our tendency to blame other people’s actions on their personalities (internal factors), but blame our own actions on the situation (external factors). Often, the primacy effect leads to the actor-observer effect—our first impression of somebody is the basis for our opinion of their personality. Social categorization is the process of classifying somebody into a certain social category based on something we observed about them. Social categorization affects our person perception by influencing what we do and do not notice about the person and how we judge them after we have placed them into a certain social category. For example, when researchers randomly classified students as “good” or “bad” students, teachers gave better grades to those labeled “good” students. In another study, mentally healthy individuals who checked into mental hospitals were diagnosed with mental illnesses."
 },
 {
  "id": 150,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define person perception, the primacy effect, and the actorobserver effect as these concepts relate to social psychology.",
  "answer": "Person perception consists of the social-cognitive mental processes whereby we make judgments and conclusions about others’ qualities and motives. The primacy effect is the concept that our first impressions of people often influence our judgments about them the most. Knowing somebody for a long time mitigates the primacy effect. So does awareness of the effect. For instance, HR professionals and other personnel are sometimes trained to ignore their first impressions of others. The actorobserver effect is essentially a combination of the fundamental attribution error and the self-serving bias. It states that we attribute others’ actions to their internal personality traits, but we attribute our own actions to the external situation we are in at the time. The fundamental attribution error states that we underestimate the external and overestimate the internal as influencing others’ behaviors. The self-serving bias is at work when we credit our successes to our internal attributes, but blame our failures on external causes."
 },
 {
  "id": 151,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how mirroring nonverbal communication enhances social interactions and how current research using computers can facilitate this process.",
  "answer": "Social and social-cognitive psychologists already know that when one person mimics or mirrors the facial expressions, gestures, and body positions and movements of another person during an interaction, the person who is imitated feels more connected to the imitator. With today’s computer software that can create online avatars to stand in for users, this process can be facilitated. Instead of an individual having to consciously remember to imitate another person’s nonverbal behaviors during a conversation or other interaction, the user’s avatar can be programmed to make these adjustments automatically. Thus, the user enhances the interaction and relationship without making any additional cognitive or physical effort. Researchers experimenting with this technology tested the concept with a “slow moving mirror.” When an avatar gave a message while copying the head movements of participants, they found the avatar more intelligent, believable, trustworthy, and persuasive."
 },
 {
  "id": 152,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Give an example of how computer technology has the potential to enhance social interactions and allow us to gain more from interactions than what is possible with face-to-face, in-person encounters.",
  "answer": "Researchers are experimenting with software programs, add-ons, and other devices designed to facilitate enhanced communication. Despite current criticisms that online interactions lack nonverbal cues, scientists believe that in the future, long-distance communication using technology may in many ways become even more intimate than conversations in person. For example, when we have conversations face to face, we can only make direct eye contact with one person at a time. In computer-mediated environments, this restriction can be removed. In anything from a simple video call, available today from Skype and other brands, to completely immersive environments with virtual rooms, suits with motion sensors, and goggles, it is possible to engineer a person’s gaze so that everybody participating via computers can get individual eye contact from the same individual. As a researcher points out, several children could be given the impression that they are getting their parents’ undivided attention through the use of such techniques."
 },
 {
  "id": 153,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain one role that sound (apart from speech sounds) plays in mediating social interactions. Describe how this effect has been replicated in virtual reality environments, how audio enhancement of digital conversation influences intimacy with others, and how this enhancement could enhance digital communications in the future.",
  "answer": "A research team found that when participants chatting in a virtual reality environment could hear another person’s heartbeat, they stepped back to increase the space between them. The team leader notes this is how we react in real-life environments when we feel an interaction is too intimate. Moreover, after chatting in virtual reality while hearing the heartbeats of conversation partners, participants felt they were more connected to their partners. In fact, the increased feelings of intimacy reported by participants were equal in magnitude to the increases in intimacy they experienced from making direct eye contact. While online interactions are often criticized for being less complete and intimate than in-person interactions, these findings indicate there are many ways to improve digital exchanges to afford enhanced intimacy. In addition, a research team leader believes that in the future, tactile indicators letting us feel another’s heartbeat (which may be possible through wearing a special ring, for instance) while talking on the phone could further enhance digital communication."
 },
 {
  "id": 154,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain how today’s technology can simulate physical contact, and describe how this can influence social cognitions and emotional connections achieved through nonverbal behavior in social interactions.",
  "answer": "Some researchers are working with a device that allows people to engage in remote handshakes. When two users in separate locations each hold a joystick connected to a computer, this device enables them to feel the other’s handshake through the joystick. This technology has the potential to improve the intimacy and quality of future digital interactions by incorporating the sense of touch usually missing from remote connections. Moreover, remote tactile contact also allows for the enhanced impressions we form of others when they mirror our nonverbal communications. We tend to like people more when they mimic our movements and expressions. Experimenters studying the digital remote handshake device gave some participants the idea that they were shaking another’s hand when they were actually feeling their own handshakes. The researchers found that those unwittingly shaking their own hands liked the “other” hand-shaker and were “nicer” in negotiations with the “other.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 155,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Evolutionary sources of social behavior inform our physiological responses to contemporary situations. Describe some physical changes that accompany modern-day anxiety and nervousness, and identify their sources.",
  "answer": "escaping the danger posed by predators, attackers, or natural disasters. Today, we exhibit the same responses to important events such as making public speeches or proposing marriage. When the brain is alerted to danger, eye blinks become faster to avoid missing what comes next. Increased flow of adrenaline makes muscles contract to fight or run; our hands shake, our jaws clench, and our teeth may chatter. Adrenaline and cortisol, both of which are stress hormones, activate the skin’s sweat glands, increasing perspiration. “Survival mode” tends to shut down the frontal lobe, so we may stutter when speaking or go blank in the middle of a sentence. Blood is diverted from the gastrointestinal system to the muscles (for fighting or running), so the stomach may knot and\/or we may experience nausea. Blood is also redirected to arm and leg muscles (again, for fighting or running). It moves away from the muscle keeping the bladder shut, which is why panic or high anxiety can trigger the urge to urinate and even result in wetting accidents."
 },
 {
  "id": 156,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe one way in which the sounds of people’s voices influence our perceptions during social interactions. Identify one way in which this has recently been tested and proven using digital technology.",
  "answer": "Psychologists have known for some time that when one person mimics the physical positions, gestures, and movements of another person during a social interaction, the person being copied tends to like the person copying them more. This effect is more pronounced when the person being copied is not consciously aware of it. We also tend to like people more when they look similar to us. Research scientists have recently discovered that we not only like people more when their actions and appearances are similar to ours, but also when the sounds of their voices are similar. An experimenter used digital technology to alter speakers’ voices very subtly so that they sounded more like the voices of participants. This effect was not obvious enough for participants to be aware of it. Participants preferred voices more similar to their own without knowing why. The experimenter concluded that when we do not consciously realize someone sounds similar to us, the other person has a greater influence on us."
 },
 {
  "id": 157,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe how our perceptions of other people’s physical attractiveness influence our perceptions of their personalities and character traits.",
  "answer": "Past research has found that when we meet somebody whom we find physically attractive, we tend to assume that this individual has a personality that is just as attractive as his or her appearance. However, current researchers have discovered that in addition to this tendency to associate personality with appearance (which may or may not be an accurate assumption), we are also able to correctly detect the individual character strengths of a person whom we find attractive. Researchers had participants chat with strangers and then rate their appearances and character attributes. Abstract personality traits such as conscientiousness were more accurately detected by participants when they occurred in the individuals participants perceived as the best looking. The investigators concluded that we are more apt to notice subtle nuances that are cues signaling character in people whom we find personally appealing. As one researcher stated, “We judge a book by its cover, but when it’s beautiful, we read it more closely.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 158,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some current research findings about how physical attractiveness influences behavior that take the evolutionary origins of human social behaviors into account.",
  "answer": "In ancient Greece, Homer famously called Helen of Troy “the face that launched a thousand ships.” Today, attractions to war are still inspired by female beauty. Researchers found that men shown pictures of attractive women did not display increases in general aggression, but did respond to words and images related to war. They also tended to agree with pro-war statements. Scientists explain these results by stating that since male sperm outnumber female eggs, male combat eliminates reproductive competition by reducing the male population. Other researchers found that people are more likely to repay money or a favor to healthy-looking people than sickly-looking ones. In evolutionary terms, we ingratiate ourselves with people who will live longer and have more opportunity to return our favors, and we associate physical beauty with good health. Today’s media influences who we view as role models. When participants were shown movie clips with more and less attractive actresses in aggressive and nonaggressive roles, research participants chose the most attractive and aggressive heroine (Angelina Jolie as Tomb Raider’s Lara Croft) as a role model."
 },
 {
  "id": 159,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some of the motivations and effects of “kissing up” (to others) behaviors, which some people use to facilitate social climbing, that have been described by personality and social psychologists.",
  "answer": "While some people use social tactics such as relational aggression to further social climbing, others engage in the opposite strategy. This involves ingratiating and obsequious behaviors to curry favor with those holding social status or power, and ignoring others’ disapproval and distaste for their actions. As a psychological researcher noted, two main bases for achieving status within a group are what you can contribute and what you are willing to sacrifice. Obsequious behavior indicates willingness to selfsacrifice. Another factor is that relationships involve a significant amount of exchange between individuals. When it is not clear what a person entering a situation can offer in exchange for what others offer, “kissing up” may be the best strategy. In addition, brown-nosing behaviors are reinforced by the recipients because people are suckers for flattery. Even when observers identify sycophantic behavior, the recipients—even ones with high selfesteem—eat it up. The fact that the recipients do not recognize the manipulation does not stem from vanity, but rather from a desire to be liked and admired."
 },
 {
  "id": 160,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Recount some findings of personality psychologists about the characteristics of teens who engage in relational aggression versus adults who engage in such behaviors. Include a discussion of adult group dynamics involving bullies.",
  "answer": "Relational aggression is not physical but involves spreading vicious lies or rumors about others, taking credit for others’ accomplishments, backstabbing, etc. Relational aggression is correlated with envy, narcissism, low self-esteem, and high social intelligence. This combination facilitates manipulation. Those who advance socially by stepping on others understand the structures of friendships and groups, and exploit this knowledge. Some psychologists call this a “Machiavellian” (the end justifies the means) personality type. It is characterized by cynicism about human nature, flexible morals, and giving goal achievement priority over relationships. These personalities cause much damage for teens. However, research finds that these behaviors are less tolerated by adults. Adult group dynamics are such that if someone tries to gain power via manipulation or coercion, the group members will unite against the bully. Psychologists find that groups benefit most from leaders with both ability and strong group orientations."
 },
 {
  "id": 161,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss recent findings about correlations between intelligence and sexual behavior.",
  "answer": "Some current research finds a negative correlation between intelligence and frequency of sex, which one sociologist calls “a bit dismaying.” The newest National Survey of Family Growth found men with college degrees half as likely to have had four sex partners or more in the past year as men with high school diplomas. Or, as a CDC demographer and health scientist notes, they are half as likely to admit to having had this many partners. Public health researchers found that the majority of teenage virgins are the ones with the highest IQs. They speculate smarter teens consider the consequences of sex more. However, these adolescents also postpone kissing, so perhaps it is the time and attention they devote to education that precludes sexual activity. Life history theory states that adults with superior executive function use slower life history strategies. Evolutionary psychologists say smarter adults have less sex and fewer partners, but greater resources for offspring. Intelligence does not help men obtain more sex, but money does, and intelligence can help them obtain more money."
 },
 {
  "id": 162,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the cultural stereotype of “gold diggers” from the perspective of evolutionary psychology. Identify the role of goals in gold digging and describe the hedonic treadmill theory.",
  "answer": "For many years, our culture has stereotyped and judged attractive women who are apparently willing to exchange their good looks, youth, and sex for security and social status. However, this stereotype overlooks the evolutionary foundations of such behavior. According to evolutionary psychologists, human females are innately programmed to seek traits in mates that will help them acquire resources and advance their future status. These traits include intelligence, drive, ambition, and industriousness. Mates who are successful and dependable help assure the survival of a woman’s children. One exception to this evolutionary explanation is women who exchange their youth and beauty with wealthy older men for financial and material benefits. Their motivation is not marriage or children. To explain the reasons behind this behavior, psychologists cite the hedonic treadmill theory: as soon as we achieve a goal such as social status, we target another goal rather than enjoying the one we have just achieved. In cost-benefit terms, women who value money and what it buys over love may trade their personal assets for it."
 },
 {
  "id": 163,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify some things patients can do during doctor visits to prevent or minimize their distortion of symptom reporting due to stress and anxious or depressed moods.",
  "answer": "New research by psychologists suggests that anxiety and depression, whether chronic or short-term, cause people to over report their physiological symptoms to doctors. Anxious patients tend to overestimate their current symptoms, while depressed patients tend to overestimate their past symptoms. Psychologists advise that patients should not attempt to conceal chronic anxiety or depression from their physicians. They also advise that patients experiencing short-term stress should use deep breathing, meditation, and\/or other relaxation techniques to calm down, which can eliminate the symptom-reporting bias. For depressed patients, psychologists find that keeping a daily log of their medical symptoms is very helpful, especially between doctor visits. Keeping track of symptoms between appointments allows patients to bring concrete data to their physicians. Another suggestion from a psychologist who researched affective influences on health symptoms is for patients to report not only physical symptoms to the doctor, but also feelings. This allows the doctor to consider the whole patient and his or her condition."
 },
 {
  "id": 164,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Describe the personality and social psychology research findings suggesting that affective states such as anxiety and depression influence our medical symptoms and how we report them.",
  "answer": "Psychological research is discovering that when we are in bad moods, we are likely to interpret symptoms such as upset stomachs or headaches, which may or may not signify physical illness, as real signs of illness. A new study by scientists revealed that anxious people tend to exaggerate the physical symptoms they are experiencing at the time, and that depressed people tend to exaggerate the number of physical symptoms they experienced in the past. As a psychological researcher observed, people with high anxiety are hyper-vigilant and self-focused. They are alert to danger, and pay close attention to themselves and the bodily sensations they are experiencing. These qualities are conducive to their giving inflated reports of their symptoms. People with depression tend to ruminate over negative past experiences, so their retrospective views are distorted. The result is that they give inflated reports of their past symptoms. Even those without chronic anxiety or depression can report symptoms inaccurately under the influence of momentary anxiousness or depressed mood."
 },
 {
  "id": 165,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain the findings of new research studies that suggest unpleasant sensory stimuli involving smell and taste can influence people’s moral judgment.",
  "answer": "Personality and social psychologists are discovering that unpleasant sensory stimuli such as unpleasant odors and tastes can actually affect our moral judgments. A psychologist attributes this effect to the kind of associations that are formed between paired stimuli in classical conditioning. In other words, we mistakenly associate an emotion we are feeling at a certain time —regardless of what stimulated that emotion—with whatever we are thinking about at that time. When research participants sat next to a garbage can that had been sprayed with novelty “fart spray” while considering controversial subjects such as legalizing marriage between first cousins or driving to work vs. walking, they were more likely to find them immoral. They associated their emotion of disgust, triggered by the bad smell, with the subjects. Similarly, another study showed people drinking a bittertasting beverage made harsher moral judgments than those drinking water or sweet punch."
 },
 {
  "id": 166,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify an example of the influence of environmental physical stimuli on moral judgment that has been suggested by new research in personality and social psychology.",
  "answer": "Most of us tend to believe that our moral characters consist of strong, stable concepts of right and wrong. However, new research suggests that our senses of morality and ethics are actually quite changeable, and are surprisingly sensitive to physical influences from the environment, even subtle or minor ones such as changes in lighting or faint odors. Some personality and social psychology researchers have discovered that people who have just cleaned their hands with antiseptic wipes are more likely to judge such controversial social issues as recreational drug use or pornography as immoral than people who have not just cleaned their hands. Researchers also found that individuals who envision themselves as being perfectly groomed because they have clean hair, clean fingernails, and clean clothing are more likely to make firmer or harsher judgments about issues involving justice or ethics."
 },
 {
  "id": 167,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Explain what psychological research has found about how a simple thing such as wearing sunglasses influences our behavior.",
  "answer": "Psychological researchers have found that both our moral cognitions and our moral behavior can be influenced by simple environmental and physical changes more significantly than previously thought. Researchers recently found that people judged accounts of moral and immoral behaviors more extremely (as more moral or more immoral) when they heard about them with their eyes closed than with their eyes open. They attribute this to the greater emotional engagement afforded by the mental imaging made possible by closing the eyes. Other researchers found that when people are playing a game involving cooperation, they behave more selfishly when they are wearing sunglasses. Also, people who are offered money to cheat on a test are more likely to do so in dimly-lit rooms than brightly-lit ones. Psychologists think that when our eyes or entire bodies are less visible, we may feel more anonymous, which gives us more license to behave badly."
 },
 {
  "id": 168,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some research findings related to how people’s moral judgments are influenced by closing their eyes, and identify researchers’ hypotheses about why this occurs.",
  "answer": "Although we tend to believe our morality is stable or even fixed, research is finding that this is not the case. New research in personality and social psychology suggests that many environmental and physiological changes can alter our ethical judgments. For example, experimenters had participants close their eyes while they heard descriptions of actions that were representative of typical kindness and others that were representative of typical wickedness. Participants judged the kind actions as more ethical and the wicked actions as more unethical than participants who listened to the same accounts with their eyes open. A researcher pointed out that we often base such moral judgments on our emotional reactions. The more emotionally outraged you feel about a reported misdeed, the more morally wrong you think that misdeed is. Researchers think that when we close our eyes, we are better able to create visual mental images of relevant scenes, which enhances our emotional engagement."
 },
 {
  "id": 169,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define expectancy bias as it relates to psychological research and give an example of its influence.",
  "answer": "When researchers only observe what they expect to see, they are exhibiting expectancy bias. Expectancy bias is closely related to confirmation bias, which is when we attend to what confirms our beliefs and ignore what contradicts them. An example of expectancy bias in research was found in a study in which experimenters asked two groups of psychology students to train rats to press a lever to get food. All rats were randomly selected from the same litter, but experimenters told one group of students they were getting very smart rats, and told the other group their rats were “slow learners.” The students’ data showed “smarter” rats performed better than “slow” ones. The students did not consciously or unconsciously falsify these data, which were accurate. However, the rats appeared to perform better for more enthusiastic audiences. Follow-up questionnaires found students were more enthusiastic, pleasant, encouraging, and interested in “bright” rats’ performance. Thus, the students’ expectancy bias altered the rats’ behavior."
 },
 {
  "id": 170,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define confirmation bias and give some examples of it. Summarize a research study that found neurological evidence of this bias.",
  "answer": "Confirmation bias is our common tendency to remember things confirming our beliefs but ignore things contradicting them. Gamblers have better memories of the times they won than of the times they lost. Similarly, people remember astrological predictions that came true but forget those that did not. Neuroscientists used fMRI before the 2004 U.S. presidential election to scan the brains of participants with strong political views while they listened to a favored politician making contradictory statements. They found that participants’ brain circuits associated with reasoning suddenly stopped their activity, but brain areas associated most with emotions continued to be active. Psychologists have commented that this change in neural activity made it look as though participants’ brains were saying they did not want to hear anything that contradicted their beliefs. Festinger’s Cognitive Dissonance Theory supports the need to resolve cognitive conflict. This study showed that confirmation bias can occur physiologically within the brain in response to contradictions."
 },
 {
  "id": 171,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define stereotype threat. Give an example of research demonstrating the effects of stereotype threat on people’s behavior.",
  "answer": "Stereotypes are generalizations about all members of a group. Stereotype threat is a condition in which members of a stereotyped group cannot efficiently utilize their mental abilities because of the negative elements of the stereotype. This impairs their performance across life domains. For example, in a 2008 study, researchers assigned a golf task to women who rated themselves as above average athletically. They told all of the participants that this task measured “natural ability.” They additionally told some of the women that gender differences in whether participants could perform the task had been found in prior studies. They asked all women to give a 100 percent effort so researchers could test their “natural skills.” Even with the request for 100 percent effort, the women who were informed of gender differences took more strokes to finish eight holes of a golf course than those not given this message. Thus, the stereotype threat—the idea that women would not perform as well as men at golf—impaired the performance of the women exposed to it."
 },
 {
  "id": 172,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss stereotypes, including the role of social categorization in stereotyping. Give an example of behavioral confirmation.",
  "answer": "We organize our social environment by categorizing ourselves and others into groups. We tend to favor members of the group we identify with due to the attraction principle of similarity. This leads to a mentality involving “in groups” and “out groups.” When we make blanket generalizations about members of other groups (out groups), this is stereotyping. Some stereotypes can contribute to a kind of self-fulfilling prophecy called behavioral confirmation. For example, somebody who stereotypes all Asian people as being “terrible drivers” might not want to get in the car with an Asian driver as a result. If this person has to ride with an Asian friend and is obviously anxious about it, the friend who is driving could easily be influenced to drive more poorly than usual by the passenger’s negative attitude, confirming the passenger’s stereotype about Asians being bad drivers."
 },
 {
  "id": 173,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize a landmark social psychology research study on reversing prejudice known as the Robbers Cave experiment. Include an overview of the study’s successes and failures.",
  "answer": "Sherif et al. reported (1961 and 1988) on an experiment they conducted in 1954 at a summer camp in Oklahoma’s Robbers Cave State Park. Two groups of boys formed bonds through camp activities, and each group was unaware of the other. Then, they were introduced through competitions such as tug-of-war, baseball games, and football games. The groups quickly became violent in their opposition to each other. Experimenters tried propaganda, praising each group to the other; this was ineffective. They tried uniting them in non-competing activities such as watching a movie in the same location; this also failed. They finally discovered that problems that could only be solved through working together to achieve a common goal resolved the animosity. Researchers made the camp truck break down. The collective strength of both groups was needed to pull it uphill. Hostilities gave way to mutual dependence, and the boys began making friends with members of the other group. Thus, researchers concluded that personal interaction and collaboration are required to reverse prejudice."
 },
 {
  "id": 174,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss how prejudice begins, and address the roles of social categorization and stereotypes.",
  "answer": "Humans organize their social environment by categorizing themselves and others into groups. The most common and simple form of categorization is placing people similar to us and ones different from us into separate groups, which creates a “me versus not me” orientation. This develops into an “us versus them” orientation when groups that we identify with as members become “in groups” and those we do not identify with become “out groups.” In-group biases can create favoritism for in-group members without the biases against out-group members that represent prejudice. However, when people believe stereotypes (broad generalizations about entire groups) of out-group members and discriminate against them accordingly, they develop learned prejudices. These prejudices can readily develop into racism, sexism, and other forms of discrimination against specific groups."
 },
 {
  "id": 175,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Identify four motives for engaging in prosocial behaviors.",
  "answer": "In the wake of major disasters such as Hurricane Katrina in America, an earthquake in China, floods in Haiti, and an earthquake, tsunami, and nuclear emergency in Japan, people within and outside these countries have responded to help. Some of these people even risked their own lives to do so. Four motives (Batson, 1994) have been proposed to explain these prosocial behaviors. The first is altruism, which is when individuals put the needs and welfare of others above their own. The second is egoism, or selfinterest. People may help others to receive a favor from them in return, or to be rewarded with money, fame, or praise. The third is collectivism, actions benefiting a certain group. People may engage in helping behavior to better the situation of their family, their political party, their fraternity or sorority, or other groups to which they belong. The final motive is principlism. People may perform prosocial acts to fulfill their own moral principles, religious principles, or civic principles. There may be more than one motive for a single behavior, and each motive may apply to different situations."
 },
 {
  "id": 176,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of human aggression, including genetic influences on physical vs. social aggression and the difference between impulsive and instrumental aggression. Provide some examples to explain your answer.",
  "answer": "Physical aggression includes hitting, kicking, biting others, etc., while social (or relational) aggression includes behavior such as maligning others’ reputations, spreading mean rumors, and influencing or manipulating others to dislike certain individuals. Twin studies have analyzed genetic influences on both types of aggression. Identical (monozygotic) twins come from the same egg and share the same genetic material; fraternal (dizygotic) twins come from separate eggs and are more genetically different. A 2005 study of six-year-old twins found that 50 to 60 percent of differences in physical aggression could be attributed to genetic factors, while only 20 percent of differences in social aggression could be attributed to genetic influences. Impulsive aggression is not premeditated. An example is when two cars crash and the drivers both get upset and become involved in a fist fight. Instrumental aggression is the opposite. It is calculated and meant to achieve a specific goal, as when somebody deliberately shoves a frail woman to steal her purse."
 },
 {
  "id": 177,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Summarize the elaboration likelihood model as it relates to persuasion. Include a discussion of the differential definitions of central vs. peripheral routes to persuasion.",
  "answer": "The elaboration likelihood model (Petty et al, 2005; Petty & Briñol, 2008) represents how likely people are to focus cognitively on the elaboration of a persuasive message they receive. In this model, the central route to persuasion involves careful thought about a persuasive message. The argument must be strong enough to change the recipient’s attitude. Such careful thinking is called “high elaboration” in this model. You would probably process an argument that gasoline should cost five dollars a gallon in this way. The peripheral route to persuasion does not utilize such critical thinking. Rather, the recipient reacts to more superficial cues. For example, when celebrities endorse products in advertisements, viewers are not persuaded by critically evaluating whether the celebrity prefers, cares about, or even uses the product, but rather by general positive feelings about the celebrity."
 },
 {
  "id": 178,
  "topic": "Social and Cultural Bases of Behavior",
  "question": "Define the Asch effect in psychology as it relates to social influences on individual functioning. Summarize one of Solomon Asch’s studies of conformity and what he found.",
  "answer": "The Asch effect represents the influence of a group’s majority on an individual’s judgments. Asch studied conformity (1940 and 1956) by informing male student volunteers they were participating in a study of “visual perception.” Students had to compare visual stimuli, and the correct answers were obvious. At first, there was unanimous agreement on which answers were correct. Then, experimenter confederates posing as participants began to give incorrect answers one by one. Finally, everybody agreed on the wrong answer except for the one student who was the actual subject in each group. Under this group pressure, only one quarter of participants stayed with their original (correct) answer, while three quarters agreed with the majority’s incorrect choice once or more. In related studies, the majority of subjects caved under group pressure, denying their own correct perceptions of reality. Independent individuals regularly refuse to conform, even when upset by the discrepancy. However, the majority of people relinquish their personal standards in favor of group standards."
 },
 {
  "id": 179,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define ego defense mechanisms as they relate to Freudian theory. Identify and describe several of these mechanisms using examples.",
  "answer": "Freud proposed that to resolve psychic conflicts between the id’s desire to express its impulses and the superego’s desire to deny them, the ego acts as a mediator and creates defense mechanisms to reduce anxiety, and to maintain a positive self-image and socially acceptable behavior. By using the defense mechanism of denial, people protect themselves from unpleasant realities by denying that they exist. This is common among substance abusers, child abusers, people with anger management issues, and those who engage in high-risk behaviors. Another defense mechanism is displacement. People release bottled-up feelings—usually of anger—onto recipients less threatening than those who caused the feelings. For example, when a man’s boss yells at him, yelling back would get the man fired, so he goes home and yells at his wife instead. In the defense mechanism of fantasy, people seek gratification for desires that are thwarted in reality through imaginary scenarios. An example is daydreaming about getting revenge on someone, winning the love of someone unattainable, or being rich, famous, or extremely successful."
 },
 {
  "id": 180,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the foundation of all psychodynamic theories of personality. Identify the three main personality structures and summarize their features. Explain these personality structures with an example.",
  "answer": "The foundation of all psychodynamic theories is Freud’s Psychoanalytic Theory. Freud proposed that the personality is organized into three main structures: the id, the ego, and the superego. The id is regulated by the pleasure principle. It represents the person’s most basic, unconscious drives and impulses. It is the personality’s energy source, and motivates people to act. The ego is regulated by the reality principle. It represents the conscious, rational mind. It acts as a mediator between the id’s desire for immediate gratification and the superego’s moral rules of right and wrong. The superego is likened to the conscience. The superego incorporates the ego ideal, the individual’s idea of the kind of person he or she should be. For example, if you want something belonging to someone else, your id says, “I want that. Take it!” Your ego says, “If I take it, I will get arrested for stealing.” Your superego says, “Stealing is wrong. I should not steal even if I would not get caught.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 181,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and explain several ego defense mechanisms described in Freudian psychoanalytic theory using examples.",
  "answer": "Freud said that our egos create defense mechanisms to manage anxiety from inner conflicts. One of these defense mechanics is reaction formation: to keep threatening impulses from being expressed, people “form reactions,” espousing opposite attitudes and behaviors as protective barriers.\n\nBoth children and adults who are attracted to someone but cannot accept the sexual tension may make a great show of their contempt or hatred for the secretly desired other. In regression, an individual reverts to an earlier developmental stage. A four-year-old whose parents have a new baby may regress to more babyish behaviors to compete for parental attention. People may also regress to lower others’ demands or expectations. The most basic ego defense mechanism is repression: a person pushes threatening or painful thoughts, feelings, and memories out of the consciousness and into the unconscious. Freud believed children repress sexual and aggressive impulses toward their parents. A spouse unhappy in a marriage may “forget” their anniversary. Sublimation is channeling sexual or aggressive impulses into socially acceptable activities. Examples are architects or builders who “erect” skyscrapers and individuals who release aggression by becoming professional boxers."
 },
 {
  "id": 182,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and explain several ego defense mechanisms described in Freudian theory.",
  "answer": "There are other Freudian defense mechanisms aside from denial (of reality), displacement (of emotion, usually anger), and fantasy (satisfying frustrated desires through imaginary events). One is identification, in which people boost their feelings of self-worth by identifying themselves with another person, group, or institution, often one with exemplary status. Isolation is an ego defense mechanism that is also known as compartmentalization. By separating conflicting attitudes into individual mental “compartments” so that they are never considered concurrently or in relationship to each other, the individual eliminates inner conflict. Isolation can also involve separating the emotional content from hurtful events. Projection involves blaming others for one’s problems or attributing one’s own unacceptable impulses to others. Abusive individuals often blame their victims, saying things like “You made me hurt you by what you did.” A person who cannot accept that he or she hates somebody might say to that person: “You hate me.” In rationalization, people try to justify their behavior as logical or rational, and hence acceptable."
 },
 {
  "id": 183,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some characteristics that were found in research to correlate with high and low scores for Eysenck’s personality traits of psychoticism and neuroticism.",
  "answer": "Various research studies have found that people with high neuroticism (N) scores are more likely to experience anxiety and depression. Typically, they have trouble sleeping and display a variety of psychosomatic symptoms (medical symptoms caused by psychological problems). People with “high N” scores typically overreact with negative emotions and are more emotionally aroused by everyday stressors. They also have more difficulty recovering from emotional upset. People with “low N” scores are more emotionally stable, calmer, and more even-tempered. They react more slowly to stressful occurrences and recover more quickly from emotionally upsetting events. Those with high psychoticism (P) scores are often loners, and display insensitivity to others’ suffering, aggression, and cruel or inhumane behaviors. Men’s P scores are typically about twice as high as women’s. People with “high P” scores often seek novelty, disregard danger, and exhibit antisocial tendencies. They are attracted to violent material and behaviors. “Low P” scorers tend to be deeply religious, while “high P” scorers are more cynical about religion."
 },
 {
  "id": 184,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the three major personality traits in Hans Eysenck’s trait model of personality, and outline the narrower traits included under each major trait.",
  "answer": "Eysenck divided the human personality into a hierarchy consisting of three major types of traits: psychoticism, neuroticism (vs. emotional stability), and extraversion-introversion. Under the psychoticism trait he included the narrower traits of aggression, coldness, egocentrism, being impersonal, impulsivity, being antisocial, lack of empathy, creativity, and toughmindedness. Under the neuroticism trait he included the narrower traits of anxiety, depression, guilt feelings, low self-esteem, tension, irrationality, shyness, moodiness, and emotionality. Under the extraversion-introversion trait he included the more specific traits associated with extraversion of sociability, liveliness, being active, assertiveness, sensation-seeking, being carefree, dominance, surgency, and being venturesome. He also included the more specific traits associated with introversion of seeming aloof or distant, being quieter, preferring a more moderate pace, passivity, less tolerance for sensory stimulation, conscientiousness, seriousness, organization, and risk aversion."
 },
 {
  "id": 185,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify some of the occupations associated with high or low scores for some of the personality factors on Cattell’s 16-Personality Factor Scales.",
  "answer": "Raymond Cattell designed a taxonomy of personality that lists 16 different personality factors (PF). Various occupational groups have been tested with Cattell’s PF scales. People in certain job groups tend to score higher or lower than the average on Cattell’s 16-Personality Factor Scales. Athletes and judges have high scores for dominance; janitors, cooks, and farmers have low scores. Air traffic controllers and military cadets have high scores for conformity, while university professors have low scores. Artists, musicians, and employment counselors have high scores for sensitivity; engineers have low scores. Accountants have high scores for suspiciousness. “Absent-minded professors,” artists, and research scientists have high scores for imagination and are more creative. Accountants and statisticians have high scores for self-sufficiency, and Antarctic explorers have some of the highest self-sufficiency scores of all occupational groups. Social workers have comparatively low scores in this category. Airline pilots have high scores for self-discipline."
 },
 {
  "id": 186,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the 16 personality factors in the scale created by Raymond Cattell, and describe any that are unclear.",
  "answer": "While one of the smallest personality trait taxonomies was Eysenck’s, which consisted of three main traits, Cattell’s was one of the largest, consisting of 16 personality factors (PF). He labeled them alphabetically.\n\nA: interpersonal warmth, similar to Eysenck’s trait of extraversion personable, easy to get along with, adapt to others’ needs, and like helping. B: intelligence. C: emotional stability, similar to Eysenck’s concept of low neuroticism – good emotional resources and self-control, and tolerate stress well. E: dominance – assertive, aggressive, competitive, forceful, and direct. F: impulsivity – lively, enthusiastic, and like variety G: conformity respect authority, are persistent and rigid, and dislike surprises. H: boldness. I: sensitivity – artistic, insecure, dependent, overprotected, and prefer reason over force. L: suspiciousness. M: imagination – impractical, unconventional, and unconcerned with trivia. N: shrewdness – diplomatic, polite, reserved, self-controlled, socially sophisticated, and poised. O: insecurity – worry, guilt, moodiness, anxiety, loneliness, depression, and sensitivity to criticism.\n\nQ1: radicalism – liberal attitudes, analytical and iconoclastic.\n\nQ2: self-sufficiency – prefer being alone, avoid group work, and don’t rely on support from others.\n\nQ3: self-discipline – organized, controlled, and neat.\n\nQ4: tension –anxiety, frustration, irritability, trouble sleeping, and taking a long time to calm down after being upset."
 },
 {
  "id": 187,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the markers used by Norman (1963) to define each of the big five personality traits.",
  "answer": "Norman used pairs of opposites as markers for each of the big five personality traits. For the trait of surgency (extraversion), he identified these markers: talkative-silent, sociable-reclusive, adventurous-cautious, and open-secretive. For the trait of agreeableness, he identified these markers: good natured-irritable, cooperative-negativistic, mild\/gentle-headstrong, and not jealous-jealous. For the trait of conscientiousness, he identified these markers: responsible-undependable, scrupulous-unscrupulous, persevering-quitting, and fussy\/tidy-careless. For the trait of emotional stability, he identified these markers: calm-anxious, composed-excitable, not hypochondriacal-hypochondriacal, and poised-nervous\/tense. For the trait of culture (also called intellect or imagination by others), he identified these markers:\n\nintellectual-unreflective\/narrow, artistic-non-artistic, imaginative-simple\/direct, and polished\/refined-crude\/boorish. Each person will fall somewhere on a continuum between these opposite extremes. For example, an individual might show greater or lesser degrees of calmness or anxiety, someone might be slightly jealous or somewhat jealous, etc."
 },
 {
  "id": 188,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize the history of the development of the five-factor taxonomy of personality traits",
  "answer": "Gordon Allport and H.S. Odbert began a lexical approach to personality research in the 1930s, identifying thousands of terms for personality traits found in the dictionary. Raymond Cattell used their list for additional lexical analysis. Computer technology was too limited in the 1940s for Cattell to conduct factor analysis on so many items, so he created a smaller list of trait clusters or groups. Fiske made a factor analysis of most (22 of 35) of Cattell’s clusters, and was the first to create a five-factor model in 1949. Tupes and Christal then identified the five factors in 1961 as surgency (extraversion), agreeableness, conscientiousness, emotional stability, and culture. Their structure was replicated by Norman in 1963, and then by many other researchers in the 1980s and 1990s, including McCrae and Costa. Research on the “big five” has proliferated over the last 20 years. McCrae and Costa designed the most widely-used test for the big five traits: the Neuroticism-Extraversion-Openness Personality Inventory, Revised (NEO-PI-R, 1989)."
 },
 {
  "id": 189,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify some combinations of the big five personality traits or dispositions that researchers have found are associated with specific life outcomes.",
  "answer": "Many researchers have found that the best predictors of getting good grades are high conscientiousness and high emotional stability. These students are more likely to study and less likely to procrastinate. Risky sexual behaviors such as not using protection and having many partners are associated with high extraversion, high neuroticism, low conscientiousness, and low agreeableness. Alcohol consumption is associated with high extraversion and low conscientiousness. The latter is also associated with increased drinking over time. Those who climb Mount Everest tend to have high scores for extraversion and emotional stability, but also psychoticism. Happiness and an overall positive affect are associated with high extraversion and low neuroticism. People who do volunteer work tend to have high agreeableness and high extraversion scores. Those who are less likely to join labor unions have low extraversion and high emotional stability scores. People who are more forgiving when others have wronged them tend to have high agreeableness and emotional stability scores. In businesses, leadership effectiveness is associated with high extraversion, agreeableness, conscientiousness, and emotional stability scores."
 },
 {
  "id": 190,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Name the key adjectives identified by Goldberg (1990) as markers for the each of the big five personality traits.",
  "answer": "Lewis R. Goldberg is known for conducting the most systematic research on the big five personality traits. He developed one-word adjectives to describe each trait. Similar to Norman (1963), he used polar opposites to represent the extremes of each trait. For the trait of surgency or extraversion, Goldberg’s key adjectives are: talkative, extraverted, assertive, forward, and outspoken versus shy, quiet, introverted, bashful, and inhibited. For the trait of agreeableness, Goldberg’s key adjectives are: sympathetic, kind, warm, understanding, and sincere versus unsympathetic, unkind, harsh, and cruel. For the trait of conscientiousness, Goldberg’s key adjectives are: organized, neat, orderly, practical, prompt, and meticulous versus disorganized, disorderly, careless, sloppy, and impractical. For the trait of emotional stability, Goldberg’s key adjectives are: calm, relaxed, and stable versus moody, anxious, and insecure. For the trait of intellect or imagination, Goldberg’s key adjectives are: creative, imaginative, and intellectual versus uncreative, unimaginative, and unintellectual."
 },
 {
  "id": 191,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain how the levels in Abraham Maslow’s hierarchy of needs are related to one another, and include an example.",
  "answer": "Maslow depicted human needs using a pyramid. He placed physiological requirements for survival at the bottom. These include air, sleep, water, food, and sex for procreation. At the next level are safety needs, which include shelter, security from danger, and an orderly, predictable life. These are also mostly physical. The higher levels are more social and psychological: the need for belongingness to groups; the need for selfesteem and others’ esteem; and self-actualization, or realizing one’s full potential (the pyramid’s peak). Maslow proposed that each level of the hierarchy depends upon the previous one. In other words, a person cannot meet higher needs without first satisfying the lower ones. For example, a person who is starving will be too occupied with the quest for food to stay alive to be equally concerned about meeting his or her full potential, being regarded well by others, or belonging to a group. Even safety needs are superseded by physiological needs. Therefore, someone might sacrifice safety for food, water, or sleep."
 },
 {
  "id": 192,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some key aspects of Abraham Maslow’s humanistic theory of personality.",
  "answer": "In contrast to Freudian\/neo-Freudian’s focus on pathology, Maslow’s theory is more optimistic. He saw the personality as driven not by inner conflicts and defense mechanisms against anxiety as Freud did, but by the need to learn, adapt, grow, and succeed. Maslow emphasized positive motivations of love, self-esteem, and self-actualization (realizing one’s full potential in life). Humanistic psychologists believe mental disorders are caused by unhealthy situations rather than unhealthy people. Maslow created a hierarchy of needs, which he represented graphically using a pyramid. He believed the lowest level of needs are related to survival, and are physiological. These needs include air, sleep, water, food, and sex. The next level is safety needs, such as having shelter and being secure from danger; and building a structured, orderly, predictable life. Above safety are belonging needs—the need to belong to families, social groups, etc. Above this level are esteem needs—we rely on ourselves and others to meet these needs. At the top of the pyramid is self-actualization."
 },
 {
  "id": 193,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some of the main concepts related to Carl Rogers’s humanistic theory of personality.",
  "answer": "Therapist Carl Rogers worked with many dysfunctional clients, yet he focused on the healthy personality, just as fellow humanistic psychologist Abraham Maslow did. He called the healthy personality the “fully functioning person.” According to Rogers, such persons have self-concepts that are both positive and consistent with reality. Rogers believed it was imperative for psychology to acknowledge the importance of our perceptions and emotions. He called these the “phenomenal field.” The phenomenal field affects our responses. We react not to an objective reality but to our own subjective experience of it. The phenomenal field is thus the part of the personality that filters our experiences. It includes the self (which Freud called the ego) and our interpretations of our inner and outer worlds. In reaction to his own unhappy childhood with overly strict parents, Rogers proposed that people need “unconditional positive regard”(acceptance from others without qualifications\/restrictions\/conditions) rather than conditional love, which is dependent on certain behaviors or factors."
 },
 {
  "id": 194,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe Abraham Maslow’s focus on healthy vs. morbid personalities. Describe some personal qualities and famous individuals Maslow associated with self-actualization.",
  "answer": "As a humanistic psychologist, Maslow found Freudian and neo-Freudian theories too focused on unhealthy personalities and mental disorders. His approach was more positive and optimistic. He believed that mental health should not be described simply as the lack of illness. He was known for his work in identifying the aspects of the healthy personality. He discovered these aspects by studying well-known people who had lived particularly full, productive lives. Maslow placed self-actualization (completely fulfilling one’s potential) at the top of his hierarchy of needs pyramid. He found that self-actualizing people with healthy personalities not only fulfilled their own abilities, but also focused on goals beyond their own basic needs. They usually supported and participated in causes about which they cared deeply. Maslow described such persons as creative, goodhumored, spontaneous, and accepting of their own and others’ limitations. He found they often had “peak experiences.” He identified Abraham Lincoln, Thomas Jefferson, Albert Einstein, Albert Schweitzer, and Eleanor Roosevelt as self-actualizing persons."
 },
 {
  "id": 195,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe Freud’s theory of lifespan development, identifying stage names and characteristics.",
  "answer": "Freud’s psychosexual theory of development is a discontinuous, or stage, theory, meaning it does not depict a gradual, inseparable process of change, but discrete developmental stages instead. Freud focused on sexuality and early parent-child interactions as influences on development. Each stage is characterized by an erogenous zone that is the child’s main focus. Infants are in the oral stage, focused on the mouth when nursing is most important. Toddlers are in the anal stage, focused on the bowels when toilet training is most important. When young children discover their genitals, they enter the phallic stage. Around school age, children focus on new academic and social activities. Freud called this the latency stage. During this stage, sexual urges become latent as the child focuses on learning and making friends. With the advent of puberty, sexual desires return to the forefront in the genital stage. Freud believed that the individual’s personality was basically developed by adolescence, and did not identify any stages beyond the genital stage."
 },
 {
  "id": 196,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some research findings regarding the romantic relationships of young people who are sexual minorities (e.g., gay, lesbian).",
  "answer": "Psychological researchers have recently started examining romantic relationships among young people who are sexual minorities. They have found that many youth who are sexual minorities date peers with different sexual orientations. Researchers believe this can help them identify or clarify their own sexual orientation. It can also help them learn how to hide their own sexual orientation from others. Most gay and lesbian youth have had some sexual experience with the same sex. However, this experience is often with peers who are “experimenting” with homosexuality, and who then move on to mostly heterosexual orientations. Some research, however, has also found that fewer gay teens have had same-sex romantic relationships because of social disapproval and limited opportunities. In one research study, gay and lesbian young people rated their most stressful problem as “coming out” to their parents, and rated their second most stressful problem as the possible breakup of their current romance."
 },
 {
  "id": 197,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the concept of anal retention\/expulsion as it relates to Freud’s theory of psychosexual development, and include an example.",
  "answer": "According to Freud, a specific body area is the focus of erotic pleasure during each psychosexual stage of development, and each stage features a conflict that must be resolved. When some aspect of that conflict is not successfully resolved, the person can become fixated on that stage. As an adult, that person will display behaviors related to the corresponding erogenous zone. Toddlers are in the anal stage of development, when toilet training is the most important activity. They must resolve the conflict between responding to anal stimulation to expel feces and learning to control their bowel movements. A less than ideal resolution of this conflict can result in fixation. At one extreme, if the person overreacts to pressure to control the bowels, the individual will develop an “anal retentive” personality. This type of person is often obsessed with cleanliness, neatness, order, perfectionism, rigidity, and excessive control. At the other extreme, if the child rebelled against toilet training, he or she may develop an “anal expulsive” personality. These people are typically sloppy, messy, disorganized, lacking in self-control, and defiant."
 },
 {
  "id": 198,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the concept of oral fixation as it relates to Freud’s theory of psychosexual development, and include an example",
  "answer": "Freud proposed that development occurs in stages related to the child’s primary focus of sexual and psychic energy at various ages. He viewed each developmental stage as involving, among other things, the resolution of a conflict. Freud said that if a child did not successfully resolve a conflict in one stage, the child could become fixated at that point. If the child remained fixated until adulthood, he or she would display behaviors characteristic of that stage’s focus. For example, Freud’s first stage of psychosexual development is the oral stage, when nursing is the infant’s most significant activity and the focus of erogenous pleasure. If a baby’s oral needs are gratified too much or not enough, the individual can develop oral fixation. As an adult, this individual will exhibit excessive oral behaviors, such as overeating, drinking too much, nail-biting, etc. Oral personality characteristics include excessive dependence on others; gullibility; and always following, never leading. Those who resist their oral impulses may display aggression and have a pessimistic attitude toward others."
 },
 {
  "id": 199,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the concept of the Electra complex as it relates to Freud’s theory of psychosexual development, and identify some examples of associated behaviors often observed by parents.",
  "answer": "Freud proposed that boys experience the Oedipus complex during the phallic stage of psychosexual development. According to Freud, boys at this stage unconsciously want to have sex with their mothers and kill their fathers to eliminate the competition. He named the complex after the Greek character Oedipus, who unwittingly murdered his father and married his mother. When neo-Freudian psychoanalyst Carl Jung proposed an Electra complex—named after the Greek character Electra, who plotted with her brother to kill their mother and stepfather for killing their father—as the female counterpart to the Oedipus complex, Freud disagreed strongly. He referred to the “feminine Oedipus attitude” and the “negative Oedipus complex,” but insisted that male and female sexuality were too different for Jung’s term to be accurate. Nevertheless, parents are familiar with their daughters preferring Daddy over Mommy between the ages of three and six. Like boys, they also subsequently “identify with the aggressor” by imitating Mother and displaying more feminine behaviors."
 },
 {
  "id": 200,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain the concept of the Oedipus complex as it relates to Freud’s theory of psychosexual development. In your answer, include the origin of the complex’s name, how it is resolved, and examples of associated behaviors often observed by parents.",
  "answer": "Oedipus was an ancient Greek figure mentioned by Homer and others, and most famously depicted in the playwright Sophocles’s tragedy, Oedipus Rex. Oedipus’s fate was to murder his father and marry his mother. Sigmund Freud borrowed his name when he developed his concept of the Oedipus complex, which he said occurs in boys when they are around three to six years old. Freud theorized that boys unconsciously have unacceptable sexual desires for their mothers, and equally unacceptable aggressive desires to kill their fathers to have their mothers all to themselves. Parents see this when a four or five-year-old son says, “Go away, Daddy. I want Mommy.” Freud theorized that boys also unconsciously dread castration by their fathers as retribution for these impulses. He said boys resolve their unacceptable urges through the process of “identification with the aggressor”: being like their fathers to avert competition and repress attraction for their mothers. Parents see this when little boys try to dress and behave “just like Daddy,” and start to develop more masculine qualities."
 },
 {
  "id": 201,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the first four stages of psychosocial development in Erikson’s theory. Provide the names of the stages, the ages at which they occur, important events, and the results of successful and unsuccessful conflict resolution.",
  "answer": "Erikson’s stage names identify the nuclear conflict that must be resolved in each stage. Spanning the time from birth to 18 months, Erikson’s stage of basic trust vs. mistrust involves nursing. If the infant is fed in a timely and consistent manner, he or she will develop trust in the world. If feeding is insufficient, excessive, or inconsistent, mistrust of the environment is the result. In early childhood, the stage of autonomy vs. shame and self-doubt involves toilet training. If the child develops feelings of control over his or her physical abilities, independence and autonomy result. If not, feelings of shame and self-doubt result. Preschoolers are in the stage of initiative vs. guilt. The important event during this stage is exploration of the environment. When children successfully exert appropriate power to control their environments, they develop a sense of purpose and initiative. If they exercise too much power, they encounter disapproval, resulting in feelings of guilt. School-aged children are in the stage of industry vs. inferiority. If they succeed in addressing new social and academic requirements, they develop feelings of competence; failure results in feelings of inferiority."
 },
 {
  "id": 202,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Provide a general overview of Erik Erikson’s theory of psychosocial development, and compare and contrast it with Freud’s theory.",
  "answer": "While Freud’s focus of development was psychosexual, Erikson’s was psychosocial. Freud focused on early child-parent interactions as influences on development, while Erikson focused on interactions between the individual and society. (One of his greatest and best-known books is Childhood and Society.) Erikson’s theory is considered neo-Freudian because so many of its elements resemble those found in Freud’s theory. This is particularly true of Erikson’s descriptions of earlier developmental stages. Both theories are discontinuous and comprised of developmental stages. While Freud believed development was essentially complete and that there were no more stages or major changes after puberty, Erikson believed that people continue to develop throughout their lives, and his theory includes stages for all ages. Both theories involve a conflict in each stage, which must be resolved. While Freud described psychosexual conflicts, Erikson described psychosocial crises or “nuclear conflicts.” While Freud named each stage after the relevant erogenous zone (oral, anal, phallic, and genital), Erikson named each of his stages after the conflict outcomes (e.g. trust vs. mistrust)."
 },
 {
  "id": 203,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the seventh and eighth stages of psychosocial development in Erikson’s theory. Provide the names of the stages, the ages at which they occur, important events, and the results of successful and unsuccessful conflict resolution.",
  "answer": "Though the earlier stages of Erikson’s theory are similar to Freud’s theory in that they focus on nursing, toilet training, exploration, school, and puberty, Erikson differed from Freud in that he proposed stages for an individual’s entire life span (up until death). In contrast, Freud’s stages ended with adolescence. According to Erikson’s theory, in middle adulthood—from the ages of around 40 to 65—people are in the stage of generativity vs. stagnation. The important events associated with this stage are work, parenthood, and\/or family. Adults who succeed in generativity by creating and\/or nurturing children and\/or other things that will last beyond their own lives and benefit others develop feelings of accomplishment and of being productive and useful. Failure to resolve this nuclear conflict results in the person having a shallow involvement with the world. From age 65 on is the stage of ego integrity vs. despair. Older adults looking back on life feel fulfillment and wisdom with success; or regret, despair, and bitterness with failure."
 },
 {
  "id": 204,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the fifth and sixth stages of psychosocial development in Erikson’s theory. Provide the names of the stages, the ages at which they occur, important events, and the results of successful and unsuccessful conflict resolution.",
  "answer": "The fifth stage in Erikson’s theory of psychosocial development occurs during adolescence. It involves the nuclear conflict of identity vs. role confusion. The important events in this stage are social relationships. Teenagers begin to develop a sense of self and a personal identity. Teens who succeed develop the ability to remain true to themselves. Those who fail are confused about their roles in life and have a weak sense of self. During young adulthood—between the ages of about 19 and 40—people are in the sixth stage of development, which is intimacy vs. isolation. The important event in this stage is the formation of intimate relationships. Young adults who succeed in resolving this nuclear conflict are able to establish strong, loving, intimate relationships with other people. Those who fail to resolve this conflict end up feeling isolated and lonely."
 },
 {
  "id": 205,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Name and summarize the features of each developmental stage in Piaget’s theory of cognitive development.",
  "answer": "In Piaget’s first, sensorimotor, stage of cognitive development, babies respond to sensory information they receive from the environment with motor activities. They repeat the motions they observe; Piaget termed these repetitions circular reactions. The second, preoperational, stage lasts from about age two to seven. Children begin to represent the environment using symbols like words and pictures. They form stable concepts and start reasoning. However, they cannot yet perform mental operations, Piaget’s term for reversible mental actions. They cannot take another’s perspective, an inability Piaget called egocentrism. In the third stage of concrete operations, which lasts from about age 7 to 11, children begin to perform and reverse mental operations, but only with concrete objects they can see and manipulate. They start to understand conservation. They also begin to comprehend certain concepts, such as that the number and amount of something remains the same despite changes in distribution and shape. At this point, however, they can only understand such concepts when they involve concrete things. They cannot yet think abstractly. In the stage of formal operations, which begins during pre-adolescence and adolescence, abstract thought develops. This allows children to understand higher mathematics, philosophy, and abstract concepts like justice."
 },
 {
  "id": 206,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some of the important basic concepts that are part of Piaget’s theory of cognitive development.",
  "answer": "Jean Piaget, who had a background in botany, conducted detailed naturalistic observations of babies and young children to discover how they learned about their environments. By observing their behaviors, Piaget theorized that children are like “little scientists” who learn by constantly “experimenting” with and on the environment. Piaget used the term schema (plural schemata) to describe the mental constructs we form about things in the environment and our experiences with them. He found that like other organisms, humans need to maintain equilibrium or balance by adapting to their environment. Piaget explained that the adaptation process consists of assimilation and accommodation. Assimilation is fitting a new object or experience into an existing schema. For example, a baby forms a schema for “things I suck.” Initially, this includes “nipple,” “pacifier,” and “my thumb.” Then, “the table leg” or “Daddy’s knee” might be assimilated into this schema. Accommodation is creating a new schema for something that cannot be assimilated into an existing one."
 },
 {
  "id": 207,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "In Piaget’s first, sensorimotor, stage of cognitive development, babies respond to sensory information they receive from the environment with motor activities. They repeat the motions they observe; Piaget termed these repetitions circular reactions. The second, preoperational, stage lasts from about age two to seven. Children begin to represent the environment using symbols like words and pictures. They form stable concepts and start reasoning. However, they cannot yet perform mental operations, Piaget’s term for reversible mental actions. They cannot take another’s perspective, an inability Piaget called egocentrism. In the third stage of concrete operations, which lasts from about age 7 to 11, children begin to perform and reverse mental operations, but only with concrete objects they can see and manipulate. They start to understand conservation. They also begin to comprehend certain concepts, such as that the number and amount of something remains the same despite changes in distribution and shape. At this point, however, they can only understand such concepts when they involve concrete things. They cannot yet think abstractly. In the stage of formal operations, which begins during pre-adolescence and adolescence, abstract thought develops. This allows children to understand higher mathematics, philosophy, and abstract concepts like justice."
 },
 {
  "id": 208,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe the last three of the six substages in the sensorimotor stage of Piaget’s cognitive developmental theory, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "In Piaget’s sensorimotor substage of (4) coordination of secondary circular reactions, which occurs between the ages of about 8 and 12 months, infants develop eye-hand coordination and intentionality, combining and coordinating existing schemes (concepts). They can simultaneously look at and grasp an object. Their actions become more outwardly directed, and they perform actions for specific purposes. For example, they might manipulate a stick to pull a toy within reach. In the substage of (5) tertiary circular reactions, novelty, and curiosity, children between the ages of 12 and 18 months old develop curiosity about the characteristics of objects and the things they can do with them, such as making them fall, spin, collide with other objects, roll, bounce, and slide. Tertiary circular reactions are schemes for purposefully exploring new actions to perform with objects and their results. In (6) internalization of schemes, which occurs between the ages of about 18 and 24 months, children begin using primitive symbols to represent concrete events. For example, Piaget observed his daughter watching a matchbox being opened and closed. She later imitated this by opening and closing her mouth, showing she had internalized this event."
 },
 {
  "id": 209,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe the first three of the six substages in the sensorimotor stage of Piaget’s cognitive developmental theory, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Infants in the sensorimotor stage of cognitive development first go through the substage of (1) simple reflexes, which involves reflexive behaviors like rooting and sucking. In (2) first habits and primary circular reactions, which occurs between the ages of about one and four months, babies develop “habits.” These are schemes based on reflexes that are detached from their stimuli, such as sucking even without the stimulation of a nipple. Primary circular reactions are schemes for trying to recreate an event that first happened accidentally. If an infant happened to suck his fingers when they were near his mouth, he looks for them to suck them again. In (3) secondary circular reactions, which occurs between the ages of about four and eight months, infants move from self-orientation to object-orientation. Schemes are not goal-directed or purposeful, but rather repeated or imitated due to reinforcing consequences, like the sound from shaking a rattle."
 },
 {
  "id": 210,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain the characteristics of egocentrism, animism, and intuitive thinking as they relate to the preoperational stage of Piaget’s theory of cognitive development, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "According to Piaget, children in the second, preoperational, stage are egocentric, meaning they cannot see things from another’s perspective. For example, a four-year-old girl answering the phone might silently nod instead of saying “yes” aloud because she does not realize the person on the other end cannot see her nod. In Piaget and Inhelder’s “three mountains” task, children walked around models of mountains to see how they looked from different viewpoints. Then, they were asked to identify photos showing how they looked from the viewpoint of a doll placed in different locations. Preoperational children tended to identify their own view, not the doll’s view. Animism is assigning human qualities to inanimate objects, and is typical at the preoperational stage. For example, a child might say, “The sidewalk made me fall down and got me mad.” Children also exhibit intuitive thinking at this stage. Children know they know things, but don’t know how they know them. Their knowledge is not arrived at through logical thought, so it may be incorrect."
 },
 {
  "id": 211,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define the concept of object permanence as it relates to Piaget’s cognitive developmental theory. Include a discussion of A-not-B errors, and provide some examples.",
  "answer": "Object permanence is one of the most important developments for babies in Piaget’s first, sensorimotor, stage. It is the understanding that objects are not “out of sight, out of mind,” but still exist even when they are not seen. For example, if a baby is interested in an object and you conceal it from view by covering it with a blanket or placing a barrier in front of it, the baby who has not achieved object permanence will not search for the object. At this point, babies find peek-a-boo games magical, because your face is there, disappears, and then reappears as if by magic. Babies with object permanence will look for hidden objects. If you hide something and then hide it elsewhere, and the baby still searches in the first hiding place, this is an A-not-B error. Babies with fully developed object permanence will look in the right place. They are entertained by peek-a-boo games and jack-in-the-box toys because they understand the concept of object permanence, and the reappearance meets their expectations."
 },
 {
  "id": 212,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some important aspects of Vygotsky’s social constructivist approach to development.",
  "answer": "Lev Vygotsky’s theory describes learning, and places an emphasis on social contexts and social interactions as the bases for constructing knowledge. Vygotsky coined the term zone of proximal development (ZPD), which refers to skills that a child is just developing but cannot yet perform independently. This zone’s lower limit is the skill level the child reaches independently, and its upper limit is the responsibility level the child can handle with assistance. Vygotsky found that children’s learning is enhanced when they receive guidance from an adult or a more skilled child to complete activities that are too difficult for them to master alone. Vygotsky also introduced the term scaffolding, which refers to support that others give a learner. This support is adjusted to reflect learning progress. Parents, teachers, older children, and more skilled peers give the learner the amount of guidance necessary initially, and then gradually withdraw it as the child’s performance progresses toward autonomy."
 },
 {
  "id": 213,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define the terms “centration” and “conservation” as they relate to Piaget’s cognitive developmental theory, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Piaget found that young children in the second, preoperational, stage exhibited centration, meaning they centered their attention on one aspect of an object and ignored all others. Centration occurs in children who have not yet developed an understanding of conservation (the concept that changing the appearance of a substance or object does not alter its properties). For example, if you pour a given amount of liquid from a short, wide beaker into a tall, narrow beaker, the preoperational child will center on the second beaker’s height and say there is more liquid than there was in the first beaker. Children around the ages of seven or eight years old who can reverse mental operations will say the amount is the same, justifying it by pointing out that if you poured the liquid back into the first beaker, the amount would be the same as before it was poured into the second beaker. Similarly, if preoperational children are shown balls of clay of the same size, and one is then rolled into a long “snake” in front of them, they will say the longer piece has more clay than the ball. Developing the concept of conservation causes “decentration.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 214,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize Urie Bronfenbrenner’s developmental psychology theory known as the ecological systems theory. Include a discussion of its system components and how it has influenced developmental research.",
  "answer": "According to Bronfenbrenner, human development is shaped by rules, roles, and norms contained within four types of systems. The microsystem represents systems in the individual’s immediate environment, like the family, the classroom, etc. The mesosystem represents the interaction between two microsystems, such as the interaction between a child’s home and school. The exosystem represents a system external to the child’s environment that affects the child despite its indirect involvement in the child’s life. An example is the workplace of the child’s parent(s). The macrosystem represents the larger cultural context within which the other systems exist. The chronosystem represents the time element of environmental events, life transitions, and sociohistorical circumstances. Bronfenbrenner stated that as children develop, their interactions within environmental systems increase in complexity commensurately with the maturation of their physical and cognitive abilities. Bronfenbrenner influenced child development researchers by directing their attention to the investigation of the family, the economy, and political factors as influences on the growth and development of children."
 },
 {
  "id": 215,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain Vygotsky’s concepts of private speech and inner speech as they relate to his theory of social cognitive development.",
  "answer": "Vygotsky believed that language and thought first develop independently, and are later combined. He emphasized the external, social sources of all thinking. He said children must use language outwardly to communicate for a long time before they can internalize it to their own thoughts. Between the ages of about three and seven, children begin to talk to themselves aloud (as many parents can attest to) to help them work through and solve problems by controlling and guiding their own behaviors. Eventually, this self-talk, or private speech as Vygotsky called it, becomes mental and silent. Vygotsky termed this mental self-talk inner speech, which becomes the child’s thoughts. He viewed children using more private speech as more socially competent, maintaining that private speech indicates an earlier development of more social communication. Research supports Vygotsky’s ideas: children use more private speech when completing difficult tasks, when they have erred, and when they are uncertain how to proceed. Researchers have also found that children who use private speech are more attentive and improve their performance more than those who do not."
 },
 {
  "id": 216,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe how behavioral theory relates to human growth and development. Summarize the key concepts of Skinner’s behavioral theory known as operant conditioning.",
  "answer": "According to behaviorism, the only things we can study scientifically are observable, measurable behaviors. Behaviorism does not deny the existence of inner states, such as emotions or thoughts. It simply does not deal with them, because anything that cannot be observed cannot be measured, and if it cannot be seen and quantified, it therefore cannot be changed, which is the goal of behavior modification. Behaviorism holds that observable behaviors are learned through experience and interactions with the environment. While stage theories like Freud’s, Erikson’s, and Piaget’s are discontinuous in that they represent development in discrete stages, behaviorism, like Vygotsky’s sociocultural cognitive theory, represents development as continuous. Skinner’s operant conditioning theory is the most prominent of the behavioral theories, and serves as the basis for all others. Skinner found that an individual is more likely to repeat a behavior that is rewarded (reinforced) and less likely to repeat a behavior that is punished or ignored."
 },
 {
  "id": 217,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize how information-processing theory addresses human growth and development, and compare and contrast it with Piaget’s and Vygotsky’s developmental theories.",
  "answer": "The focus of the information-processing theory of human growth and development is the way in which people interpret the information they obtain from the environment; and how they monitor this information, manipulate it, and use it to strategize. Whereas Piaget’s cognitive developmental theory is discontinuous, proposing discrete stages of development, information-processing theory is not. It is more similar to Vygotsky’s social cognitive theory, which depicts gradual, continuous progress. Similarly, information-processing theory states that the individual’s ability to process information gradually increases as they grow, enabling them to attain knowledge and skills of increasing complexity. According to information processing theorists, perceiving, encoding, decoding, representing, storing, and retrieving information are components of information processing, and information processing equals thinking. Learning effective strategies for processing information is important to development. For example, to improve in reading, a student might learn to look for and identify the main themes in reading materials."
 },
 {
  "id": 218,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define and discuss biological, cognitive, and socioemotional processes as parts of lifespan development.",
  "answer": "Development, or patterns of change throughout life, is complex. It is the result of biological, cognitive, and socioemotional processes. Biological processes effect physiological changes in a person. Genes we inherit from our parents, increases in weight and height, the brain’s development, the development of motor skills, hormonal changes during puberty, and cardiovascular decline with aging are all biological processes that influence development. Cognitive processes are changes in our intelligence, language, and thinking. Cognitive processes are involved when a baby watches a mobile above his or her crib, when a toddler composes a two-word sentence, when an older child memorizes a poem, when a teen imagines what it would be like to be a movie star, and when an adult solves a crossword puzzle. Socioemotional processes are changes in our emotions, our personalities, and our interactions and relationships with other people. They include an infant smiling at a parent, a toddler’s aggression against a playmate, a school-aged child’s development of self-assertiveness, a teen’s excitement about the prom, and the affection between elderly spouses."
 },
 {
  "id": 219,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize some key aspects of Bandura’s social-cognitive theory of development.",
  "answer": "Albert Bandura combines behavioral, cognitive, and social factors in his theory. He agrees with behavioral theorists that development involves the acquisition of learned behaviors that are strongly influenced by interactions with the environment. He agrees with Piaget that cognition is also a significant factor in understanding development. In this respect, his theory contradicts behavioral theory. Like Vygotsky and Bronfenbrenner, he emphasizes social influences on learning. Bandura found that people learn not only through direct experiences, but also through observation. His experiments proved that children who observed violent behavior by other people, both in vivo and in video recordings, would imitate it and behave more aggressively. He also found that those observing another person being rewarded or punished for a behavior would commit or avoid the same behavior accordingly. Bandura recently created a model of learning and development consisting of three components: behavior, person\/cognition, and environment. Personal characteristics such as self-efficacy and cognitive processes such as strategies are represented by person\/cognition. Interactions among components are reciprocal."
 },
 {
  "id": 220,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and describe the first four of the eight developmental periods in the human lifespan.",
  "answer": "The prenatal period is the (usually) nine months from conception to birth. There is enormous development during this time. A single cell forms into a complete organism with a brain. The period of infancy lasts from birth to 18 to 24 months. It is characterized by great dependence on adults. Many psychological abilities and processes are just starting to develop. These include sensorimotor coordination, language, symbolic thinking, and social learning. The period of early childhood follows infancy, and lasts until the age of about five or six. Young children and preschoolers learn more skills related to self-care and self-sufficiency. They also learn skills that help prepare them for school, such as following directions and recognizing the letters of the alphabet. The developmental period of middle and late childhood corresponds roughly with the elementary school years. Children in this stage are between the ages of 6 and 11, and master reading, writing, and arithmetic during this period. They receive formal exposure to the bigger world and to their culture. Children’s self-control increases, and achievement becomes more important to them."
 },
 {
  "id": 221,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss the relationship between biological, cognitive, and socioemotional processes in human development, and include an example.",
  "answer": "Biological processes, or changes in our physiology; cognitive processes, or changes in our intellect, language, and thinking; and socioemotional processes, or changes in our feelings, personalities, and social relationships all interact reciprocally with one another. As such, they are intertwined and cannot be separated. For example, when a parent touches an infant and the baby smiles in response, all of these processes are involved. The physical property of touch and response to touch are the result of biological processes. The ability to understand intentional behavior, which allows the baby to recognize the parent’s intention to interact, involves cognitive processes. The baby’s smile reflects a positive emotional response. In addition, the act of smiling facilitates positive connections with other humans, so the baby’s smile in response to the parent’s touch is the result of socioemotional processes. Also, these processes often interact bidirectionally. For example, biological processes can affect cognitive processes, and vice versa."
 },
 {
  "id": 222,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and describe the last three of the eight developmental periods in the human lifespan.",
  "answer": "In the developmental period of early adulthood, which lasts from the twenties to about age 40, people focus on establishing their personal and economic independence, on career development, on forming intimate relationships, and on starting families. In the period of middle adulthood, which lasts from about age 40 to 60, people focus on expanding their personal and social responsibility and involvement. They engage in activities to help the next generation grow and develop into mature, competent persons. Middle adults also typically concentrate on attaining and sustaining career satisfaction. In the period of late adulthood, which begins in the sixties or seventies and continues until death, people engage in life reviews, looking back on the course of their lives, determining what they accomplished and did not accomplish, and taking stock of their satisfactions and regrets. They retire from their jobs, and must adjust to new social roles. These roles are also changed by declining strength and health. Currently, late adulthood lasts longer than any other developmental period."
 },
 {
  "id": 223,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and describe the fifth of the eight developmental periods in the human lifespan.",
  "answer": "The transition from middle and late childhood to adulthood is the developmental period of adolescence. It is the fifth of the eight developmental periods, and lasts from about age 10 to 12 to about 18 to 22. The onset of puberty marks the start of adolescence. It is characterized by rapid physiological changes, such as growth spurts, weight gains, changes in body shape, and the development of secondary sexual characteristics like breast growth, pubic and facial hair growth, and deepening of the voice. During this period, teenagers are involved in developing a sense of individual identity, and in pursuing independence. Cognitively, they are fully able for the first time to think abstractly and logically. This new understanding of abstract concepts often contributes to idealistic beliefs and attitudes, including visions for reforming society and critical attitudes about unethical or immoral adult behaviors they observe. Teens also spend more time away from their families."
 },
 {
  "id": 224,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe how Jean Piaget conceptualized the moral development of children.",
  "answer": "After formulating his theory of cognitive development, Piaget observed and interviewed children regarding rules and ethics. He proposed that children go through two stages of moral reasoning, and a third, transitional period in between. From about age four to seven, Piaget said children are in the first stage of moral development: heteronomous morality. They view rules, justice, and right and wrong as fixed characteristics of the environment that people cannot control. They view the consequences of actions as more important than the actor’s intentions when determining right and wrong. They believe in “immanent justice,” which is the concept that punishment inevitably and immediately follows wrongdoing. Piaget said that between the ages of 7 to 10, children are transitioning between the two moral stages. From around age 10 on, Piaget found that children demonstrate autonomous morality. They realize that rules and laws are made by people, not omnipotent authorities, and as such are subject to change. When considering people’s actions, they find their intentions more important than the consequences."
 },
 {
  "id": 225,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the four “ages” of lifespan development described by some developmental psychologists, and discuss differences among older adults.",
  "answer": "Some developmental psychologists interested in adult development and aging (Baltes, 2006) describe lifespan development as having four ages. The first age is childhood and adolescence. The second age is “prime” adulthood, which lasts from the twenties through the fifties. The third age lasts from about age 60 to about age 79. Adults 80 or older are in their fourth age. This model’s main focus is on the third and fourth ages, the times of most interest to those studying adulthood and aging. Some (Baltes and Smith, 2003) identify the “young old” as those aged 65 to 84 and the “oldest old” as those who are around the age of 85. Their category of “oldest old” is designed to mark a major change they feel occurs in older adults’ lives. Scientific evidence supporting this idea is increasing. The “young old” still have the potential to maintain, improve, or attain physical and cognitive fitness, and to develop coping strategies in response to aging. However, many (but not all) of those who are 85 and older experience significant losses in physical health, become frailer, experience a decline in cognitive skills, and experience an increase in chronic stress and a decline in overall well-being."
 },
 {
  "id": 226,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe the six stages in Lawrence Kohlberg’s theory of moral reasoning.",
  "answer": "In Kohlberg’s preconventional level of moral reasoning, stage 1 is called heteronomous morality. This stage is also identified in Piaget’s theory of moral development in children. At this point, children’s morality is not internalized, but is related to external consequences. Bad behavior is punished and good behavior is rewarded. This shapes the child’s concept of good and bad, right and wrong. Stage 2 is individualism, purpose, and exchange. In this stage, people follow their own interests and let others do the same.\n\nPeople at this level view equal exchanges as good and right. Part of Kohlberg’s conventional level, during which the internalization of morality is in an intermediate stage, stage 3 is mutual interpersonal expectations, relationships, and interpersonal conformity. Trust, loyalty, and care for others are valued as foundations for moral judgments. In Stage 4, social system morality, individuals base moral judgments on their understanding of the social system, justice, laws, and duty. Part of Kohlberg’s postconventional level, at which point moral standards have become fully internalized, stage 5 is social contract or utility and individual rights. Individuals perceive that laws are underpinned and\/or transcended by values, principles, and rights. At Stage 6, universal ethical principles, individuals base moral judgments on universal human rights, following their individual consciences to resolve conflicts with laws."
 },
 {
  "id": 227,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify and describe the three main levels of thinking in Lawrence Kohlberg’s theory of moral reasoning.",
  "answer": "Kohlberg based his theory of moral reasoning on Piaget’s theory of cognitive development. His theory includes the concept that opportunities to assume others’ perspectives and conflicts between one’s present level of moral reasoning and someone else’s higher level promote advancement to each successive level and stage. Kohlberg’s first and lowest level of moral reasoning is the preconventional level. At this level, morality is not internalized. Children view good and bad only as the sources of extrinsic rewards and punishments. Level 2 is the conventional level, during which the internalization of morality is in an intermediate stage. For instance, children and teens apply moral standards, but they are provided by others (parents, the government, etc.). Level 3 in Kohlberg’s theory is the postconventional level of moral reasoning. At this point, moral standards have become fully internalized. Individuals at this highest level can identify various alternatives among moral choices, explore them, and then choose their own personal set of moral beliefs, known as a moral code."
 },
 {
  "id": 228,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss influences on moral reasoning proposed by Kohlberg’s developmental theory. Identify Kohlberg’s beliefs, other researchers’ findings, and applicable concepts developed by Piaget and Vygotsky.",
  "answer": "Kohlberg’s theory was based on Piaget’s theory of cognitive developmental stages. He also applied Piaget’s concept of perspective-taking, being able to see another’s point of view, as an influence on the advancement of children’s moral reasoning. Additionally, Kohlberg agreed with Piaget that the individual seeks homeostasis and equilibrium, and that the conflict created by disequilibrium motivates further moral development to resolve it. Other researchers have experimented with Vygotsky’s concepts of scaffolding and the zone of proximal development by exposing children to discussions involving slightly higher levels of moral development than the children’s current levels. Scaffolding is providing the support and guidance needed to help a child begin to comprehend a concept, and then gradually withdrawing it as the child learns. The zone of proximal development applies to situations in which children can complete tasks with guidance, but not independently. The guidance provided in such situations promotes learning and independent mastery of the skill. Researchers found that any exposure to higher moral levels promotes moral development, supporting Kohlberg’s beliefs."
 },
 {
  "id": 229,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the approximate ages that Lawrence Kohlberg associated with the levels and stages he proposed in his theory of moral reasoning. State what some other researchers have found regarding the connection between age and Kohlberg’s proposed stages.",
  "answer": "Kohlberg found that most children were in his first, preconventional stage of moral reasoning before the age of nine. He found that most progressed to his second, conventional level by early adolescence. Most adolescents were at stage 3 of level 2, but some showed signs of being at stage 2 of level 1 or stage 4 of level 2. He found not everybody, including adults, reaches level 3. In fact, only a minority of people do. Other researchers conducted a 20year longitudinal study and found that stages 1 and 2 decrease with age. They found that stage 1 ended before age 18 in their sample, and that less than 10 percent of participants were in stage 2 by age 24. This percentage decreased even more by the time participants reached the age of 36, the highest age sampled. Researchers found that stage 4 was nonexistent in 10year-olds and existed in 62 percent of 36-year-olds. They also found that stage 5 appeared around the ages of 20 to 22. People at this stage comprised only 10 percent of adults in their sample. They did not find stage 6. Thus, they concluded that moral stages develop a bit later than Kohlberg believed, and that stage 6 was rarer than Kohlberg thought."
 },
 {
  "id": 230,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize Carol Gilligan’s argument about gender differences related to Lawrence Kohlberg’s theory of moral development, and discuss other researchers’ findings regarding her argument.",
  "answer": "Carol Gilligan perceived a gender bias in Kohlberg’s theory.\n\nKohlberg was male, did research with mostly males, and used males’ responses as the model for his theory. Therefore, the basis for this theory was a male norm.\n\nGilligan said that the average male views abstract principles and independent moral decisions as more important than relationships and caring for others. Gilligan defined Kohlberg’s theory as having a “justice perspective,” and argued that women have a “care perspective,” seeing morality in terms of interpersonal connections, communication, relationships, and concern for others. Gilligan’s own research supported her arguments. However, a statistical metaanalysis of many studies found only small gender differences in care-oriented moral reasoning among adolescents. These differences were even smaller in adults. This meta-analysis found that the nature of a given situation explained differences in moral reasoning better than gender. Men and women both tended to use care perspectives in interpersonal situations and justice perspectives in societal ones. Other studies found that altruistic, helping, and prosocial behavior is more important to females. Additional research found girls used more care reasoning to resolve dating dilemmas than boys."
 },
 {
  "id": 231,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain the relationship between cognitive development and moral development proposed by Kohlberg, including his views on social interactions with peers versus interactions with adults.",
  "answer": "Kohlberg’s theory of moral development mirrors aspects of Piaget’s theory of cognitive development in terms of stages of thinking, and also echoes Piaget’s concepts of heteronomous and autonomous morality.\n\nTherefore, each of Kohlberg’s stages of moral development presumes a particular level of cognitive development that enables a specific level of moral reasoning has been reached. However, Kohlberg also maintained that progression to higher cognitive levels does not automatically dictate that the individual will progress to correspondingly higher levels of moral thinking. He found that experiences that involve addressing moral conflicts and questions are also important influences on children’s moral development. Other psychological researchers have tested this argument by introducing children to conversations involving slightly higher levels of moral judgment. Their findings supported Kohlberg’s assertion—this practice did advance moral development. Kohlberg also found peer interactions crucial as social stimulation to promote this progress.\n\nWhile adults impose rules on children, equal exchanges among peers allow perspective-taking and a democratic generation of rules to advance children’s moral reasoning."
 },
 {
  "id": 232,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize the principles of John Bowlby’s theory of attachment in babies and children.",
  "answer": "Bowlby viewed development from an ethological perspective (1969 and 1989). He believed that both infants and parents are biologically predisposed to form attachments, and that newborns evoke attachment behaviors in parents by their early behaviors of crying, cooing, clinging, and smiling. These and their later behaviors of crawling, walking, and following the parent accomplish the short-term effect of keeping the caregiver near, and increase the baby’s chance of survival over the longterm. Bowlby’s concept of attachment develops in phases (adapted by Schaffer, 1996). Phase 1 lasts from birth to two months. Infants instinctually smile and cry to indiscriminately attract attention from all humans. Phase 2 lasts from two to seven months. In this phase, babies develop an attachment to the main caregiver. Phase 3 lasts from 7 to 24 months. With improving locomotor skills that allow them to actively seek out contact, babies develop specific attachments to mothers and\/or fathers. Phase 4 lasts from 24 months on. At this point, children develop awareness of others’ emotions, plans, and goals, and begin to consider these when deciding on their own actions."
 },
 {
  "id": 233,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize Harry Harlow’s experiment with monkeys and surrogate “mothers,” and identify the landmark discovery about infant attachment he made during this study.",
  "answer": "Harry Harlow (1958) separated monkeys from their mothers at birth and gave them one of two types of surrogate “mothers.” One type was made of soft cloth and the other type was made of hard wire. He had half of the monkeys fed by the wire “mother” and half by the cloth one. Outside of feedings, data on how much time the baby monkeys spent with each “mother” were collected and recorded. Regardless of which “mother” fed them, all of the monkeys spent more time with the cloth “mother.” Those “raised” by the cloth “mother” also ran and clung to the cloth “mother” when frightened, while those “raised” by the wire “mother” did not. Harlow found that the infant monkeys associated a substitute “mother” with security if they felt it gave tactile physical comfort. Harlow’s landmark discovery was that the attachment process does not depend only upon being fed, but also the comfort received through physical contact."
 },
 {
  "id": 234,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the styles of caregivers associated with each type of infant attachment defined by Mary Ainsworth through her strange situation studies.",
  "answer": "Psychologists have widely accepted and applied Ainsworth’s definitions. She described securely attached babies and insecurely attached babies, which were avoidant, resistant, or disorganized in their behaviors. Later research studies have found several patterns of association. Babies who display insecurely attached, avoidant behaviors (such as avoiding contact and interaction) are likely to have caregivers who either reject the babies or are unavailable. They frequently do not respond to the babies’ communications, engage in little physical contact with them, and may respond irritably or angrily in interactions with them. Insecurely attached, resistant babies (ones that resist contact and interaction) are likely to have caregivers who respond to their needs inconsistently, are generally not very affectionate, and display little synchrony when interacting with them. Babies with insecure, disorganized attachment styles (ones that are disoriented, extremely fearful, and\/or confused) frequently have caregivers who physically abuse and\/or neglect them."
 },
 {
  "id": 235,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe the findings of Mary Ainsworth during her experiments with the “strange situation” about babies’ attachments to caregivers.",
  "answer": "Mary Ainsworth devised a series of experimental measures she called the “strange situation” to describe different infant attachment styles. She defined four types of attachment—one secure and three insecure. Securely attached babies explored a playroom environment from the secure “base” of the mother. They sometimes objected mildly when the mother left, but reestablished positive interaction on her return, smiling or climbing into her lap. These babies then resumed their play. Insecurely attached, avoidant babies avoided the caregiver, were not upset when she left the room, and did not make contact on her return. They usually looked and\/or leaned away when the mother made contact. Insecurely attached, resistant babies frequently clung to their mothers, and then fought contact. In the strange situation they anxiously clung to their mother, did not explore the playroom, cried loudly when the mother left, and pushed away from contact on her return. Insecurely attached, disorganized babies seemed disoriented in the strange situation. They displayed extreme fear and\/or confusion, avoidance, or resistance."
 },
 {
  "id": 236,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the four parenting styles proposed by Diana Baumrind, and outline the associated dimensions and the degrees, or extremes, of the dimensions associated with each style.",
  "answer": "Baumrind described authoritarian parents as restrictive, directive, and punitive. They rigidly enforce but do not explain rules, and regularly express anger. In the dimension of acceptance and responsiveness, they are rejecting and unresponsive; in the dimension of demand and control, they are demanding and controlling. At the other extreme, indulgent parents are accepting and responsive, and undemanding and uncontrolling. They are warm and involved, but permissive. Neglectful parents are rejecting and unresponsive, and undemanding and uncontrolling. They are not strict, but are not involved either, paying insufficient attention to their children and giving them the feeling they are not as important as other parts of their parents’ lives. Authoritative parenting is Baumrind’s ideal style. These parents are accepting and responsive toward their children. They are also demanding and controlling in that they do set limits on their children’s behavior. They are warm and nurturing, and allow much give-and-take discussion with children, encouraging and expecting independence and age-appropriate behavior from them."
 },
 {
  "id": 237,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Explain how developmental psychologists describe the family, and include an overview of reciprocal influences and direct and indirect effects.",
  "answer": "Developmental psychologists regard the family as a complex, whole entity that is composed of subsystems within the family system. The members or parts making up each subsystem are interrelated and interact with one another. Each member of a family interacts within several of these subsystems. For example, one subsystem is made up of the mother and child; another is represented by the father and child; and the mother, father, and child together make up yet another subsystem. In families with more than one child, each relationship between two siblings constitutes a subsystem, each relationship among more than two siblings is another subsystem, etc. Family members and subsystems influence one another reciprocally. For example, an infant’s development and behavior, the parenting of the mother and father, and the parents’ marital relations can all affect each other—both directly and indirectly. The parents’ behavior has a direct effect on the child. The parents’ marital relationship has an indirect effect on the child."
 },
 {
  "id": 238,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe some of the general developmental changes in parentchild relationships that take place during middle and late childhood.",
  "answer": "Some researchers found that parents of 5- to 12-year-old children spent less than half as much time on caregiving, instruction, reading, talking, and playing compared to parents of preschoolers. Despite this reduction in time, parents are still very important to children at these ages. They are particularly influential in stimulating and supporting their children’s academic performance. Children’s achievement levels in school are strongly influenced by the value their parents place on education. Parents also influence their children’s extracurricular activities. Research studies have found that the degree to which parents enroll their children in activities such as music and sports has a strong influence on whether children will participate in such activities. Parental discipline shifts from physical (commonly used with preschoolers) to verbal and behavioral as children grow older. Parents gradually allow children more control as they develop more self-regulation. Major shifts toward autonomy, including relating regularly to non-familial adults (like teachers), emerge in adolescence."
 },
 {
  "id": 239,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the general emotional and social characteristics of children raised using each of Diana Baumrind’s four parenting styles.",
  "answer": "According to Baumrind, parents with authoritarian styles, which combine high demand and control with low acceptance and responsiveness, tend to produce unhappy, fearful children who feel anxiety over comparisons with others, have weak communication skills, and do not initiate activities. Parents with neglectful styles, which employ low demand, control, acceptance, and responsiveness, tend to produce children who are immature, are socially incompetent, have difficulty coping with independence, have poor self-control, and exhibit low self-esteem. They may also be alienated from their families. As teens, they may display truant and\/or delinquent behaviors. Parents with indulgent styles, which combine high acceptance and responsiveness with low demand and control, think the warmth and freedom they provide will produce confident, creative children. However, these children have problems with self-control; disrespect others; and may be egocentric, noncompliant, and domineering. They may also have difficulty with peer interactions.\n\nAuthoritative parents, who combine high acceptance, responsiveness, demand, and control, tend to produce children who are self-reliant, self-controlled, cheerful, and achievement-oriented. They usually get along well with peers and adults, and cope well with stress."
 },
 {
  "id": 240,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Summarize James Marcia’s theory of identity. Identify his primary influence, the two components of identity development that determine identity status, and the four identity statuses he proposed.",
  "answer": "James Marcia based his theory of identity on Erik Erikson’s theory of psychosocial development. Erikson’s developmental stage of identity vs. role confusion is associated with adolescence. Marcia identified four ways of resolving the identity crisis associated with this stage, which he called identity statuses. Marcia proposed that these statuses are determined by the presence, absence, or degree of crisis and\/or commitment. He defines “crisis” as a period during identity development when the individual is exploring alternatives. He defines “commitment” as making a personal investment in an identity. Marcia’s first identity status is identity diffusion, meaning individuals have experienced neither crisis nor commitment. They are undecided and usually uninterested in identity. The second identity status is identity foreclosure. Individuals have made a commitment, but have not encountered a crisis. Teens whose parents have imposed commitments on them before they could explore alternatives on their own are often in identity foreclosure. The third is identity moratorium. Individuals are in a crisis but have vague or no commitments. The fourth is identity achievement. Individuals have experienced a crisis and made a commitment."
 },
 {
  "id": 241,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify five types of peer status children experience according to developmental psychologists, and describe the characteristics of each.",
  "answer": "Developmental psychologists routinely study sociometric status, which is how much a child is liked or disliked by his or her peer group. Developmental psychologists typically evaluate this status either by asking children how much they like or dislike each of their classmates, or by asking them to nominate the classmates they like and dislike the most. Psychologists have identified five basic types of peer status. “Popular” children are seldom disliked by peers, and are often nominated as best friends by classmates. “Average” children are disliked and liked by an average number of their peers, and receive an average number of positive and negative nominations from their peers. “Neglected” children are seldom nominated as best friends, but are not actively disliked by peers either. They are more ignored by others rather than considered friends or enemies. “Rejected” children, like neglected children, are infrequently nominated as best friends. Unlike neglected children, however, they are actively disliked by peers. “Controversial” children receive frequent nominations both as best friends and as people who are disliked."
 },
 {
  "id": 242,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define the family life cycle and name its five stages. Describe some aspects of moving through these stages. Identify a benefit of successful transitions, according to family life cycle theory.",
  "answer": "The family life cycle represents the intellectual and emotional stages that an individual goes through as a member of a family over its life span. In each stage, we encounter challenges within our family lives that lead to the acquisition of new skills or the building upon of existing ones to cope with these challenges. Developing these skills enables us to work through the changes inherent in family life. The family life cycle is made up of these stages: (1) independence, (2) coupling or marriage, (3) parenting children from infancy through adolescence, (4) launching children as young adults, and (5) retirement or the senior years. Our mastery of the milestones and skills associated with each stage enables us to progress to the next stage. We will still move to the next stage without mastering the previous stage’s skills. However, lack of mastery leads to relationship problems and difficulties in making future transitions. Family life cycle theory suggests that successful transitions may also prevent stress-related and emotional disorders and diseases."
 },
 {
  "id": 243,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Cite some cultural differences in various parts of the world related to the roles of adolescents.",
  "answer": "In cross-cultural comparisons of adolescents, researchers noted numerous variations in customs and traditions related to adolescence. These variations were noted in 2002. In India, two-thirds of teenagers consented to arranged marriages chosen by their parents. In the Philippines, many teenage girls moved to the city to get jobs and send the money they earned home to their families, giving up their own futures. Many adolescents in Middle Eastern countries were prohibited from interacting with the opposite sex, even in school. In many developing nations, including Kenya, “street” youth have learned to survive in extremely stressful life circumstances. Some have even been abandoned by their parents. They may engage in prostitution and\/or delinquent activities to provide for themselves financially. Researchers also found that while people have been marrying at later ages than previous generations in the United States, youth in Russia have been marrying at earlier ages to engage in socially acceptable sexual activity."
 },
 {
  "id": 244,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe some of the major aspects of development during the coupling stage of the family life cycle, according to family life cycle theory.",
  "answer": "After attaining independence in the first (teen-young adult) stage, we explore our ability to commit to a new family and lifestyle in the coupling stage. In addition to the adaptations and relationship building skills learned in the independence stage, marriages or committed civil unions usually demand other unique skills. Our experiences and relationships in our original families influence our contributions to the new family systems we form, which incorporate our personal values, expectations, and beliefs. In a marriage or union, we combine our family system with our partner’s family system. This requires both partners to reshape their goals. A characteristic of the most effective relationships is the ability of the partners to take their two viewpoints and create a third choice that neither had previously considered.\n\nInstead of sacrificing something, which is a requirement of compromises, the couple generates an additional, better alternative. When we become part of a couple, we often find that some of our earlier expectations were unrealistic. We may need to adjust our expectations regarding finances, in-law relationships, recreational pursuits, sexuality, friendships, and placing another’s needs before our own."
 },
 {
  "id": 245,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Describe some of the major aspects of development during the independence stage of the family life cycle, according to family life cycle theory.",
  "answer": "The independence stage is considered the most critical stage of the family life cycle. Its developments incorporate aspects of Erikson’s psychosocial developmental stages of identity vs. role confusion (adolescence) and intimacy vs. isolation (young adulthood). In this stage, we begin separating from our families, working toward supporting ourselves physically, financially, emotionally, and socially. We further define our unique individual identities. In intimate relationships, we learn about similarity, compatibility, attachment, non-familial dependence, commitment, and shared emotion. Lesbian, gay, bisexual, and transgendered (LGBT) individuals may “come out” to others during this stage. We explore career interests and goals and establish ourselves in work. We also become responsible for our own health, developing habits related to nutrition, exercise, and sex. In addition to identity, we develop trust, morality, initiative, and work ethics. Even after the actual independence stage is over, we continue to learn additional skills related to independence throughout our lives."
 },
 {
  "id": 246,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of the early part of the parenting phase in family life cycle theory related to having a baby, including roles and changes for the adults.",
  "answer": "Parenting is among the most challenging parts of the family life cycle. Because having children takes up so much time and attention, mastering communication, problem solving, and relationship skills in earlier phases is important. It is more difficult to develop them during such a busy time. Additionally, the parenting stage routinely challenges these skills. Each adult in this stage has three separate, demanding roles: individual, partner, and parent. Partners’ individual identities shift, and so does how they relate to one another and to others. Successful transitions to this phase depend on having mastered skills for compromise and commitment in earlier stages. As well as joy, prospective parents experience stress and fear. Pregnancy and childbirth are enormously stressful for women physiologically, emotionally, and psychologically. It is common for women to experience anxiety and fear at this time. Men often don’t express their fears and emotions, which can lead to health problems."
 },
 {
  "id": 247,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify the major goal of the coupling\/marriage stage of the family life cycle, according to family life cycle theory. Discuss a prerequisite for this stage, applications, life skills learned, challenges, and specific goals.",
  "answer": "According to family life cycle theory, the major goal of the coupling\/marriage stage is to achieve interdependence. The prerequisite for this is the achievement of independence during the previous stage. Interdependence is characterized by fully participating in a relationship, sharing goals, and sometimes deferring your needs in favor of your partner’s needs. The life skills we learn in the coupling phase provide a basis for parent-child, teacher-student, physician-patient, and other relationships. We learn skills related to problem solving, advanced interpersonal communication, forming boundaries in relationships, and sharing goals for emotional and spiritual development. We also learn when to put our partner’s needs first. This stage includes challenges, such as making the transition to a new family system, including our partners in our relationships with friends and family members, prioritizing another’s needs, and committing to making the marriage or union work. The more specific goals of the coupling stage are to realign our relationships with our family of origin and our friends to include our partner, and to create a new family with our partner."
 },
 {
  "id": 248,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of the phase of parenting adolescents, according to family life cycle theory.",
  "answer": "Adolescence challenges parents’ relationship skills, but also affords creative exploration and positive growth for all family members. The most successful families with adolescents have developed strong and flexible relationships through learning good skills related to trust, support, mutual care, communication, and problem solving. Teens seek to separate from the family and become independent, yet still need support. Parents’ strengths as individuals and as a couple are crucial. Parents need to be flexible, setting boundaries and limits for teens while also encouraging exploration. A primary challenge for parents is developing adult relationships with their children. Well-developed individual identities in parents equip them to cope with the challenges of adolescents’ experiments and changes. Parents without strong individual identities will feel threatened. Late in this stage, parental focus shifts from helping teens mature to career and relationship issues. This transition is less problematic if parents nurture, not neglect, their individual development and relationship. At this stage, parents also begin to consider caring for their own aging parents."
 },
 {
  "id": 249,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss some key aspects of the parenting phase of the family life cycle related to parenting young children, including role changes, prerequisite skills, and specific goals.",
  "answer": "In family life cycle theory, parenting young children involves incorporating them into other relationships as a key emotional aspect. Members of couples transition to being parents. While they are still developing as individuals, they are concurrently becoming decision makers for their family. Strong marriages result when each partner continues to express his or her individuality, while also working together well as a couple. Strong relationships between parents benefit the child, whose healthy development relies on his or her parents providing a safe, loving, and organized environment. Because caring for young children greatly reduces a couple’s “alone time,” having learned life skills like compromising for the family’s welfare in earlier phases is important to the success of the relationship. When parents of young children have not previously mastered these skills, extramarital affairs and divorces are common. Specific goals of this stage are adjusting the marital system to include children, assuming parental roles, and realigning extended family relationships to include grandparenting and parenting roles."
 },
 {
  "id": 250,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify some of the physiological and psychological stressors parents in the “empty nest”\/launching adult children phase of the family life cycle commonly experience, and outline the specific goals of this stage.",
  "answer": "By the time their children have grown up and are leaving home, most parents are in middle age. At this time in the family life cycle, middle-aged adults’ energy levels decline. Chronic illnesses are diagnosed in some adults, and midlife health issues develop. These include such things as weight problems, high blood pressure, arthritis, menopause, osteoporosis, cardiovascular disease, stress-related illnesses, and depression. In addition to health problems associated with aging, many middle-aged adults are caring for their own aged parents. This is a source of additional physical and psychological stress, which can have an impact on the health of adult caregivers. Specific goals of the launching phase of the family life cycle are to refocus on the couple’s relationship without children; to develop adult relationships with their grown children; and, when their grown children start their own families, to realign their relationships to include new in-laws and grandchildren."
 },
 {
  "id": 251,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss some salient aspects of the “empty nest” stage of launching adult children, according to family life cycle theory.",
  "answer": "The period when grown children leave home has many pros and cons. When a family has developed strong skills throughout the family life cycle, children have learned what they need to feel ready to cope with life’s challenges independently. Parents who are relieved of many daily parental duties may rekindle their relationships as couples. Some also resume or revise their career goals. Couples who did not share in their transitions may find they have grown apart or are no longer compatible. However, according to family life cycle theory, they can still learn whatever skills they did not master in earlier stages through self-examination, education, and counseling. In this phase, developing adult relationships with one’s children continues to be as important as is it was while parenting adolescents. One challenge is accepting new family members via adult children’s relationships. “Empty nest” parents may reassess their life priorities and beliefs and forgive others’ past wrongs."
 },
 {
  "id": 252,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Define the terms risk factors and resilience factors and describe their impact on development. Identify the domains related to risk factors and resilience factors. Identify several risk factors and their corresponding resilience factors.",
  "answer": "Risk factors are situations or conditions that are empirically associated with certain outcomes (Reddy et al, 2001). Resilience is a quality that enables individuals to “….make appropriate behavioral choices in the presence of multiple risk factors” (Finley, 1994). Risk and resilience function via complex interactions across domains of life, including the domains of the individual, the family, the school, social peer groups, and the community. Some individual risk factors researchers have identified are cognitive deficits: in reading readiness, in following directions, in vocabulary, and in social skills. Resilience factors that help offset negative outcomes from these risk factors include early intervention programs involving training in cognitive skills; training programs for parents that teach them how to teach their children; and preschool programs such as Head Start, Jump Start, or the Perry Preschool Program to bring young children’s school readiness up to sufficient levels so they can succeed when they begin elementary school."
 },
 {
  "id": 253,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Discuss some aspects of the retirement\/senior phase of the family life cycle, including benefits, challenges, and specific goals.",
  "answer": "According to family life cycle theory, seniors often enjoy freedom from the responsibilities of parenting and careers that allows them to explore personal interests. They also experience family changes as their children marry, make them grandparents, and\/or divorce. Some retirees focusing on sustaining their spousal relationship and exploring their own interests are also still caring for aged parents. Deaths of spouses and\/or other family members, declining physical and\/or mental health, and changes in financial or social status are additional challenges of the senior phase. Family life cycle theory finds that how well we adjusted to changes in earlier phases determines our quality of life in this phase. Specific goals of this stage are: maintaining your and your partner’s physical functions and interests, exploring new familial and social roles, emotionally supporting adult children and extended family, including older adults’ experience and wisdom in the family system, supporting older generations without overextending oneself, coping with others’ deaths, preparing for one’s own death, and reviewing and reflecting on one’s life."
 },
 {
  "id": 254,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify some risk factors related to the domain of school that can adversely affect child development, and outline corresponding factors of resilience that can counter these risk factors.",
  "answer": "One primary risk factor related to the school domain that adversely affects child development is low school involvement by the student. A major contributor to low involvement in school is a cycle of failure. For example, a student finds academics difficult; the student engages in escape behaviors to escape his or her failure; and the teacher avoids the issue, perpetuating the failure cycle. Some resilience factors to support students identified by educational psychology researchers are: including students in school policy decisions, matching instruction to individual students’ ability levels, engaging in educational practices that make it easier for students to succeed, providing effective academic instruction, and using effective behavior management techniques. Another major risk factor is the chain of events stemming from poor involvement in academics. These include truancy, suspension, expulsion, and dropping out. Resilience factors to combat this include: increasing students’ active participation, providing instruction that is meaningful to students, facilitating prosocial student groups, developing functional behavior assessments, and replacing participation in gangs and other deviant behaviors with more prosocial behaviors."
 },
 {
  "id": 255,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Identify a number of risk factors related to the domain of the family that affect development, and outline corresponding factors of resilience that can counter these risk factors.",
  "answer": "In the family domain, a significant risk factor that adversely affects child development is poor parenting skills. These manifest in child neglect, child abuse, harsh treatment, rejection, parental substance abuse, and parental crime. Prenatal parental training is a resilience factor that can mitigate the risk factor of poor parenting skills by teaching parenting skills to couples or individuals before the child’s birth. This training helps parents learn how to produce and raise healthier children. Risk factors in the child include malnutrition, aggression, and emotional problems. Resilience factors to counter the negative outcomes of these conditions include teaching the child self-care skills, skills to promote and maintain their health, and emotional coping strategies. Another significant family risk factor is poverty. Researchers have found this factor is the most predictive of behavioral problems and school failure. Resilience factors to combat poverty include helping families access needed medical, social, and employment services; and teaching children’s educators about poverty."
 },
 {
  "id": 256,
  "topic": "Growth and Lifespan Development",
  "question": "Name some risk factors related to the domain of the community that threaten normal child development, and identify some corresponding resilience factors that can offset the associated negative outcomes.",
  "answer": "In the community, forms of media such as television constitute a risk factor because they can influence children’s attitudes, beliefs, and behaviors. Some of these negative influences on children include habituating them to reports of crime; exposing them to video violence, which promotes aggressive behaviors; and providing unrealistic and\/or unhealthy role models. Recreational activities can be risk factors when they are not monitored or supervised, and are dangerous and\/or unhealthy. They can also detract from or interfere with academic progress if they are indulged in excessively. Disorganized neighborhoods, drugs, and firearms are additional risk factors. Resilience factors include monitoring children and teens, teaching them how to reflect on their own and others’ attitudes and behaviors, creating after-school programs that provide opportunities to participate in positive leisure activities, providing access to community mentors and mentoring programs, establishing links between the community and the school, and providing community drug prevention programs for youth and adults."
 },
 {
  "id": 257,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the term psychometrics. Identify two main research tasks in psychometrics. Identify professionals who can work as psychometrics practitioners and outline practice requirements. Name some pioneers of the field of psychometrics.",
  "answer": "Psychometrics is the theory and associated techniques of psychological measurement. It includes measuring abilities, knowledge, attitudes, and personality traits, as well as conducting educational measurements. Two major research tasks in psychometrics are (1) constructing and validating various measurement instruments, and (2) developing and refining various theoretical approaches to psychological measurement. Psychometrics practitioners may be clinical psychologists, school psychologists, human resources professionals, or learning and development professionals. Regardless of their occupation, practitioners must possess specific psychometrics credentials. The founder of psychometrics was Sir Francis Galton, who was the first person to apply statistical methods to study intelligence and differences among humans. He also coined the phrase “nature vs. nurture,” created the statistical concept of correlation, identified regression toward the mean, and introduced questionnaires and surveys for data collection, among many other things. Psychometrics pioneers include Wilhelm Wundt, the father of experimental psychology; psychologist and IQ test creator James Cattell; Charles Spearman, the creator of “g” (general intelligence) and the Spearman correlation coefficient, as well as a factor analysis pioneer; and L.L."
 },
 {
  "id": 258,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Explain how reliability is estimated in classical test theory, and outline the importance of Cronbach’s alpha.",
  "answer": "According to classical test theory, it is impossible to make direct estimates of test reliability, because it would require knowing a test-taker’s true score, which, according to this theory, can never be obtained. Due to some inevitable measurement error, only the observed score can be obtained. One potential way to estimate instrument reliability in classical test theory is to construct a “parallel test,” which provides the same true and observed score variances as the original test for each individual test-taker. However, parallel tests are seldom used in psychometrics practice because it is too hard to find or create them for each original test. The popular alternative is an internal consistency measure called Cronbach’s alpha (α). Its formula gives a lower reliability limit, so the reliability of test scores in a given population is always higher than the value of Cronbach’s α is in that population. This makes it workable empirically, so researchers often use it. Cronbach’s α can be calculated with standard statistical packages like Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) and Statistical Analysis System (SAS)."
 },
 {
  "id": 259,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Explain some salient characteristics of classical test theory, including its purpose, true vs. observed scores, and error.",
  "answer": "Classical test theory is a body of psychometrics theories that predict the results of psychological testing by considering such factors as test-takers’ abilities or test item difficulty. Its main purpose is to understand and enhance the reliability of psychological tests. It is similar to true score theory. The term “classical” identifies this theory not only as older than other theories, but also as distinct from more modern theories, which are collectively known as item response theory. Classical test theory’s assumption is that everyone has a “true score,” which is obtained only if no measurement errors occur. The “true score” is the expected score over an infinite number of independent test administrations, and therefore it can never be obtained. There is always some measurement error, so only the “observed score” can be obtained. Thus, where T = true score, X = observed score, and E = error, X = T + E. True score variance + error score variance = observed score variance. The ratio of true score variance to observed score variance equals the reliability of observed scores."
 },
 {
  "id": 260,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the term “item response function” as it relates to item response theory. Discuss the relationships among item parameters, trait, item difficulty, and location.",
  "answer": "One of the assumptions of item response theory is that a test-taker’s response to a test item can be represented by the item response function (IRF) model. The IRF is used to calculate the probability that a test-taker with a certain ability level will give the correct response. The chances of test-takers with higher ability levels getting the right answer are greater than those of test-takers with lower ability levels. For example, those with higher ability levels in math are more likely to get mathematical test items correct. An IRF has a set of item parameters. The item parameters, combined with the test-taker’s ability, determine the exact probability value. In attainment testing, the test-taker’s “ceiling” is the item beyond which the test-taker cannot provide the correct answer. Therefore, the item’s location corresponds to its difficulty. The IRF model scales the person’s trait (the test-taker’s ability) onto the same continuum as the item’s difficulty (location). Thus, correct item responses reflect ability level, and a person’s trait (ability) level can be compared to an item’s difficulty level."
 },
 {
  "id": 261,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Provide a general overview of item response theory, including synonyms, how it differs from classical test theory, the principle on which it is based, and two of its specific advantages over classical test theory.",
  "answer": "Item response theory is also called “modern latent trait theory,” “modern mental test theory,” and “strong true score theory.” It is based on applying relevant mathematical models to test data. It is generally preferred over classical test theory for “high-stakes” exams like the Graduate Record Examinations (GRE) and Graduate Management Admission Test (GMAT).\n\nWhereas classical test theory focuses on instruments at the whole test level, item response theory focuses at the level of individual items on a test. It is based on the principle that the probability of a correct response to a test item is a mathematical function of item and person parameters. Person parameters, such as intelligence or aptitude, are called “abilities” or “latent traits.” Item parameters are things like difficulty or discrimination. Test reliability can be improved using IRT’s more sophisticated data instead of classical test theory. Another advantage over classical test theory is that applications like computerized adaptive testing that are not compatible with classical test theory can be used with item response theory. Item response theory assumes: (1) a one-dimensional trait, θ; (2) local independence of test items; and (3) that a test-taker’s item response can be modeled by a mathematical “item response function.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 262,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe observer-report data as it is used in psychological assessment. Include a discussion of advantages and disadvantages, two main strategies for selecting observers, and the pros and cons of one of these strategies.",
  "answer": "In addition to self-reports, data can be obtained from others’ observations of the individual being assessed. One advantage is that multiple observers can be used instead of just one. This permits assessors to evaluate inter-rater reliability, which is the amount of agreement among observers. Also, statistically averaging multiple observers’ assessments decreases the biases and idiosyncrasies of single observers. Another advantage is that observers can report on an individual’s interactions with others, his or her individual status in a group hierarchy, social reputation, and the impression he or she makes on others. All of this information is unavailable from other sources. One strategy is selecting trained professional observers who are strangers to the participant. The other strategy is selecting friends, relatives, roommates, or other people who know the participant. An advantage of this is that multiple social personalities that vary according to contexts can be assessed. There is also more opportunity to observe the participant’s natural behavior. A disadvantage is that intimate observers may be biased."
 },
 {
  "id": 263,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify the main advantages associated with self-reports. Describe the following types of self-reports used in psychological assessment: structured and unstructured interviews, open-ended and structured questionnaires, checklists, and Likert scales.",
  "answer": "Advantages of self-reports are that individuals can provide information about their own feelings, wishes, beliefs, and private experiences that are inaccessible to others; their self-esteem and perception of others’ esteem; how they relate to others, and vice versa; their short-term and long-term goals; and their deepest fantasies and fears. In unstructured interviews, the assessor asks the individual open-ended, “shotgun” questions, which might include, “Tell me about your childhood\/job\/marriage.” Structured interviews involve asking more specific questions. Open-ended self-reports include the Twenty Statements Test, wherein the individual completes 20 blank items that all begin with “I am…..” This reflects one’s self-concept.\n\nPsychologists interpret responses using techniques such as counting how many completed responses refer to certain dimensions (shyness, intelligence, sociability, etc.). Some structured questionnaires use simple checklists, wherein the participant selects adjectives describing traits he or she feels accurately describe him or her. These might include “generous,” “anxious,\" “artistic,” “good-natured,” “greedy,” “zany,” etc. Other, more complex questionnaires use a Likert scale. Respondents rate traits on a seven-point scale to indicate traits that are most characteristic of them and least characteristic of them. This helps researchers measure relative degrees of traits."
 },
 {
  "id": 264,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss the purpose of standardized test data in assessment, and identify some limitations and advantages.",
  "answer": "When researchers place participants into standardized testing situations, the purpose is to find out whether different individuals respond differently to an identical situation. This can be useful for eliciting behaviors that reflect different personality variables, not just for obtaining comparative school aptitude or achievement scores. One limitation of standardized test data is that some participants try to guess what the experimenters are measuring, and then change their responses to give a certain impression of themselves. Another is that the participants may not define the testing situation the same way as the experimenters do. If their conceptions are not confirmed by the testing situation, this can introduce error. Another disadvantage is that standardized testing situations are interpersonal by nature, so experimenters can accidentally influence participants’ behavior. Advantages include the fact that tests can be designed to elicit behaviors not readily observed in real life, investigators can control contexts and eliminate extraneous influences, and investigators can test specific hypotheses regarding causality."
 },
 {
  "id": 265,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss using naturalistic observation vs. using artificial observation to collect observer-report data in psychological assessments, and describe some advantages and disadvantages.",
  "answer": "Experimenters typically use artificial observation in laboratory settings. They give instructions to participants for performing tasks and observe their behavior in the settings they have constructed. An advantage is that experimenters are able to control the surrounding conditions and events, and to elicit the pertinent behavior(s) from the participant. The disadvantage is that experimenters are not able to observe the participants in the context of everyday life, so the data collected are not as realistic. Naturalistic observation involves observing participants during their normal life experiences. For example, an observer might be in a participant’s home while they do everyday, real-life activities. Or, an observer might follow a child for an entire day to observe his or her activities. The particular purposes of a research study and the strengths and weaknesses of each method should be considered when choosing whether to use naturalistic or artificial observation methods."
 },
 {
  "id": 266,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the term validity as it relates to testing. Define face validity, criterion validity, and convergent validity.",
  "answer": "In testing, validity refers to the extent to which a test measures what it claims to measure. Face validity is whether a test appears on the surface to measure what it purports to measure. It is more so an assumption than evidence of true validity. Criterion (or predictive) validity is whether a test predicts external criteria. For example, a test of sensation-seeking should predict who would pursue real-life sensation-seeking activities like skydiving or bungee jumping. A test measuring conscientiousness that predicts who shows up on time and follows rules has high criterion validity and predictive validity. Convergent validity is whether a test correlates with other relevant measures. If a self-report measurement of tolerance correlates well with peer opinions of tolerance, or if mechanical recordings of activity levels correlate highly with observer-based reports of activity levels, the convergent validity of these tests is high."
 },
 {
  "id": 267,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the term reliability as it relates to assessment. Identify and describe three ways to estimate reliability.",
  "answer": "Reliability refers to how closely a measurement reflects the true level of the measured trait or quantity. If an individual’s true IQ is 115, for example, a test with perfect reliability would give a score of 115. It would also result in that same score every time the test is given to the same person. One way of estimating reliability is through repeated measurement. For example, a group of people could be given a test one day, and then be given it again a month later. If the scores from both tests are very similar or identical, the test has high test-retest reliability. Another method is to see whether the items within one test are closely related with one another. If so, all items are measuring the same trait or quantity, and the test has high internal consistency reliability. A third way of measuring reliability that can only be used with observer-based measures is to get measurements from multiple observers. When they agree, the measure has high inter-rater reliability; if observers disagree, inter-rater reliability is low."
 },
 {
  "id": 268,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the term generalizability as it relates to assessment. Discuss how results from different groups of people and different conditions are useful in determining generalizability, and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Generalizability is the extent to which a test can be generalized across contexts and maintain its validity. A personality psychologist might want to know whether a questionnaire retains predictive validity with different age groups, ethnic groups, genders, or cultures. For example, some tests yield different results when given to European Americans than when given to African Americans, men and women might respond differently to the same measurement instrument, or a test might or might not measure the same quality or trait in university students as it does in middle-aged adults. When a test or scale applies to a wide variety of people and cultural contexts, it has high generalizability across populations. Generalizability is also affected by different conditions. For example, a scale measuring dominance might predict who becomes a leader in business settings differently from who becomes a leader in informal social settings. A test that measures such qualities equally in different settings has high generalizability across conditions."
 },
 {
  "id": 269,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define discriminant validity and describe how it differs from convergent validity. Define the terms theoretical constructs and construct validity, and include examples.",
  "answer": "While convergent validity is how strongly a test correlates with other measures of the same characteristic, discriminant validity is the opposite. It is the extent to which a test measures what it should not correlate with or measure. It is important for researchers to be aware of a test’s discriminant validity. For example, a researcher needs to know the discriminant validity of a test measuring life satisfaction that also measures social desirability (the tendency to say nice things about ourselves). Theoretical constructs are abstract concepts, such as personality variables like intelligence or introversion. Construct validity means a test measures what it claims to measure (the general definition of validity), that it correlates with what it should (convergent validity), and that it does not correlate with what it shouldn’t (discriminant validity). Thus, construct validity incorporates face validity, criterion\/predictive validity, convergent validity, and discriminant validity. For example, if a questionnaire testing creativity yields scores that correlate with other creativity measures conducted with the same people (such as friends’ ratings, art class grades, and behavioral test data), and it does not correlate with intelligence measures, it has enough construct validity to be useful."
 },
 {
  "id": 270,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the MMPI personality test, including how it departed from other personality tests commonly used at the time it was developed.",
  "answer": "The Minnesota Multiphasic Personality Inventory (MMPI) is the most widely-used personality inventory. It is often used in clinical settings to inform patient diagnoses and treatments. Unlike the predominantly theoretical and intuitive approaches used in the 1930s and 1940s when it was developed, the MMPI was innovative because it used empirical methods. Items were only included in a scale if they clearly differentiated between two groups (those with schizophrenia and a normal comparison group, for example). Each item had to show validity through being answered similarly by members of one group, but differently by the two compared groups. The MMPI has 10 clinical scales to distinguish respective clinical groups, such as those with schizophrenia, those with bipolar disorder, etc. It has validity scales to reveal inaccurate response patterns due to carelessness, evasiveness, defensiveness, or dishonesty. Testers check the validity scales first before interpreting scores. The MMPI also has content scales, meaning items chosen for each clinically pertinent topic are based on their theoretical relationship to the topic. Items are also chosen for their statistical homogeneity. Each scale should measure a single, unified concept."
 },
 {
  "id": 271,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify two different general types of personality tests and how they are used. Name some popular personality tests.",
  "answer": "Personality tests can be objective or projective. Objective tests are fairly simple to administer and score. Some even use computer scoring. Responses are typically forced-choice, like yes\/no or true\/false. They may also use Likert scales, in which choices reflecting several (usually five to seven) degrees of agreement or disagreement with a statement are presented.\n\nSome potential choices would be “I enjoy loud parties” or “I prefer working alone.” Projective tests use standardized, ambiguous stimuli and open-ended questions. Participants’ responses project their own interpretations onto the stimuli. Popular projective tests include the Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) and the Rorschach inkblot test. Psychologists frequently use a combination of different personality tests to get a more comprehensive understanding of the individual’s personality. A common objective personality test is a self-report inventory. One of the first, from 1917, was the Woodworth Personal Data Sheet, which asked questions like “Are you often frightened in the middle of the night?” Today’s personality inventories use statements. The Minnesota\n\nMultiphasic Personality Inventory (MMPI) and the NEO Personality Inventory (NEO-PI) are popular objective personality inventories."
 },
 {
  "id": 272,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the Rorschach test as a projective personality measure, and identify some pros and cons.",
  "answer": "The Rorschach test is more commonly known as the “inkblot test.” The blots are not representational images but ambiguous, symmetrical shapes. Respondents are asked first to identify a blot as whatever it looks like to them, and then to elaborate on their responses. Testers record what respondents say, the time they take to respond, the total time taken per inkblot, and how they handle the card. They score responses based on three features: (1) location, which refers to whether the respondent refers to the whole blot or part of it, and the size of details mentioned; (2) response content, which is the nature of the thing or process the respondent saw; and (3) determinants, which refers to the characteristics of the card (color, shading, etc.) that elicited the response. Uniqueness and originality versus popularity and conformity of responses may also be scored. Controversy over the Rorschach stems from the fact that practitioners use it to make diagnoses without supporting empirical evidence. However, the test has been proven valid for diagnosing abnormal thought patterns symptomatic of specific psychological disorders."
 },
 {
  "id": 273,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the NEO-PI personality test, and discuss its theoretical basis.",
  "answer": "The NEO Personality Inventory is based on the five-factor model of personality. NEO stands for the first three personality factors: neuroticism, extraversion, and openness. The other two are agreeableness and conscientiousness. It tests 30 separate traits, six for each of the main factors. For example, individual scales measuring anxiety, angry hostility, depression, self-consciousness, impulsiveness, and vulnerability represent six facets of the neuroticism factor. Many research studies on the NEO-PI have found that its dimensions have high reliability; homogeneity; and good criterion, predictive, and construct validity. Psychologists use this personality inventory to study stability and personality changes across the life span. They also use it to examine the relationships between personality traits and different life events, such as career success or early retirement, and the relationships between personality traits and physical health."
 },
 {
  "id": 274,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the Beck Depression Inventory as a tool for assessing emotional functioning.",
  "answer": "Dr. Aaron Beck and his colleagues developed the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI) to assess the presence of depression in both normal and clinical patients. When he began practicing therapy and conducting research, Beck found that a big drawback in psychotherapy was a lack of empirical evidence to support diagnoses. Accordingly, he developed tests to do this, including the BDI. It takes roughly five minutes to complete, and can be self-administered or conducted orally with a trained test administrator. It applies to people between the ages of 13 and 80. Each item lists four statements about a specific symptom of depression that increase in severity. The BDI’s criteria for depression are aligned with those of the DSM (Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of Mental Disorders), the APA’s official set of diagnostic criteria. BDI items address symptoms such as loss of energy, increases and decreases in appetite and sleep, and depressive symptoms over the past two weeks, which is a current DSM criterion for diagnosis."
 },
 {
  "id": 275,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the TAT as a projective personality test. Identify some criticisms of the test, popular uses, and one measurement the test is used for that has been validated.",
  "answer": "The Thematic Apperception Test (TAT) involves the use of picture cards showing scenes that are ambiguous and open to interpretation. Respondents are asked to tell stories about what the people in the pictures are doing, what they are thinking, what led up to the scene, and how it will end. Testers evaluate the respondent’s behavior and the content and organization of the stories to determine some of the respondent’s personality traits, main motivations, and concerns. A respondent who describes many pictures as involving someone plotting against someone else, for example, might be evaluated as having paranoid ideations. Or, one who tells stories in an organized, serious manner, focusing on people keeping their promises, might be evaluated as conscientious. Criticism of the test is related to testers using the TAT for purposes for which its validity has not been proven. It has frequently been used to show individual differences in what needs—the need for power, the need for affiliation, the need for achievement, for example—are predominant. Several decades of research has proven that the TAT is a valid tool for measuring the need for achievement."
 },
 {
  "id": 276,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss some ways neuroimaging techniques can show neuropsychological functions, and provide some examples of how they have been used to assess affective states.",
  "answer": "Neuroimaging methods such as positron emission tomography (PET) scans, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI), and functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) can reveal which areas of the brain are more active during certain emotional states, as well as during certain cognitive processes. For example, neuropsychologists have discovered that people in the early phases of romantic love show more activity in the regions of their brains that are associated with motivational and reward systems. They found greater activity in these brain areas than in areas associated with sexual drives, suggesting that early romantic love is less motivated by needs for sex than by needs for other kinds of pleasure, such as the need for affiliation, the need for rewards, etc. Neuroimaging has also found that the same pleasure and reward circuits are activated in people’s brains by receiving, observing, and\/or anticipating food, sex, beauty, and addictive drugs and substances. Additionally, psychologists have used imaging techniques to study the neuroanatomy and affective elements of moral judgments."
 },
 {
  "id": 277,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the Beck Anxiety Inventory as a tool for assessing emotional function.",
  "answer": "When Dr. Aaron T. Beck first began practicing psychotherapy, he observed that the lack of empirical data to support psychological or psychiatric diagnoses was a major weakness in the field. To remedy this, he developed emotional tests, including the Beck Depression Inventory and the Beck Anxiety Inventory (BAI). The BAI takes 5 to 10 minutes to administer, and can be self-administered or conducted orally with a trained test administrator. It has 21 items. Patients respond to each item by rating it on a scale from zero to three to indicate the extent to which they feel the item does or does not represent their feelings. Each item describes an anxiety symptom that is subjective (personal, not objective reality), somatic (bodily), or panic-related. The BAI has been used in various clinical populations, and has been found effective for differentiating between anxious and non-anxious diagnostic groups. It is clinically validated, and was developed using data from patients diagnosed with panic disorders, as well as those who had or had not been diagnosed with agoraphobia, social phobia, obsessive-compulsive disorder, and generalized anxiety disorder."
 },
 {
  "id": 278,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify and describe the six scales used by the Suicide Evaluation.",
  "answer": "Suicide risk is not identified via any single symptom, but by a combination of symptoms. The Suicide Evaluation divides these into six scales.\n\nIf one scale’s score is elevated, suicide is a possibility. Risk increases when one or more additional scales are elevated. The first scale is the truthfulness scale, which identifies denial, guardedness, minimizing problems, and trying to “look good.” Elevated scores in this scale can indicate emotional detachment, emotional turmoil, defiance, withdrawal, or internalization. The second scale is the suicide scale, which measures an individual’s probability of committing suicide via verbal expressions of suicidal ideations and hints. The third scale is the depression scale, which measures melancholy, dysthymia, dysphoria, and depressed mood. These depreciated emotional states can range from normal to pathological. Depression is a major contributor to suicide. The fourth scale is the alcohol scale, which measures the severity of alcohol use and\/or abuse.\n\nSuch abuse often precedes suicide attempts, presumably because it can help the person become mentally or emotionally numb. The fifth scale is the drug scale, which measures the severity of drug use or abuse. Like alcohol abuse, drug abuse is associated with suicidal acts. The sixth scale is the stress coping scale, which measures an individual’s ability to cope with stress. Stress exacerbates mental and emotional problems, and inadequate coping skills can lead a person to escape from severe stress via suicide."
 },
 {
  "id": 279,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss the topic of mental health screening for suicide risk. Describe the Suicide Evaluation as an assessment instrument. Outline administration time, how it is scored and interpreted, and criteria for risk.",
  "answer": "National and worldwide suicide rates have been rising in the 21 st century. Most mental health professionals agree that not every patient must be screened for suicide risk, but emotionally disturbed and severely depressed patients should be. Conducting complete suicide evaluation interviews with every patient is impracticable for mental health professionals because of the associated time and energy requirements. A primary barrier to suicide prevention is not remediation of suicide risk, but identifying the risk. The Suicide Evaluation was developed to help mental health professionals determine an individual’s suicide risk. It takes 25 to 30 minutes to administer. Its reliability and validity have been proven. The patient responds to 142 test items. These items are scored, the scores are interpreted, and a report is generated and printed. This is all done by a computer program, and scoring the test and generating a report takes just two to three minutes. This test gives professionals an objective second opinion. Patients scoring in the 39 th percentile are at a low risk; a medium risk is associated with scores in the 40 th to 69 th percentiles; people with “problem” risk are those that score in the 70 th to 89 th percentile range, and are considered at risk for suicide; and a severe suicide risk is associated with scores in the 90 th to 100 th percentiles."
 },
 {
  "id": 280,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some assessment and screening tools used to identify violence in adults, and describe their applications.",
  "answer": "A dozen tests used for different purposes that assess adults’ potential for violent behavior are available from Behavior Data Systems. The Parolee Inventory evaluates prisoners being considered for parole. The Prison Inmate Inventory assesses risk, determines supervision levels, validates inmates’ readiness for changes in status or classification, and substantiates inmates’ rehabilitation and treatment needs. The Defendant Questionnaire evaluates defendants in drug courts. The Domestic Violence Inventory evaluates adult domestic violence offenders; there is also a short form of this inventory. The Reinstatement Review Inventory assesses whether adults whose driver’s licenses have been suspended or revoked should have them reinstated.\n\nThe Self-Audit is used in adult counseling and treatment intake, in probation and corrections programs, in courts, by health maintenance organizations (HMOs), and in employee assistance programs (EAPs). The Domestic Violence Inventory Pre-Post assesses domestic violence treatment effectiveness. The Offender Assessment Index is used for program intake, adult probation, and court defendants. The Sexual Adjustment Inventory is for accused or convicted sex offenders. The Substance Abuse QuestionnaireAdult Probation III is for screening and evaluating probationers."
 },
 {
  "id": 281,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Name several assessment instruments that test for violence in juveniles, and outline their applications in terms of settings, processes, situations, and diagnostic and\/or legal status of individuals.",
  "answer": "Behavior Data Systems offers four juvenile violence tests that have been demonstrated to be accurate, reliable, and valid. The Adolescent Chemical Dependency Inventory (ACDI)-Corrections Version II is one. It is used in juvenile court, including family court, drug court, municipal court, etc.; in probation departments; in community corrections departments; and in community treatment programs. The Juvenile Presentence Evaluation was developed specifically for use during juvenile presentence evaluations, as its name suggests. It is also used in juvenile court evaluations, in community corrections and probation departments, in juvenile drug courts, and by licensed and certified mental health professionals. The Domestic Violence Inventory is designed to assess juvenile domestic violence offenders. It is used in probation departments, counseling and treatment programs, and juvenile domestic violence court. The Sexual Adjustment Inventory-Juvenile is used to identify sexual deviance and paraphilias in accused or convicted sex offenders on probation or in the corrections system. It is also used during caseload evaluations, as a screening tool for individual or group counseling, and in treatment programs.\n\nEach instrument includes scales for truthfulness, violence, alcohol, drugs, distress, adjustment, etc."
 },
 {
  "id": 282,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe some ways to conduct assessments of individuals with English as a second language (ESL), English language learners (ELL), and those with limited proficiency in the English language. Include a discussion of alternate, simplified, adapted, and accommodated assessments.",
  "answer": "Alternate assessments for ESL\/ELL individuals let them respond in a different format. Assessors can label diagrams or pictures, and can draw pictures to represent concepts or ideas. They can explain ideas and ask questions orally for those who have adequate receptive English comprehension, but do not read English as well. Respondents can respond orally instead of in writing. Testers can supplement assessment instruments with pictures. When giving simplified assessments, assessors can provide ESL\/ELL individuals with word banks to assist translation and comprehension. With instruments giving multiple choices, choices could be reduced to two, as long as this does not compromise the test’s purpose, validity, reliability, content, or accuracy. When using adapted assessments, it is possible to administer only parts of some instruments to collect certain kinds of data, or to split tests up and administer portions separately. To give accommodated assessments, testers can use the same testing instruments, but give the ESL\/ELL respondent more time to complete them. Testers can also allow these students to use bilingual electronic dictionaries or translators if they are available."
 },
 {
  "id": 283,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some ways that assessment procedures can be adapted for diverse populations.",
  "answer": "One common way for assessors to adapt testing is to allow more time for a test-taker with a disability to complete a test. They can also redistribute time on power tests. For those who have difficulty with handwriting, scribes can be recruited to record test-takers’ responses. Another technique is to use ipsative measures. These involve comparing the test-taker’s scores and\/or responses to scores and responses previously obtained from the same individual. In school settings, assessors can also evaluate the process an individual used to get an answer, not just the final product. Assessors in any setting, not just educators, can depart from traditional methods of taking only spoken or written responses and consider alternative ways of responding. For example, respondents could use motor activity demonstrations; pantomime; photographs; graphic displays; or artistic expressions like musical composition, acting, collages, or sculptures. This is useful for patients with severe mental illness, autism spectrum disorders, emotional or behavioral disorders, and physical disabilities."
 },
 {
  "id": 284,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify and describe four types of observations that can be obtained in controlled settings when multidisciplinary staff’s observations are integrated into a patient’s psychiatric or psychological evaluation.",
  "answer": "Hospitals, residential treatment facilities, and other controlled settings afford opportunities to integrate observations and\/or assessments from nurses, social workers, case managers, peer counselors, chaplains, etc. into patients’ evaluations. These observations include: (1) general observations on the patient’s behavior, statements, concerns, cooperation with or resistance to staff, sleeping\/waking patterns, and self-care; (2) diagnosis-specific observations, such as confirming a diagnosis and assessing the severity, sub-type, and\/or complications of disorders (observing and recording withdrawal symptoms in addicts or conducting mealtime monitoring of patients with eating disorders, for example); (3) patient-specific observations, which are intended to assess a clinical hypothesis (if familial conflicts are suspected as contributors to a patient’s psychotic relapse, staff might closely observe the patient’s behavior following a family meeting, for example); and (4) observations of responses to treatment interventions. For the latter type of observation, the target behavior during a behavioral therapy trial would be systematically recorded. Effects of newly-prescribed medications could also be observed. Following behavioral and psychotherapeutic interventions, nurses can be asked to complete rating scales to measure changes."
 },
 {
  "id": 285,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss some guidelines for using interpreters during interview portions of psychiatric or psychological assessments.",
  "answer": "According to the APA and the U.S. government, when patients have limited English language proficiency, or are deaf or hard of hearing and communicate by using sign language, the use of professionally trained interpreters who also have mental health experience is recommended. Using family members, friends, or community members is discouraged, except in emergency situations or if the patient refuses the services of a professional interpreter, which should be documented in the patient’s records. If a professional interpreter is not available, one alternative is to use an interpreting service over the telephone. One weakness of this approach is that it can be more difficult to establish rapport with a patient when communicating in this way. In addition to having an interpreter, it can also help if the facility doing the testing has bilingual and bicultural staff members present. It is important to tell interpreters to translate the patient’s own words, and not to paraphrase them, except when they are doing so to make the meaning of idiomatic or other culture-specific communications clear."
 },
 {
  "id": 286,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Discuss some considerations related to gathering information for a risk assessment of a patient undergoing psychological evaluation.",
  "answer": "According to the APA, standardized rating scales for assessing suicidal or aggressive behaviors are frequently employed in research studies, and can help direct clinical inquiries. A limitation of their clinical use, however, is that they are not predictive enough. A clinical risk assessment includes suicide and homicide risks, plus risks for self-injurious behaviors (cutting, for instance), aggressive behaviors, neglecting self-care, and\/or neglecting care of dependents. Assessing specific risk factors informs interventions that can modify them to decrease overall risk. Risk factors include age, gender, and other demographic characteristics; past behaviors such as suicide attempts, self-injury, or aggression; psychiatric diagnoses; psychiatric symptoms, such as hopelessness or anxiety; co-existing general medical conditions; psychosocial stressors; sociocultural factors; and\/or individual strengths and vulnerabilities. The APA publishes a Practice Guideline for the Assessment and Treatment of Patients With Suicidal Behaviors. Risk assessments also include evaluating parenting ability if patients have dependent children, and evaluating the children’s mental health."
 },
 {
  "id": 287,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some types of information that would be integrated into a clinical psychological assessment.",
  "answer": "Integrating information helps the psychiatrist and\/or psychologist understand the patient as a unique, whole person and appreciate his or her environment, challenges, strengths, and coping skills. The purpose of an evaluation dictates the scope and depth of the patient-specific information collected. Psychological, sociocultural, neurobiological, and phenomenological issues relevant to diagnosis and treatment are included.\n\nInformation that may be integrated into a clinical psychological assessment includes the patient’s individual characteristics; general medical conditions; genetic predispositions; laboratory abnormalities; developmental history; past life experiences; quantity and quality of interpersonal relationships; central conflicts; defense mechanisms; current and historical symptoms, including childhood illnesses, illnesses secondary to syndromes, factors predisposing the patient to illness, factors precipitating illness, factors perpetuating illness, and factors protecting the individual from illness; and how symptoms have responded or are responding to treatment. When phenomenological variations are influenced by factors such as the patient’s gender or age, these can help determine whether a behavior reflects psychopathology. Diagnostic, therapeutic, and prognostic implications of the evaluation’s findings may also be discussed."
 },
 {
  "id": 288,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify a number of different methods for conducting work-related performance appraisals.",
  "answer": "In the critical incident method, a manager records an employee’s positive and negative performance behaviors throughout a selected time period, while the employee is working. In the weighted checklist method, raters familiar with the job duties being evaluated make a comprehensive list of statements describing effective and ineffective work behaviors, and managers then score employees on these list items. Paired comparison analysis is a means of prioritizing alternative options: an individual lists a range of plausible options and compares each against the others, and then tallies the results. The preferable option is the one with the highest score. Graphic rating scales are the oldest and most widely used performance appraisal method. The rating scale is a form showing performance levels, and the manager places checkmarks next to the levels that apply to the employee’s performance. In the essay evaluation method, managers write qualitative descriptions of employee strengths and weaknesses. Because it is not quantitative, this method is usually combined with graphic rating scales."
 },
 {
  "id": 289,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some reasons for ordering neuropsychological tests during a psychological evaluation. Discuss how neuropsychological testing can help professionals make differential diagnoses.",
  "answer": "Ordering neuropsychological testing ultimately involves clinical judgment. Some situations in which neuropsychological tests might be ordered include when cognitive deficits are suspected in a patient, when the severity of a disorder or symptoms must be defined, when functioning deteriorates, or when symptoms progress over time. In the latter two situations, professionals conduct neuropsychological testing to measure these processes. Neuropsychological measurements can also aid differential diagnoses of cognitive disorders versus factitious disorders or malingering (faking symptoms). When older adults present with new onset of mood disorders or psychotic symptoms together with cognitive deficits, neuropsychological testing can differentially diagnose between age-related dementia and other psychiatric disorders. Research has identified cognitive deficit patterns that are typical of schizophrenia, Alzheimer’s disease, bipolar disorder, major depressive disorder, and autism spectrum disorders. Research has also found that some cognitive deficits and their resulting impaired social and occupational function can persist, even when other major symptoms have been treated effectively. For example, positive and negative symptoms of schizophrenia can respond to treatment, but impairment in working memory may persist. Depressive symptoms can be relieved by treatment, but executive function may remain impaired."
 },
 {
  "id": 290,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify a number of methods of collecting information for job analysis in the workplace.",
  "answer": "Direct observation is a way to observe and record behaviors, activities, events, tasks, and duties as they occur. Job analysts can use the interview method with applicants, employees, and supervisors individually or in groups. This method may involve using structured interviews, unstructured interviews, and open-ended questions. Job analysts can combine all methods to collect information. For example, direct observation should always be accompanied by interviewing. Repetitive and manual production jobs like assembly line or factory work are analyzed by work methods analysis, which may include time and motion studies and micro-motion analysis. The critical incident technique of job analysis classifies work behavior as good or poor performance. A task inventory lists the separate activities that constitute a specific job in a specific workplace. The job element method is like the critical incident technique, but focuses less on abstract characteristics and more on work behaviors and their results."
 },
 {
  "id": 291,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify a number of different methods for conducting work-related performance appraisals. (continued)",
  "answer": "In addition to critical incident, weighted checklist, paired comparison analysis, graphic rating scales, and essay evaluation performance appraisal methods, there are behaviorally anchored rating scales, which are performance ratings that focus on specific behaviors or sets of behaviors as indices of effective or ineffective performance. They combine the critical incident and rating scale methods. The performance ranking method compares an employee to another employee instead of to a standardized measurement or norm. In this method, employee performance is ranked from best to worst. In the management by objectives (MBO) method, managers and\/or employees establish employee objectives. Managers periodically evaluate employee performance relative to these objectives, and reward employees according to the results. This method focuses on goals rather than methods of attaining them. In the 360-degree performance appraisal, employees get confidential, anonymous feedback from other employees. In forced ranking\/distribution, employees are ranked according to a predetermined distribution, such as the top 10 percent, the middle 80 percent, and the bottom 10 percent. Behavioral observation scales rate the frequency of an employee’s critical incidents."
 },
 {
  "id": 292,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify and describe six questionnaire methods for conducting job analysis in the workplace.",
  "answer": "The Position Analysis Questionnaire is a structured instrument that measures 195 job elements describing general human work behaviors.\n\nThe Functional Job Analysis Model from the U.S. Department of Labor’s Employee and Training Administration includes three worker-function scales; one worker-instruction scale; three scales measuring reading, mathematics, and language; and a measurement of the percentage of time spent with data, people, and things. The Work Profiling System is a computer-administered job analysis questionnaire. The MOSAIC (Multipurpose Occupational Systems Analysis Inventory--Closed-Ended) questionnaire gathers information from applicants and supervisors. There are 151 job tasks for effective job performance that are rated by importance, 22 competencies rated by importance, and items related to required entry-level proficiency. The Common Metric Questionnaire is a “workeroriented” instrument that applies to a wide range of jobs. It has 41 general background questions, 62 people contacts questions, 80 decision-making items, 53 physical and mechanical activity items, and 47 work setting items. The Fleishman Job Analysis System includes 52 necessary physical, sensory, psychomotor, and cognitive capabilities (including operational and differential definitions), as well as a grading scale."
 },
 {
  "id": 293,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify a number of methods of collecting information for job analysis in the workplace. (continued)",
  "answer": "In addition to direct observation, interviews, work methods analysis, the critical incident technique, the task inventory, and the job element method, another method of collecting information for job analysis is the diary method. It asks workers to keep daily records or lists of their daily job duties. Checklists and rating scales inventory job elements such as the job’s purpose, key areas of responsibility, organization, relationships, decisionmaking, authority, skills, knowledge, experience, and working conditions. Competency modeling involves determining specific competencies associated with success and high performance in a specific job, including abilities, knowledge, skills, values, interests, and personalities.\n\nAnother method involves examining reference manuals\/materials, such as the company’s human resources manual, quality manual, procedures, instructions, forms, job descriptions, etc. Analysts can hold technical conferences with subject matter experts and brainstorm to identify job elements. The Threshold Traits Analysis System (TTAS Model) uses a standardized set of 33 traits. In this analysis, “ability traits” are “can do” factors, and “attitudinal traits” are “willing to do” factors."
 },
 {
  "id": 294,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some principles of job evaluation in the workplace.",
  "answer": "In job evaluation in the workplace, a number of principles apply. First, identifiable, clearly defined jobs must exist, and must be accurately described in agreed-upon job descriptions. Second, all an organization’s jobs are evaluated with an agreed-upon job evaluation plan.\n\nThird, job evaluators must acquire a thorough understanding of any job they evaluate. Fourth, job evaluation does not involve evaluating people, only jobs.\n\nFifth, jobs are evaluated as though they are being performed in completely competent and acceptable ways, without reference to any particular employee(s)’ performance. Sixth, job evaluation is not scientific, as it is based upon people’s judgment. However, when used correctly, job evaluation can enable evaluators to make more objective judgments. Seventh, judgments can be made about the contribution a job makes to the organization, and about the connection of that contribution to other jobs in the organization. Eighth, the true test of the results of a job evaluation is how acceptable they are to all those participating. Ninth, because it highlights task duplication and gaps between functions and jobs, job evaluation can assist in organizational problem-solving."
 },
 {
  "id": 295,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the technique of job evaluation. Identify the two most common job evaluation methods used in workplaces.",
  "answer": "Job evaluation is a technique that can be used by trained, experienced staff to judge the sizes of specific jobs related to those of other jobs in the same organization. It allows staff members to rank jobs internally. It is not used directly to decide wage grades, but when job evaluations are made of all hourly-pay workers, it can be used to establish relative pay rates for different tasks. It can be used for all positions within a company, including senior management. One common job evaluation method is whole job ranking: each job as a whole is ranked in relation to the others. Another common method involves a points system: various elements required for a job, such as education or experience, are assessed and awarded point values. The higher a job’s requirements are for a given element, the higher the number of points that are assigned to it."
 },
 {
  "id": 296,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Define the steps involved in designing an effective needs assessment.",
  "answer": "To design an effective needs assessment, the first step is to determine its purpose by identifying the objectives for conducting it. The second step is to identify the resources needed for the assessment. This includes determining which resources are currently available; whether the organization or institution provides help with developing and implementing surveys; and whether the assessor has or needs assistance with distributing, collecting, and analyzing the assessment. The third step is to decide who is responsible for designing, implementing, and analyzing the needs assessment. The fourth step is to ascertain which research questions need to be included in the needs assessment. The fifth step is to decide on the methodologies that will be used to distribute, collect, and analyze the needs assessment. The sixth and final step for designing an effective needs assessment is establishing a feasible timeline for accomplishing each step."
 },
 {
  "id": 297,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some purposes, benefits, and orientations of needs assessments. Provide some examples of the kinds of information they can provide.",
  "answer": "Before an organization develops programs or solutions, it must first determine its current status. A needs assessment is a systematic means of determining this. For example, collecting baseline data on the service needs of a target population will save an organization time, money, and human resources. Needs assessments can be reactive or proactive in orientation. For example, if there are declines in profits, production, enrollment, retention, etc. (depending on the type of organization), a reactive needs assessment can identify the cause(s) and\/or possible solutions. In organizations that have not observed problems or negative indices, proactive needs assessment can be used to predict and plan for future needs. Comprehensive needs assessments can provide information such as perceptions of a job’s, organization’s, or industry’s meaning; techniques and resources currently being used effectively, and those not currently being used effectively; professional development needs of employees or members; and additional resources needed by employees or members."
 },
 {
  "id": 298,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify some of the needs of organizational frameworks.",
  "answer": "Organizations acquire information through measurement, but they also need to determine how this information is accrued from one project to the next. Organizations need to know how they develop their core competencies, and how to amass and build upon knowledge that is pertinent to the specified domain. Organizations need to use information to build baseline levels over time for defects, use of resources, etc. They must construct a measurement program that will endure over time and across individual projects. Organizational leaders must recognize and capture what they have learned from implementing individual programs; and they must also learn from one project to the next. In addition, they must save the results obtained through their measurement program for future analyses. This allows them to continue to learn from past achievements and mistakes, and permits them to compare future practices and results to previous ones."
 },
 {
  "id": 299,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify the purpose of functional behavior analysis\/assessment. Describe some steps involved in conducting a functional behavior analysis\/assessment.",
  "answer": "The purpose of functional behavior analysis\/assessment (FBA) is to determine a particular behavior’s function or purpose. The underlying behavioral principle is that all behavior has a function. People engage in behaviors to get something or to get away from something. It is much easier to modify a behavior when we know what function it serves. For example, if an individual exhibits a maladaptive, unacceptable behavior to get attention, consequences can be manipulated so attention is not given in response to these behaviors, eliminating reinforcement (which will lead to extinction). A more adaptive, acceptable behavior can be taught by rewarding it with attention. The first step in conducting a functional behavior analysis\/assessment is to define the behavior operationally, broadly (physical aggression, for instance), and specifically (hitting, kicking, and\/or shoving, for example) through observations and interviews. Identifying when, where, with whom, in what situations, and under what conditions the behavior occurs (including precipitating antecedents and perpetuating consequences) will uncover the behavior’s purpose and function. It might be attention, control, escape, communication when other means are deficient, etc. Baseline data are collected on instances, frequency, duration, and conditions of the behavior before planning or implementing interventions."
 },
 {
  "id": 300,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Describe the DSM.",
  "answer": "The Diagnostic and Statistical Manual (DSM) of Mental Disorders is the APA’s standard for diagnosing mental illnesses, intellectual disability, personality disorders, anxiety disorders, depressive disorders, adjustment disorders, and other related disorders. The current version is the DSM-5. Starting with the DSM-IV-TR, the DSM has used codes that are compatible with the ICD (International Classification of Diseases). The ICD-10 is the manual used by medical professionals to diagnose medical diseases, health problems, injuries, and causes of death. The DSM provides a common language and standard criteria for the classification of mental disorders. It is also a classification system with periodic revisions. It includes comprehensive descriptions of the symptoms and manifestations of mental disorders and associated information such as prevalence. It does not discuss causation (etiology). The DSM offers specific criteria for clinicians to diagnose disorders.\n\nThe DSM also takes cultural context, cultural belief systems, and cultural differences between client\/worker into account and includes Culture-Bound Syndromes. The DSM also presents a Defensive Functioning Scale, which assesses the client’s defenses or coping patterns at time of the evaluation and just preceding it."
 },
 {
  "id": 301,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "Identify several steps in creating a project quality improvement paradigm for organizational frameworks.",
  "answer": "There are several steps in creating a quality improvement paradigm for organizational frameworks. The first is to describe or characterize a current project and its environment relative to models and metrics. The second is to set measurable goals for successful project performance and performance improvement. The third is to select an appropriate process model for the project, as well as methods and tools to support the selected process. The fourth is to execute the chosen process, construct the designated products, collect data, validate the data, and analyze the data to enable feedback in real time regarding corrective action. The fifth is to analyze the data to evaluate current practices, identify problems, document findings, and generate recommendations for project improvement in the future. The sixth is to “package” the entire experience gleaned from the current project and previous ones in the form of structured knowledge. Specifically, this “package” is in the form of refined, updated models. This information is then stored in an “experience base” that can be accessed to inform future projects."
 },
 {
  "id": 302,
  "topic": "Assessment and Diagnosis",
  "question": "List the major DSM-5 classifications.",
  "answer": "DSM-5 Major Classifications: Neurodevelopmental disorders, Schizophrenia spectrum and other psychotic disorders, Bipolar and related disorders, Depressive disorders, Anxiety disorders Obsessive-compulsive and related disorders, Trauma- and stressor-related disorders, Dissociative disorders, Somatic symptom and related disorders, Feeding and eating Disorders, Elimination disorders, Sleep-wake disorders, Sexual dysfunctions, Gender dysphoria, Disruptive, impulse-control, and conduct disorders, Substance-related and addictive disorders, Neurocognitive disorders, Personality disorders, Paraphilic disorders, Other mental disorders, Medication-induced movement disorders."
 },
 {
  "id": 303,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Cite some recent statistics regarding the prevalence of co-existing mental illness and substance abuse, and include a discussion of prevalence by employment status.",
  "answer": "According to the 2004 (reported in 2006) National Survey on Drug Use and Health (NSDUH, formerly the National Household Survey on Drug Abuse\/NHSDA), 4.6 million adults had dual diagnoses of substance abuse and mental disorders and\/or serious psychological distress. Within this group, six percent received treatment for both substance abuse and mental health problems.\n\nFive percent received treatment for substance abuse only. An estimated 41.4 percent received treatment for mental health problems only, and 47.5 percent received no treatment at all. Of full-time employed adults between the ages of 18 and 64, 10.6 percent had exhibited the symptoms of a substance abuse disorder within the past year, 10.2 percent had serious psychological distress within the past year, and 2.4 percent had both. Roughly 13.2 percent of males in this group versus 6.9 percent of females had experienced substance abuse problems over the past year. Roughly 14.2 percent of females versus 7.3 percent of males had problems with serious psychological distress over the past year.\n\nAmong 2.9 million full-time employed adults between the ages of 18 and 64 with dual diagnoses of substance abuse and serious psychological distress, almost 60 percent received no treatment, and less than 5 percent received treatment for both diagnoses."
 },
 {
  "id": 304,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize some research and development work on a vaccine against cocaine addiction.",
  "answer": "Some scientists are beginning to approach substance abuse and addictions as processes analogous to viral diseases in the sense that they believe they can be prevented rather than merely treated after a problem has developed. This reasoning has led them to begin working on vaccines to address these issues. A vaccine for cocaine addiction is presently being tested in clinical trials. It caused strong immune responses in some cocaine users, and these individuals subsequently gave high proportions of urine samples that were free of cocaine. However, this experimental vaccine produced these results in only one-third of participants. Researchers suspect that genetic influences may be involved, and are investigating this further. Another separate research team combined a chemical similar to cocaine with the parts of a cold virus that stimulate immune response, and created a vaccine that produced long-term drug immunity in mice. Clinical trials to test this vaccine are expected to begin in a few years."
 },
 {
  "id": 305,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe some preliminary research into immunological treatments for drug abuse.",
  "answer": "Normally, drugs of abuse pass the blood-brain barrier and excite the brain’s reward circuits, making them addictive to users. Until now, drugs such as methadone, behavioral therapy, and quitting “cold turkey” have been among the few available treatment methods. However, some scientists now regard addictive substances as introduced toxins, and thus seek to treat them like the flu—immunologically, with vaccines. Related experiments have involved combining an immune-stimulating foreign protein with an addictive substance, and then using this combination to make a vaccine. Vaccination makes the patient’s immune system respond by producing antibodies, which eliminate most of the substance from the system before it reaches the brain. This process can also stimulate immune memory: the body recognizes future drug doses, even without the added protein, and mounts the same immune response, diluting the user’s high. Scientists have found that users do not compensate by increasing drug dosage, but instead decrease their use or quit altogether. Vaccines could become available in 15 to 20 years."
 },
 {
  "id": 306,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize recent phencyclidine (PCP) use trends, abuse symptoms, and research into developing a treatment versus prevention.",
  "answer": "The recreational use of phencyclidine (PCP), popularly known as “angel dust,” has recently increased. Those who use this drug chronically develop symptoms that mimic the symptoms of schizophrenia, a very serious mental illness characterized by hallucinations, delusions, paranoia, disorganized thinking and behavior, and loss of cognitive and adaptive skills, among other things. PCP toxicity can be extremely dangerous. Scientists have recently been working on developing vaccines to prevent abuse of and addiction to various substances. By combining immune-responsestimulating carrier proteins with addictive substances, vaccines can cause users’ immune systems to generate antibodies against the substances. Such a vaccine for PCP is in the very early stages of development. However, before continuing work on a vaccine, researchers may want to develop a treatment for PCP overdose first because overdoses of this particular drug are so dangerous."
 },
 {
  "id": 307,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Identify the status of research and development of vaccines to prevent nicotine addiction.",
  "answer": "Through first-hand experience or observations of others, most of us are familiar with how difficult it is for most users to quit using tobacco, even if they are motivated to quit. Currently, some scientists are looking at substance abuse in a different way. While the disease model of addiction has existed since AA was founded, treatment has been mostly behavioral and\/or has involved the use of effect-blocking drugs like methadone or naltrexone. Now, some researchers are working to develop preventive vaccines comparable to those used to prevent polio, influenza, or pneumonia. Vaccines work by stimulating the immune system to produce antibodies to a pathogen. Current research aims to develop vaccines that produce immune responses against addictive substances. Clinical tests of three different nicotine vaccines are ongoing; one is expected to be available within the next few years. One researcher admitted that this vaccine needs to be improved to have the desired level of effectiveness. However, he also predicts it will serve as a good model for immunization against other abused substances."
 },
 {
  "id": 308,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the history of research and development regarding a vaccine against heroin addiction, the pros and cons of methadone treatment, and potential advantages of immunization over treatment.",
  "answer": "Researchers first began research and development for a vaccine against heroin’s addictive effects in the 1970s. However, when the drugs methadone and buprenorphine were found to block brain receptors responsible for heroin’s stimulation of the brain’s pleasure centers and reward circuits, they came into widespread use. Methadone and buprenorphine both rapidly relieve heroin overdoses, and they prevent withdrawal symptoms by imitating heroin and occupying the same neuroreceptors. However, patients remain dependent on these drugs of treatment. They help many heroin addicts live normal lives, but addicts must still make frequent trips to clinics for injections. A psychiatrist researching and developing vaccines against addictive drugs found that preventing heroin addiction from developing in the first place would be preferable to methadone clinic treatments. A vaccine could prevent heroin use for several months or longer. This would give addicts more freedom, and could possibly allow them to completely quit using heroin for good."
 },
 {
  "id": 309,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Identify a current application of passive immunization, and describe a method for implementing it. Identify its approval status as a treatment for substance abuse. Identify the status of research and development toward a vaccine against the addictive effects of methamphetamine.",
  "answer": "Passive immunization differs from vaccination in that it produces only short-term rather than lasting immunity. Currently, it is used to temporarily stimulate patients’ immune systems to treat cancers such as lymphoma. One method of passive immunization is combining the pathogen with a carrier protein, and then injecting an animal with this combination. The antibodies produced in the animal are then extracted and injected into human patients to combat the disease. It’s expected this same process could be used with substances of abuse, not just disease-causing organisms. Development of a vaccine against methamphetamine, which would be administered directly to addicts without the animal intermediary, is in its infancy. Scientists have not yet even reached an agreement about which carrier protein to try. Meanwhile, they are investigating passive immunization, which could ameliorate overdose effects, but would not confer ongoing protection. Passive immunization is currently approved for treating cancer, but not addictions to commonly abused substances."
 },
 {
  "id": 310,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe some techniques involving games and puzzles that are used in cognitive remediation therapy (CRT) for eating disorders. Identify how they modify disorder symptoms and two reasons they are effective.",
  "answer": "CRT, originally developed for treating schizophrenia, has been adapted to treat eating disorders. Both disorders are characterized by cognitive inflexibility, and CRT is designed to develop cognitive flexibility. In the map game, patients find one route between two places on a map, then another, then a third one, and so on. Through completing this task, they realize there are multiple approaches to problem solving. In the letter game, patients start reading all words in a list starting with F. Halfway through, they start reading all words starting with P. This exercises flexible thinking. In the summary game, patients read a letter or short story, and then summarize it in a single sentence. They learn to stop obsessing over details and grasp the “big picture,” which alters their perspective. In the visual illusion game, patients examine illusions or deceptive images, such as the dual images of young and old women in the Thematic Apperception Test. Patients practice perspective-taking, learning to see others’ points of view, including loved ones’ perceptions of their illness. These techniques work because they are simple, and because they do not focus on food and\/or emotions."
 },
 {
  "id": 311,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Identify a new treatment for schizophrenia that a psychologist has adapted into a treatment for anorexia nervosa. Identify cognitive symptoms shared by these two disorders. Explain how this therapy is implemented and how it works.",
  "answer": "Cognitive remediation therapy (CRT), a new treatment for schizophrenia, takes advantage of neural plasticity. Neural plasticity refers to the fact that our brains can establish new synapses and pathways, and thus can be retrained to respond differently. Schizophrenics tend to become fixated on minute, trivial details, and often harbor delusions. Those with the eating disorder anorexia nervosa have distorted body images (seeing their normal or thin bodies as fat), starve themselves, obsess over diet and food, exercise compulsively, and rigidly follow unusual routines and rituals. Anorexics display the same cognitive inflexibility as schizophrenics. Both are incapable of changing or widening their perspective. CRT trains people to change their thinking by practicing tasks that develop the ability to shift perspective, or even broaden it. These are often low-stress tasks, such as taking a different route to work.\n\nCRT is considered an add-on to therapy and dietary management. No single treatment can effectively treat all eating disorders. However, preliminary research suggests CRT significantly enhances patients’ capacities to change their behaviors, and initiates the recovery process in a non-threatening manner."
 },
 {
  "id": 312,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize some aspects of the behavioral theory approach to psychotherapeutic treatment.",
  "answer": "Behaviorism does not address internal states since they are not observable, but works to change outward behaviors. Desired changes in behavior lead to changes for the better in how the patient feels. In the structured approach of behaviorism, the therapist first obtains information from the client through interviews, and by asking the client to keep records. The therapist can observe from the client’s responses and records what the client is doing that perpetuates the presenting problem(s). The therapist and client then work together to select some behaviors or activities the client can engage in that will result in positive reinforcement. Therapists will often develop a schedule of activities that the client will engage in during the week. If a client lacks the confidence and\/or social skills for social activities, the therapist can help by conducting role playing exercises to practice things like starting conversations, making friends, etc. Behavioral contracts involve committing to specified behaviors or activities. Something rewarding to the client is provided as reinforcement if the client displays the behaviors or participates in the activities he or she committed to in the contract."
 },
 {
  "id": 313,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Comment on some general issues related to addiction treatment, including matching treatment to the individual’s occupational, financial, and mental health status.",
  "answer": "In the USA, over 25 million people have addictions, but only 10 percent seek treatment annually. Many are not motivated to recover. Others are, but do not know where to look. Many fear stigmatization or insurance issues.\n\nAdditionally, information regarding the probabilities of treatment success is contradictory and confusing. Experts note this does not happen with a broken leg. Hospitals efficiently triage physical problems, and experts state addiction treatment should be more like this. Specific medications, cognitive behavioral therapy, behavioral contingency management, motivational interviewing, social support, exercise, and meditation are all effective techniques. The addiction treatment industry, however, is not well-managed or organized.\n\nMoreover, legislation for parity in addiction and mental health treatment progresses slowly. Addiction researchers advocate incorporating addiction treatment into medical care, with increased standardization to reflect increased resources. They are testing a criteria system to guide addicts to appropriate treatments. For example, someone working full-time with a limited budget should not consider residential facilities, providers without serious mental health services admitting addicts on medications for schizophrenia should be avoided, and so on."
 },
 {
  "id": 314,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the basic principle of cognitive psychotherapy. Name some common cognitive errors this approach identifies, and define and give an example of personalization.",
  "answer": "Cognitive therapy is based on the basic principle that our thoughts cause our feelings. According to this approach, psychological disorders are caused by incorrect thinking and beliefs. Therefore, correcting these faulty ideas improves the individual’s perception of events, and hence his or her emotional state. Psychological research into depression in particular has found that people with depressed moods often have inaccurate beliefs about themselves, their circumstances, and the world in general. Common cognitive errors include personalization, dichotomous thinking, selective abstraction, and magnification-minimization. Personalization is taking negative events personally without having an objective reason to do so. The following scenario is an example of personalization. Gina passes the boss in the hall at work and says hello, but the boss does not return her greeting. Gina construes this as meaning the boss dislikes her, and feels hurt, rejected, and discouraged.\n\nHowever, the boss might have been preoccupied with things unrelated to Gina, such as a major work problem or personal issue. By considering that the boss’s behavior might have nothing to do with her, Gina could avoid her own negative feelings."
 },
 {
  "id": 315,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Give examples of some behavioral techniques used to treat diagnosed psychological conditions.",
  "answer": "The following is an example of behavioral therapy. Lee has been diagnosed with depression. The therapist has him self-monitor for a week by keeping a daily activity log. This log shows he goes to work in the morning, comes home in the evening, and watches TV until bedtime, allowing no time for social interactions. The therapist helps Lee identify activities he is willing to do that afford positive social experiences. They agree he will join a bowling team and eat dinner out with a friend weekly. The therapist discovers that Lee is shy and does not know how to initiate conversations with strangers. Through role playing, Lee practices these skills with the therapist. Common techniques used in behavioral therapy are behavioral contracts and reinforcement. Continuing with the scenario above, if Lee wants to buy a new MP3 player, he and the therapist might agree to a contract. This contract could state that when Lee reduces his televisionwatching to three hours daily and engages in three new activities, he can reward himself by buying the player."
 },
 {
  "id": 316,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the basic principle of cognitive psychotherapy. Name some common cognitive errors this approach identifies, and define and give an example of selective abstraction.",
  "answer": "According to cognitive theory, unhappy feelings are caused by inaccurate thinking. Faulty beliefs that we entertain about ourselves, others, situations, and life lead us to feel badly. Changing our thoughts so they are more realistic can therefore make us feel better. Common errors in thinking identified in cognitive theory include personalization, dichotomous thinking, selective abstraction, and magnification-minimization. Selective abstraction is thinking only about selected aspects of a situation, typically the most negative ones. The following scenario is an example of selective abstraction. Karen presents a proposal at work for solving a particular workplace problem. All meeting members are very interested in her solution, and many praise a number of her ideas. Her supervisor mentions only one negative point: that her budget for the solution seems extremely insufficient. Karen construes this single comment as her supervisor’s lack of support, and believes the supervisor intended to embarrass her in front of the group. She forgets all the positive feedback and obsesses over the single negative response."
 },
 {
  "id": 317,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the basic principle of cognitive psychotherapy. Name some common cognitive errors this approach identifies, and define and give an example of dichotomous thinking.",
  "answer": "Cognitive therapy maintains that feelings result from thinking, and that much of our thinking is inaccurate. Oftentimes, if our false beliefs are corrected, our feelings improve. Cognitive psychotherapeutic theory identifies some common cognitive mistakes, including personalization, dichotomous thinking, selective abstraction, and magnificationminimization. Dichotomous thinking results when someone has a black-and-white\/all-or-nothing viewpoint. People demonstrate this when they are only able to identify two choices in a given situation. The following scenario is an example of dichotomous thinking. Guy feels that one particular supervisor at work is treating him unfairly. He sees the only alternatives for resolving this situation as “telling off” this supervisor or quitting. Since the first option could result in Guy being fired, either of these choices could result in unemployment. Guy has failed to realize the existence of many other options, such as approaching the supervisor with a constructive attitude to discuss the situation, asking a superior supervisor for guidance or advice, speaking to the employee relations department, etc."
 },
 {
  "id": 318,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the history of Dr. Aaron T. Beck’s development of cognitive behavioral therapy.",
  "answer": "As a psychotherapist, Aaron Beck observed that his patients often seemed to have “internal dialogues” taking place in their minds, as if they were silently talking to themselves. (This parallels Vygotsky’s concept of inner speech.) They reported very little of this thinking to him. For example, a patient might think, “The doctor isn’t saying much today. Maybe he’s mad at me.” This could engender feelings of anxiety or anger. If the patient then thought, “Maybe I’m avoiding my main problems by talking about more trivial things,” or, “Maybe he’s just tired today,” these thoughts could change the patient’s feelings. Beck realized that thoughts and feelings are significantly connected. He coined the term “automatic thoughts” to describe thoughts laden with emotions that pop into people’s minds. People are often unaware of these thoughts, but they can learn to recognize and report them. Beck found that identifying negative, unrealistic, unhelpful thoughts enabled people to understand and overcome their problems."
 },
 {
  "id": 319,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the basic principle of cognitive psychotherapy. Name some common cognitive errors this approach identifies, and define and give an example of magnification-minimization.",
  "answer": "Cognitive theory holds that faulty beliefs and thinking are the sources of negative affective states, and hence mental disorders. Cognitive therapy replaces inaccurate or unrealistic thoughts with more appropriate ones to improve corresponding emotions and moods. Common cognitive errors include personalization, dichotomous thinking, selective abstraction, and magnification-minimization. Magnification-minimization involves having a distorted view of the importance of particular events that take place in one’s life. Depressed individuals magnify negative events so that they are disproportionate to their true influences on a situation, and minimize positive events so they seem less influential than they really are. The following scenario is an example of magnification-minimization. Ken is a pre-med college student who usually gets straight A’s. He knows his GPA will be considered for admission to medical school. He receives a D in one American civilization class. He despairs that he will never achieve his dream of being a doctor. He has magnified one low grade in a course not essential to his major into the destruction of his entire future. At the same time, he has minimized the importance of the straight A’s he got in all other courses."
 },
 {
  "id": 320,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Explain how cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) identifies the source of negative thoughts and addresses them, and provide an example.",
  "answer": "Dr. Aaron Beck, the originator of CBT, suggested that negative thought patterns begin in childhood, and then become automatic and somewhat fixed. The following is an example of the development of negative thought patterns. A child received few demonstrations of affection from his parents, but they praised him for schoolwork. He came to think, “I must always perform well; otherwise, people will reject me.” Beck called this type of thought a “dysfunctional assumption.” As a life rule, this assumption might work most of the time and motivate the person to work hard. However, encountering failure due to forces outside the person’s control activates the dysfunctional assumption, and it can become automatic. The person might think, “I failed; nobody will like me; I can’t face them.” CBT helps the client understand this process, detach from the automatic thoughts, and test them. The therapist invites the client to consider what happened to him or her and others in similar real-life situations, affording a more realistic perspective. The client can then test others’ opinions by asking friends what they think. Their responses will almost certainly contradict the client’s exaggerated beliefs about rejection."
 },
 {
  "id": 321,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Define some basic characteristics of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT).",
  "answer": "Originally developed by Dr. Aaron T. Beck, CBT combines principles of cognitive therapy (the theory that our thoughts determine our emotions, and that correcting inaccurate or unrealistic thoughts causing our negative emotions can improve affect) and behavioral therapy (the theory that internal affect can be improved by changing external behaviors through changing their antecedents and consequences). CBT is a structured, short-term approach that is goal oriented, practical, and espouses hands-on problem solving. It aims to change patterns of both thinking and behavior thought to be responsible for psychological problems. The treatment duration of CBT for most emotional difficulties is four to seven months of weekly 50-minute sessions. The therapist and client collaborate to find more effective strategies for coping with problems. Because the client learns a set of principles through CBT that he or she can then apply to future situations throughout life, the results can last indefinitely even though the therapy is brief."
 },
 {
  "id": 322,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Discuss the application of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) to groups vs. individuals, and outline some advantages of using it in group situations.",
  "answer": "CBT is often used in individual counseling sessions. However, it is also effective for family therapy and group therapy, particularly in their earlier stages. Although it is normal for many clients to feel intimidated about sharing personal problems with groups, especially strangers, most find the results of group therapy beneficial if and when they can surmount this trepidation. They can discuss various problems with other people who share similar experiences and understand how they feel. They receive valuable advice and support from peers rather than just from the therapist. Another advantage of using CBT in therapy groups is that service providers are able to meet with more than one client at a time. If there are 10 people in a therapy group, then help is offered to 10 times as many people than in an individual session. Ultimately, more people can get help sooner."
 },
 {
  "id": 323,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe how cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) differs from some other forms of psychotherapy in that it is more structured, and outline the main reasons for this.",
  "answer": "Unlike psychoanalytic and psychodynamic therapies, wherein the patient is encouraged to free-associate (speak freely about whatever comes to mind), CBT is structured. The client and therapist first meet to identify specific problems the client is experiencing, and to set goals they will try to achieve through therapy. Based on these problems and goals, they jointly plan session content. They begin each session by deciding which main topics they will address that week, reviewing and discussing the conclusions made during the previous session, and reviewing the progress the client made with the homework he or she self-assigned during the previous session. At the end of the session, they plan another homework assignment. The structure of CBT maximizes the efficiency of the short therapy course. It prevents the client and therapist from overlooking important information, such as homework results. It also helps the client and therapist consider new assignments that naturally proceed from each new session. CBT therapists actively structure early therapy.\n\nAs clients learn helpful principles and make progress, they take increasing responsibility for session content. By the end of therapy, they feel empowered to continue independently."
 },
 {
  "id": 324,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Identify some characteristics of individuals who would not benefit from cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT), and those of people who would benefit from it. Name a number of problems for which CBT has been found effective.",
  "answer": "People who feel vaguely unhappy or dissatisfied, but have no specific symptoms and cannot identify any specific problems in their lives that they would like to solve would not benefit from CBT since it focuses on solving specific problems and setting and meeting specific therapeutic goals. People who agree with CBT’s ideas and prefer practical solutions, rather than making their first priority the attainment of deep insights, would benefit from CBT. CBT has been found effective for a wide range of problems, including: anxiety; panic attacks; anger management; issues of childhood and adolescence; chronic fatigue syndrome; chronic pain; depression; drug, alcohol, and substance abuse; eating disorders; general health problems; facial tics; habits; mood swings; obsessive-compulsive disorder; phobias; post-traumatic stress disorder; relationship problems; sexual problems; and sleep problems. A new, quickly burgeoning trend in psychotherapy is combining medications with CBT to treat hallucinations and delusions caused by schizophrenia, cocaine toxicity, some cases of bipolar disorder, long-term difficulties with social interactions, and other disorders and issues."
 },
 {
  "id": 325,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Contrast the client-therapist relationship in cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) with the one that develops when other psychotherapeutic approaches are used.",
  "answer": "In some psychotherapies, the client develops a dependence on the therapist, which is encouraged to facilitate the treatment process. For example, in psychodynamic therapies, the client may come to regard the therapist as a parent substitute, which is important to the psychodynamic process of transference that allows the client to work out unresolved child-parent issues. The client may view the therapist as an omniscient, omnipotent authority for a time. Other therapies require the therapist to be very didactic and directive with the client. In CBT, the client-therapist relationship differs in that the relationship is much more equal. Some also consider it more businesslike in that it is practical and focused on problems and solutions. CBT founder Aaron Beck coined the term “collaborative empiricism” to describe how the client and therapist work together with real-life evidence to test how CBT’s principles apply to the client’s individual problems and circumstances."
 },
 {
  "id": 326,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Name a few neo-Freudian therapy theorists. Identify some differences between Freud’s and neo-Freudian theorist’s psychodynamic therapy models.",
  "answer": "Some of the most prominent neo-Freudians included Carl Jung, Alfred Adler, Karen Horney, and Anna Freud. Their theories maintained Freud’s focus on motivation. However, their treatments were shorter. For instance, they might conduct weekly sessions for several months rather than conducting sessions several times a week for several years as Freud did. Neo-Freudian psychodynamic therapies tend to focus more on conscious motivations than unconscious ones, which eliminates much time spent delving into repressed memories and unconscious conflicts. They place more emphasis on the importance of the ego or self instead of on the id. They are also concerned with the influences of life experiences beyond childhood and adolescence, whereas Freud mainly focused on early childhood influences. While Freud concentrated on sexual and aggressive drives as the fuel for motivation, neo-Freudian psychodynamic therapists place more importance on the roles of social needs and interpersonal relationships. Freudian psychoanalysts would probe early childhood memories, seeking clues about a patient’s depression. Neo-Freudian psychodynamic therapists, on the other hand, would more likely examine current relationships for clues, attributing depression more to social than sexual sources."
 },
 {
  "id": 327,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Give a general summary of some of the principles and methods of a psychodynamic model of psychotherapeutic treatment.",
  "answer": "Psychodynamic treatment models are based on Freud’s psychoanalytic theory. One general principle is that the client’s problems originate in unresolved inner childhood conflicts, unconscious motivations, and early child-parent interactions. Another principle is that three personality structures are at work in any individual. The id energizes the personality by generating impulses to act, the ego governs the person’s sense of reality, and the superego provides a conscience or moral sense. An additional principle is that the ego generates defense mechanisms to protect the individual from threatening thoughts, feelings, and impulses. Psychodynamic treatments focus on relating current problems to unresolved conflicts, exploring these, and seeking and finding solutions. Methods include free association, wherein the client speaks freely about whatever comes to mind that is related to the presenting problems. Transference, wherein the patient relates to the therapist as a parental figure, is a key therapeutic process. Therapists typically listen a lot, make notes, ask questions, and analyze the client’s feelings. This is an indepth type of therapy that is neither brief nor time-limited. It can take years, and affords many valuable insights into a client’s motivation and behavior."
 },
 {
  "id": 328,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe Carl Rogers’s client-centered therapy. Include some important qualities identified as necessary by Rogers, a key technique used, and some research findings on therapeutic effectiveness.",
  "answer": "Carl Rogers developed a humanistic type of therapy he called clientcentered or person-centered therapy. Rogers assumed, as humanistic psychologists do, that healthy development and motivations are the norm. He also assumed these developments and motivations could be disrupted by conflicts between a person’s need for a positive self-image and criticisms from oneself and others, which could lead to unhappiness and anxiety. Rogerian therapy aims to create a nurturing environment wherein clients can work through their individual issues to attain feelings of self-respect, and to self-actualize (realize their complete potential). Rogers identified key qualities of empathy, genuineness, and what he termed “unconditional positive regard”–acceptance and respect of the client without judgment–as major contributors to therapeutic success. Providing these qualities in therapy enables clients to clarify feelings impeding personal growth. An important technique is reflective listening, wherein the therapist listens and then mirrors or reflects back the client’s expressed feelings by paraphrasing them. Research by an APA task force found that effective therapies commonly share exactly the qualities Rogers defined: unconditional positive regard, feedback, genuineness, and empathy."
 },
 {
  "id": 329,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize some of the main principles of humanistic therapies in general, and discuss how they differ from psychodynamic therapies.",
  "answer": "While psychodynamic therapies focus on motivations and conflicts among them, humanistic therapies focus on such influences as low self-esteem, misdirected goals, and unsatisfying relationships as the sources of mental disorders or difficulties. Humanistic therapies aim to resolve “existential crises,” which are problems related to the purpose and meaning of existence that produce feelings of alienation, difficulties in and\/or lack of fulfillment in relationships, and overall dissatisfaction with life. A basic tenet of humanistic therapies that sets them apart from psychodynamic approaches is that, generally, people are motivated by healthy needs for psychological well-being, growth, and self-actualization. The idea of the whole person who is continuously changing and growing is emphasized. Negative self-evaluations and criticisms from others can create unhealthy environments that interfere with normal growth and development. Humanistic therapies regard such negative influences as the causes of mental disorders. They seek to help clients realize their own freedom, improve their self-esteem, and realize their full potential."
 },
 {
  "id": 330,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe some characteristics of group therapies and how they relate to individual therapies. Identify some common orientations of group therapies, their applications and benefits, and a few types of group therapy.",
  "answer": "The majority of theoretical orientations used for individual therapy are also used in group therapy. Some therapy programs, especially ones designed to treat addiction in adolescents, for example, primarily stress the importance of the group therapy experience. Individual sessions can also be conducted as needed. Group therapy approaches most often embrace a humanistic theoretical orientation. The second most common approach to group therapy is the psychodynamic orientation. Group therapy is valuable for treating issues related to interpersonal interactions, relationships, and social behaviors.\n\nGroups are beneficial for people sharing the same diagnoses, symptoms, or issues, such as substance abuse, depression, anxiety disorders like obsessive-compulsive disorder, etc. Clients not only find others who have similar experiences in common, but also receive support from fellow members within a non-judgmental environment. Additionally, they can observe, learn, and practice new and improved social skills in this safe atmosphere. Another benefit of group therapy is that more clients receive therapy at one time. Some group therapy types include couples\/marital therapy, family therapy, and self-help groups."
 },
 {
  "id": 331,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Explain how Aaron Beck’s practice of psychotherapy, which originally relied on Freudian psychoanalysis, led him to develop cognitive therapy. Describe how his methods would be used to treat depressive and obsessive-compulsive disorders, and summarize research findings related to the effectiveness of Beck’s approach.",
  "answer": "Aaron Beck originally practiced Freudian psychoanalysis. However, in doing so, he observed that when his patients with depression used the Freudian techniques of free-association and recounting their dreams, they expressed a lot of negative ideas. For example, they might say, “If they really knew me, nobody would like me.” Beck began to think depression resulted from such negative beliefs and “self-talk.” He concluded that the job of the therapist was to help the client identify these negative thinking habits and learn habits of thinking more positive thoughts to replace the self-defeating negative ones. The cognitive therapist works with depressed patients by helping them identify, face, and examine the self-destructive beliefs or thoughts that contribute to and perpetuate their depression. For the obsessive thoughts characteristic of obsessive-compulsive and other disorders, cognitive therapy would help clients focus on challenging the irrationality of their obsessive beliefs and their assumptions that catastrophes will occur without their compulsive actions. Research studies find Beck’s approach to treating depression can be as effective as medication."
 },
 {
  "id": 332,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe some benefits and features of couples\/marital counseling or therapy as a group therapy.",
  "answer": "While individual therapies help clients address individual issues, group therapies are especially useful for clients who need to learn about social relationships and improve their own relationships. Couples’ counseling sometimes involves one couple meeting with a therapist; it can also be a group couples’ therapy, in which several couples participate in a session. In addition to resolving relationship issues, the focus is on clarifying interpersonal communications and improving the quality of interactions. Typically, couples’ therapy does not concentrate on individual personalities, but on the relationship’s processes, especially ones related to conflicts and communicating. Therapists teach couples non-directive listening skills to help them clarify their emotions and thoughts and express them. They help couples identify the ways, both verbal and non-verbal, that each member confuses, controls, or dominates the other. Then, they assist them in withdrawing from conflicts and reinforcing more desired responses in one another."
 },
 {
  "id": 333,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize the development, several benefits, and characteristics of self-help support groups as a type of group therapy.",
  "answer": "The self-help concept was pioneered in the 1930s by Alcoholics Anonymous (AA). AA’s 12 steps to recovery from addiction were based on the experiences of its earliest members. In the 1960s, the feminist movement’s emphasis on raising consciousness expanded the self-help concept to target a broader range of recipients. Since then, interest in self-help support groups has continued to grow. Support groups that are not directed by paid healthcare professionals are often free of charge, and can therefore benefit people with limited financial means. Another benefit is sharing experiences and ideas with others who have similar issues, including those who are coping very well, in a non-threatening atmosphere. In addition to substance abuse, today’s self-help groups address other behavior control issues like overeating, gambling, and sexual addictions. They also help attendees manage life crises or transitions such as divorce or a child’s death; physical disorders such as heart attack, stroke, and diabetes; mental disorders such as depression and anxiety; coping with the stress of having a loved one who is dealing with addiction; and coping with terminal illness."
 },
 {
  "id": 334,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Contrast the approach of behavioral therapies with insight-oriented therapies. Identify some problems that respond well to behavioral therapies.",
  "answer": "Insight-oriented therapies include psychodynamic, humanistic, and cognitive therapies. Behavioral therapies include those based on classical conditioning, operant conditioning, and observational learning. Insightoriented therapies seek to understand inner thoughts, feelings, and motivations. In contrast, behavioral therapies seek only to understand problematic behaviors, not inner states. Behavioral theory holds that maladaptive behaviors are learned, and can therefore be unlearned. More adaptive behaviors can then be learned to replace the maladaptive ones. Behaviorism also maintains that only observable behaviors that can be measured or behaviorally described can be changed. Behavioral therapies have been found to be very effective for treating such problems as bedwetting, shyness, overeating, or antisocial behavior. Behavioral therapists also report successful treatment of such psychological issues as depression, aggression, compulsions, fears, delinquent behaviors, and addictions."
 },
 {
  "id": 335,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Describe some characteristics of family therapy as a group therapy, including its approach, some of its benefits, and the therapist’s roles.",
  "answer": "In family therapy, the family, rather than an individual member, is the client. Each family member is regarded as part of a system of relationships. Family therapists help family members identify the behavior patterns or concerns that are causing problems in the family system. Changing the interpersonal dynamics of family interactions is the goal of family therapy. Its benefits include not only decreasing tensions within the family, but also helping individual family members identify their roles within the group. This allows each member to enhance their individual functioning. Research has found that family therapy is particularly effective in treating the eating disorder anorexia nervosa, depression, and other mood disorders. It even benefits families trying to cope with schizophrenia in a family member. Psychotherapist Virginia Satir, a pioneer in family therapy, remarked that family therapists play the roles of interpreting and clarifying family session interactions, mediating, refereeing, and advising. Rather than blaming one member for problems, therapists show families how they interact and help them solve problems collaboratively and constructively."
 },
 {
  "id": 336,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Explain how Joseph Wolpe developed the method of systematic desensitization, and outline the two main concepts it combines. Summarize the extinction process in systematic desensitization.",
  "answer": "Psychiatrist Joseph Wolpe challenged the Freudian concept of symptom substitution, which predicted that attacking symptoms by changing behaviors without eliminating underlying causes would result in worse symptoms replacing the presenting ones. According to the classical conditioning model, new, previously unrelated (unconditioned) stimuli become conditioned to evoke the same responses as other stimuli through their association. Wolpe theorized that irrational emotional responses like fear could become associated with crowds, insects, lightning, etc. through this process. He also found that the nervous system cannot be simultaneously agitated and relaxed. Wolpe combined these two concepts to form the basis of systematic desensitization, wherein the association of stimuli with undesirable responses is unlearned. The extinction process begins with relaxation training. Patients are then instructed to imagine situations that are progressively more anxiety-provoking. The therapist and patient rank situations in order of severity to develop an “anxiety hierarchy.” Through visualization and\/or direct exposure, clients confront progressively more fearful circumstances, gradually developing desensitization to one at a time until they can confront the most severe anxiety-provoking circumstances without experiencing anxiety."
 },
 {
  "id": 337,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize two highlights in the early history of behavioral therapy based on classical conditioning. Explain the delayed emergence of behaviorism in psychotherapeutic practice.",
  "answer": "In 1924, psychologist Mary Cover Jones documented the first use of behavioral therapy based on classical conditioning. She treated Peter, a little boy presenting with extreme fear of furry things, such as rabbits. She used successive approximations, bringing a rabbit a little closer to Peter during each session over several weeks. He gradually became less fearful until he could pet the rabbit on his lap. Despite Jones’s success with this patient, the use of behavior therapy was not reported again until 1938, when psychologists (Mowrer & Mowrer) used it to treat bedwetting. During this treatment, an alarm triggered by wetness would wake the patient. Whereas psychodynamic therapy discussing the symptom’s meaning failed abysmally, this prototype of the enuresis alarm had a 75 percent success rate. Still, behavior therapy was not accepted in psychotherapy until 20 years later. This was because the Freudian concept of unconscious underlying causes for symptoms was so strong that therapists feared “symptom substitution.” They thought attacking symptoms without eliminating root causes could result in a worse symptom replacing the treated one."
 },
 {
  "id": 338,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Explain how some cognitive behavioral therapists have recently combined computer technology with behavioral therapy to treat phobias and other anxiety disorders through systematic desensitization.",
  "answer": "While cognitive therapy focuses on identifying and changing irrational beliefs and thoughts that cause undesirable emotions, and behavior therapy focuses on identifying and changing undesirable learned behaviors, cognitive behavioral therapy does both. Behaviorism uses systematic desensitization to help individuals unlearn the association of fearful or anxious responses with conditioned stimuli. Behaviorists believe this process of classical conditioning is responsible for specific phobias. They use the same process in systematic desensitization to dissociate those responses from the target stimuli. Recently, some cognitive behavioral therapists have been using the computer technology of virtual reality environments for systematic desensitization. They create virtual environments, which are safe for clients. In these environments, they expose them to their specific feared stimuli, which could be snakes, spiders, small spaces, heights, etc. This virtual exposure can be more visually real than mental imagery for some clients. It is also less threatening than real-life exposure, facilitating desensitization for many."
 },
 {
  "id": 339,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Give an example of an anxiety hierarchy that might be used in systematic desensitization. Identify some psychological disorders that have been found to be especially responsive to systematic desensitization.",
  "answer": "The behavioral technique of systematic desensitization uses classical conditioning to help clients unlearn undesirable conditioned responses to stimuli. For example, if a client has an extreme fear of public speaking, the client and the therapist would construct an anxiety hierarchy.\n\nThe client would list fearful situations relevant to public speaking. The therapist and client would rank the following situations in order, from least anxiety-provoking to most: (1) viewing a picture of someone else making a speech; (2) seeing someone else make a speech; (3) preparing one’s own speech; (4) introducing oneself to a big group; (5) waiting to be called to speak during a meeting; (6) being introduced to a group as a public speaker; (7) walking to a dais, podium, or stage to speak; and (8) actually giving the speech to a big group. The client imagines and\/or actually performs each item until he or she can do it without anxiety before proceeding to the next item, working from the least anxiety-provoking task to the most anxiety-provoking item. This technique has been found particularly helpful when used to address specific phobias and other anxiety-related issues such as agoraphobia, social phobias, stage fright, and sexual performance anxiety."
 },
 {
  "id": 340,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Define the processes of operant conditioning and contingency management. Give an example of changing behavior through contingency management. Identify some settings and populations wherein this technique has worked.",
  "answer": "Operant conditioning is a behavioral process whereby behaviors that are rewarded or reinforced become more frequent, and behaviors that are punished or ignored become less frequent. Contingency management manipulates rewards and punishments to increase or decrease the frequency of targeted behaviors. The following is an example of contingency management. A young child goes grocery shopping with his parents. He asks for candy and they buy it for him, reinforcing his behavior. When they refuse to buy him candy, he throws a screaming temper tantrum. To end his tantrum behavior, which is punishing to them, the parents give in to his demands, further reinforcing his behaviors. If they ignore his demands and tantrums, they may eventually extinguish these behaviors. They can also reward him whenever they observe him behaving well so that he gets attention for this instead of for misbehavior. In contingency management, then, consequences are controlled and contingent upon specific behaviors. This technique has been found effective when used in families, workplaces, schools, psychiatric hospitals, the military, and prisons. It has also been found to decrease self-injurious behaviors in autistic children."
 },
 {
  "id": 341,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Identify the principle underlying aversion therapy, give examples of its practice, and explain why a client would voluntarily submit to this treatment.",
  "answer": "A principle of classical conditioning, a behavioral model, is that when a neutral stimulus is paired with another stimulus and a certain response is elicited, the neutral stimulus becomes conditioned to elicit the same response as the other stimulus through association. This principle underlies both systematic desensitization, wherein the individual learns to extinguish undesirable responses to previously conditioned stimuli, and the converseaversion therapy, wherein clients actually learn to associate unpleasant responses with particular stimuli. This is used with harmful stimuli, such as tobacco, alcohol, other abused drugs and substances, violent behaviors, etc. For example, a smoker might have to chain smoke cigarettes while a noxious odor is blown in his or her face until he or she associates smoking with nausea. The drug Antabuse, which causes nausea upon drinking alcohol, employs the same principle. Non-harmful but unpleasant electric shocks have also been paired with target stimuli in aversion therapy. Other than probation court orders, the most common reason clients voluntarily submit to aversion therapy is for problematic addictions that have proven unresponsive to other treatments."
 },
 {
  "id": 342,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Define the technique of participant modeling, and identify its three theoretical influences. Give an example of this technique. Cite research findings related to its effectiveness compared to that of some other approaches.",
  "answer": "Participant modeling incorporates behavioral principles of classical conditioning, operant conditioning, and the observational learning described by Albert Bandura’s social learning theory. Bandura proved people learn not only from direct experience, but also from observing others’ behaviors and how they are rewarded or punished. People will then behave accordingly based on these observations. People can learn maladaptive responses like fears and phobias through observing and imitating others’ behavior. They can also learn adaptive responses in the same way. Athletic coaches have long used participant modeling. If a client has a phobia of cats (ailurophobia), for example, the therapist could model successive approximations by approaching a cat in a carrier first, then touching the cat, etc. The client would then imitate the therapist’s model at each level until he or she could perform the task without anxiety. Bandura’s research compared participant modeling to systematic desensitization therapy; symbolic modeling, wherein participants were indirectly exposed to fearful stimuli via videos; and a control group with no treatment. Participant modeling was found to be the most effective."
 },
 {
  "id": 343,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Explain how a token economy works, and identify its main principle. Identify some populations wherein token economies can be used.",
  "answer": "The behavioral method of the token economy is a variation of positive reinforcement. The main principle is that reinforcements (rewards) for desired behaviors are received immediately following the display of those desired behaviors. However, unlike simple reinforcement, it involves tokens, which are then exchanged for rewards. This way, participants can accumulate a number of tokens to earn a reward. For the trainer, this facilitates teaching multiple instances, longer durations, and\/or higher frequencies of desired behaviors. It motivates the trainee to engage in more desired behaviors to accrue enough tokens. It also helps trainees identify the desired behavior since it is immediately reinforced with a token. The trainee then associates the eventual reward with that behavior, and with a certain amount of it. When this system is used in schools and with children, tokens are often stickers, gold stars, marks on a chart, points, or play money. Token economies can also be adapted effectively for use with developmentally disabled children, psychiatric patients, and correctional inmates."
 },
 {
  "id": 344,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Briefly describe positive psychotherapy (PPT). Identify its two main influences, discuss an example of a PPT technique, outline additional PPT goals, and discuss some preliminary research findings regarding its effectiveness.",
  "answer": "Psychologist Martin Seligman is the founder of PPT, a newer variation of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT). PPT’s main influences are humanistic psychology and CBT. PPT is humanistic in orientation in that it emphasizes balancing the negative focus on mental disorders typical of psychology with a positive focus on mental health, personal growth, and happiness. However, its methods are mainly cognitive behavioral, and emphasize research. PPT techniques are didactic in the sense that therapists assign clients homework. For example, in the “three good things” exercise, the therapist instructs the client to write down three things that went well that day and why they went well before going to bed. PPT therapists also teach their clients to respond constructively to others, to concentrate on positive emotions, and to pursue pleasure more at home and work. Preliminary findings of Seligman’s research team show PPT more effective in alleviating depression than antidepressant drugs or conventional therapy."
 },
 {
  "id": 345,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Summarize some of the basic principles of Albert Ellis’s RationalEmotive Behavior Therapy (REBT), and include some examples.",
  "answer": "Ellis’s REBT is a variation of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT). CBT proposes our feelings are caused by our thoughts, and that unpleasant emotions are caused by irrational thoughts (cognitive). It also states that maladaptive behaviors are learned, and can therefore be unlearned and\/or replaced by learning more adaptive ones (behavioral). Ellis identified the irrational beliefs of maladjusted people as unattainable goals and unrealistic values. He opined that such people base their lives on goals they cannot achieve and values they cannot realize. Because they are incongruent with reality, Ellis termed these goals and values “neurotic.” Examples of irrational beliefs are: believing that people should always like you, that you should always be successful, that others should always approve of you and your actions, that everybody should always treat you fairly, and\/or that your life experiences should always be pleasant. According to Ellis, telling yourself you “should” exercise daily, get all A’s, etc. is “neurotic self-talk.” He called it “should-ing on yourself.” REBT involves identifying assumptions, questioning their rationality, and replacing faulty beliefs with more realistic ones."
 },
 {
  "id": 346,
  "topic": "Treatment, Intervention, Prevention, and Supervision",
  "question": "Give an example of how neuroimaging technology has been used to document the results of cognitive behavioral therapy (CBT) used to treat mental disorders, and explain what these imaging results prove.",
  "answer": "Newer imaging techniques show increased activity in specific parts of the brain, allowing scientists to see which areas are associated with certain drives, feelings, and thoughts. For example, neuropsychologists conducted a study with patients who had obsessive thoughts typical of obsessive-compulsive disorder, such as constantly worrying after leaving home that they had left the stove turned on or the door unlocked. They were given CBT training to reframe their worries as being obsessions, not rational concerns, and to distract themselves by doing other things for around 15 minutes instead of compulsively rushing home to check on things. During the study, the researchers took positron emission tomography (PET) scans of their brains. They found that the areas of the participants’ brains that showed higher activity levels in connection with their obsessive worries gradually showed less activity over time with CBT training. This proves not only that CBT helps people change their thinking, but also that when people change their thinking it actually changes their brains."
 },
 {
  "id": 347,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Identify the five steps of the scientific method. Give a detailed description of the first step.",
  "answer": "The five steps of the scientific method are: (1) developing a hypothesis; (2) performing a controlled test; (3) gathering objective data; (4) analyzing results and rejecting or confirming the hypothesis; and (5) publishing, criticizing, and replicating the results. Hypothesis literally means “little theory.” It is a statement that is often part of a larger theory, or an idea one wants to investigate. To test a hypothesis, it must be falsifiable, meaning it can be proven right or wrong. To know how to test it, all parts of an experiment must be operationally defined. Operational definitions specify the operations used to conduct the study and measure its results. For example, to test a hypothesis that sugar causes hyperactivity in children, sugar, hyperactivity, and children must be operationally defined. For example, “children” could be defined as all students in one third-grade class, “sugar” could be defined as the 39 grams of sugar in a can of Sprite, and “hyperactivity” could be defined as a significantly higher rating on a 5point activity scale (where 1=passive, 3=moderately active, and 5=very active) compared to students drinking Diet Sprite."
 },
 {
  "id": 348,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Identify the five steps of the scientific method. Give a detailed description of the third step.",
  "answer": "The five steps of the scientific method are: (1) developing a hypothesis; (2) performing a controlled test; (3) gathering objective data; (4) analyzing results and rejecting or confirming the hypothesis; and (5) publishing, criticizing, and replicating the results. In gathering objective data, scientists use direct observation and whichever measurement techniques and tools apply. For example, to test a hypothesis that sugar causes hyperactivity in children, some experimenters used a five-point rating scale to measure children’s activity levels after drinking Sprite with sugar or Diet Sprite. Their independent variable was sugar. They varied this by giving two randomly selected groups of third-graders from the same class either regular Sprite containing sugar or Diet Sprite. They measured the dependent variable, activity level, by rating the children’s amount of activity after drinking the sodas. If experimenters were testing the effects of some variable on people’s attitudes or opinions about a specific topic, they might gather objective data by conducting surveys before and after the experiment and then examining these survey responses."
 },
 {
  "id": 349,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Identify the five steps of the scientific method. Give a detailed description of the second step.",
  "answer": "The five steps of the scientific method are: (1) developing a hypothesis; (2) performing a controlled test; (3) gathering objective data; (4) analyzing results and rejecting or confirming the hypothesis; and (5) publishing, criticizing, and replicating the results. Performing a controlled test of the hypothesis involves conducting an experiment that will confirm the hypothesis or prove it is incorrect. For example, to test the hypothesis that sugar causes hyperactivity in children, the experimental group would consist of students in the experimental condition. They would be given Sprite with sugar. For comparison, the control group would consist of students in the control condition. They would be given Diet Sprite. Randomly selecting and assigning group members prevents the confounding effects of other variables like gender or personality, and avoids systematic biases. Holding all other conditions constant, experimenters manipulate and change one variable independently (the independent variable, which is sugar in this example) to see whether this manipulation affects the dependent variable (activity in this example)."
 },
 {
  "id": 350,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Identify the five steps of the scientific method. Give a detailed description of the fifth step.",
  "answer": "The five steps of the scientific method are: (1) developing a hypothesis; (2) performing a controlled test; (3) gathering objective data; (4) analyzing results and rejecting or confirming the hypothesis; and (5) publishing, criticizing, and replicating the results. When researchers have completed statistical analysis showing that their hypothesis is either true or false by determining whether changing the independent variable(s) did or did not change the dependent variable(s), they report these findings in a presentation at a professional convention and\/or publish them in a professional journal article or book. Criticism of publishing results includes the fact that journal and book editors may require revisions before publication. Criticisms in the scientific community related to published research include questions of whether the experimenters properly selected participants, whether statistical analyses were correctly performed, whether results are attributable to other variables, and whether the same results will be obtained if the experiment is replicated.\n\nFor example, researchers (Wolraich et al, 1994) tested the common belief that sugar makes children hyperactive and found this hypothesis unsupported. Others have replicated this experiment and found it reliable."
 },
 {
  "id": 351,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Identify the five steps of the scientific method. Give a detailed description of the fourth step.",
  "answer": "The five steps of the scientific method are: (1) developing a hypothesis; (2) performing a controlled test; (3) gathering objective data; (4) analyzing results and rejecting or confirming the hypothesis; and (5) publishing, criticizing, and replicating the results. Once objective data have been collected on the results of an experiment, they are often interpreted using statistical analysis. This is a mathematical way of determining whether the results are caused by the independent variable or by chance, especially when the difference is small but statistically significant. Tests like the analysis of variance (ANOVA), analysis of covariance (ANCOVA) when experimenters have more than one discrete dependent variable that cannot be combined, and multivariate analysis of covariance (MANCOVA), etc. yield exact percentages regarding the differences between or among dependent variable(s) that correspond to changes made in the independent variable(s). The test results tell researchers whether to reject or accept their hypothesis. If the variance is statistically significant, the independent variable(s) affected the dependent variable(s) and the hypothesis is true. If the variance is not statistically significant, the hypothesis is false."
 },
 {
  "id": 352,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define the correlation coefficient and explain what it expresses. Define the terms positive correlation, negative correlation, and zero correlation, and discuss examples.",
  "answer": "The correlation coefficient expresses the strength of the relationship between variables. The Pearson product-moment correlation coefficient, or r, measures the strength of their linear relationship as the covariance of the sample’s variables divided by their standard deviations. The Spearman and Kendall tau are rank correlation coefficients showing relationships between different rankings of the same group of data. Correlation means that variables are related, but does not imply that one causes another. Correlation coefficients range from -1.0 to +1.0. The maximum positive correlation is +1.0. Positive correlation means that if one variable increases, so does the other. For example, the correlation between SAT scores and college grades is about +0.4—a moderate positive correlation.\n\nNegative correlation means that as one variable increases, the other decreases.\n\nFor example, alcohol consumption would have a negative correlation with college grades—the more students drink, the lower their grades. Negative correlations can be just as significant as positive ones. Zero correlation means there is no relationship. For example, researchers investigating the connection between height and grade point average would likely conclude there is zero correlation."
 },
 {
  "id": 353,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain the difference between causation and correlation in scientific research. Explain how correlational research addresses situations in which conducting actual experiments is not feasible.",
  "answer": "Scientists commonly express the general principle that “correlation does not necessarily mean causation.” In other words, two variables can be related in that as one increases, so does the other (a positive correlation), or as one increases, the other decreases (a negative or inverse correlation). However, this does not mean one actually causes the other. Correlational research is useful for investigating situations that would be harmful to individuals placed in such situations during an actual experiment. Experiments designed to test whether environmental toxins like lead paint or air pollution cause learning disabilities in children, for instance, cannot be conducted, as exposing children to toxins is both harmful and unethical. Instead, correlational studies can show relationships among variables. These studies don’t have a control group like an experiment does, and they can’t prove causation. Researchers rely on naturally existing, real-world conditions. For instance, they might compare the incidences of learning disabilities in children previously exposed to environmental toxins to those in children who had never been exposed. They would also attempt to control for other factors by matching both groups in terms of age, gender, race, family income, and other factors as much as possible."
 },
 {
  "id": 354,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Describe the research method of naturalistic observation, and provide a few examples of well-known researchers who have used it. Identify some of its major pros and cons.",
  "answer": "Naturalistic observation entails closely, but usually not obviously, observing the behaviors of people and other animals in their natural environments. Scientists often observe unnoticed to keep subjects’ awareness of observation from changing their usual behavior and introducing bias. This method differs from experimentation. While experiments control the research conditions, naturalistic observation does not control conditions, but simply observes and records behaviors under natural conditions. It is useful for studying things like people’s shopping habits, public flirting behavior, or parents’ child-rearing practices. Jane Goodall studied chimpanzees in the wild, and Dian Fossey studied gorillas in the wild using naturalistic observation.\n\nJean Piaget used both naturalistic observation and case study methods to see how young children learn as he formulated his theory of cognitive development.\n\nObservation settings can include a range of locations, such as wildernesses; college campuses; schools; private homes; public places like shopping malls, stores, and restaurants; and others. Disadvantages of this method are lack of control and the inability to prove causation. Advantages of this method are capturing natural behaviors and, with careful advance planning, collecting more accurate data on usual responses without experimental interference."
 },
 {
  "id": 355,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain how and why researchers use the survey method, and outline its main pros and cons.",
  "answer": "Researchers interested in people’s likes and dislikes, attitudes, personality traits, etc. do not have to conduct experiments or correlational studies. Instead, they can use the survey method, which involves collecting people’s responses to questionnaires, rating scales, or checklists. These may be written or oral. A common method is distributing prepared questions or statements to which participants respond. Major advantages of using surveys include that they are easy to give and take, they save time, and they produce large numbers of responses with a relatively small investment of time and energy. Major disadvantages include the fact that respondents do not always answer the items honestly; that the survey instruments may have questions that are not worded clearly enough, and\/or that are inherently biased; and that the sample population that chooses to respond may not be sufficiently representative of the larger population that the surveyors are interested in examining. Surveys have widespread use, and can be used to conduct market research, political polls, and psychological and sociological research."
 },
 {
  "id": 356,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define the term “double-blind study” as it relates to experimental research. Define the term “placebo,” and explain how placebos are used in double-blind studies of drugs. Identify an advantage and a disadvantage of these types of studies.",
  "answer": "When scientists conduct controlled experiments, they manipulate (vary) an independent variable, which in drug studies would be a drug, to see whether it affects a selected dependent variable. The dependent variable in drug studies is usually the illness or condition targeted by the drug. The aim of drug studies is to determine whether the drug being tested relieves, controls, or manages symptoms; cures the illness or condition; or slows or halts its progression, among other things. Drug side effects may also be dependent variables if they are of concern. “Double-blind” means that neither the experimenters nor the participants know whether participants are getting the drug or a placebo (a lookalike, but inactive, fake “drug”). The major advantage of “double-blind” studies is that they prevent bias. Experimenters do not have expectations that influence how they treat participants in experimental versus placebo groups, and participants do not have expectations of treatment effects either. The disadvantage for patients with serious illnesses who participate in clinical trials of new experimental drugs is that they do not know whether they are receiving a new treatment that might work where others did not, or an ineffective placebo."
 },
 {
  "id": 357,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain what a case study is. Identify the types of research that are likely to employ the case study method, and give some examples. Identify major pros and cons of this method.",
  "answer": "A case study is an in-depth examination of a single individual or of a few individuals. As might be inferred from the name, case studies are also conducted by social workers, psychologists, and psychiatrists to give a thorough picture of an individual client, including medical history, family history, diagnoses, personality characteristics, intelligence, presenting problems, etc. When therapists use case studies to formulate theories about mental illnesses, this is sometimes called the clinical method. When examining the unique qualities of a particular individual, one cannot compare groups of people, and the case study applies. Howard Gardner, who formulated the theory of multiple intelligences, wrote a book entitled Creating Minds (1993), wherein he explored the thinking processes of several highly creative persons, including Sigmund Freud, Pablo Picasso, and Albert Einstein using the case study method. Disadvantages of case studies include small sample size, lack of control over variables, lack of objectivity, and lack of generalizability. Advantages include more comprehensive, in-depth profiles, and the ability to obtain valuable, otherwise inaccessible information."
 },
 {
  "id": 358,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain what a cross-sequential research design is and how it works.",
  "answer": "Psychologist Klaus Warner Schaie created the cross-sequential design to combine the advantages of longitudinal and cross-sectional research designs. Longitudinal designs show changes in the same participant sample over a long period of time, typically years. Cross-sectional designs show differences and similarities among individual participants or participant groups at a single point in time. Schaie devised a method of obtaining both kinds of information. In this method, participant groups are selected for separate age cohorts. For example, groups might be made up of five-yearold children, six-year-olds, seven-year-olds, etc.; or of 20-year-old adults, 30-year-olds, 40-year-olds, 50-year-olds, etc. Researchers take measurements of whatever variables they are studying in each age cohort at specified periods (every year, for example). Then, using statistical methods, the different age groups are compared to each other at the same points in time. Changes over time within each age group are identified, and the longitudinal changes within each age group are also compared. Schaie’s methodology is complicated, but his cross-sequential design allows researchers to obtain a wealth of information."
 },
 {
  "id": 359,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define longitudinal research designs and cross-sectional research designs, and explain the difference between them.",
  "answer": "When scientists want to find out what effects a variable might have over an extended period of time, they use a longitudinal research design. For example, some psychotropic drugs have significant side effects, such as tardive dyskinesia’s involuntary motor movements, which do not appear until the patient has taken the medication for a long time, in some cases up to 20 years. Whether a new drug will cause such delayed side effects can only be determined by longitudinal research. Researchers take relevant measurements of the same participants periodically (annually, for example) for years to evaluate changes. In contrast to longitudinal designs, the cross-sectional research design obtains results from different individuals or groups at the same time and compares them. Cross-sectional designs do not show changes over time in the same individuals and groups, but show differences among individuals and groups at one point in time. Longitudinal designs cost a lot of money and take a long time, but provide valuable longterm information. Cross-sectional designs are quicker and less expensive, but do not show gradual or cumulative changes."
 },
 {
  "id": 360,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Briefly describe the difference between descriptive and inferential statistics. Provide some further information about inferential statistics to explain them more in-depth.",
  "answer": "Descriptive statistics utilize mathematical operations objectively and uniformly to describe different characteristics of numerical data. Any student who has computed his or her GPA has made use of descriptive statistics. Inferential statistics utilize probability theory to make valid conclusions about which outcomes could have happened through chance alone, due to normal variations. While descriptive statistics show differences between groups, inferential statistics are needed to determine whether these differences are big enough to be meaningful, or if they simply resulted from chance. For example, if a research study using descriptive statistics were to be replicated, it could yield results showing the same patterns as the original study. If the results showed the same patterns, the group differences are meaningful. If not, the original study’s results could have been random. If it were possible to actually measure the entire populations represented by study samples, the means and standard deviations of those populations might or might not be the same as those of the smaller samples used in studies. Inferential statistics show which inferences and conclusions can legitimately be made from sample data."
 },
 {
  "id": 361,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Briefly describe the difference between descriptive and inferential statistics. Provide some further information about descriptive statistics to explain them more in-depth.",
  "answer": "Descriptive statistics utilize mathematical operations objectively and uniformly to describe different characteristics of numerical data. Any student who has computed his or her GPA has made use of descriptive statistics. Inferential statistics utilize probability theory to make valid conclusions about which outcomes could have happened through chance alone, due to normal variations. Descriptive statistics summarize patterns in data. They can be utilized to describe sets of numbers or scores for one experimental participant, but are usually used to describe data collected from different participant groups. They can also be used to describe relationships among variables. They show numbers and scores that are most typical for each group, and how much variation there is around a typical score. Variation is high when numbers are spread out across a wide range, and is low when numbers are closely clustered in a smaller range."
 },
 {
  "id": 362,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define measures of central tendency as they relate to descriptive statistics. Define mode, median, and mean.",
  "answer": "A measure of central tendency is a way to indicate the single score or number that is most representative or typical of a research participant group. It is in the center of a score distribution, with other scores clustered or spread around it. Mode, median, and mean are three measures of central tendency typically used by psychologists. Mode is the most frequent score obtained from a group. It is the easiest to determine, but often the least useful. There may be many numbers below or above the mode of a data set, so it does not seem central or typical, even though it appears most frequently in the data set. Finding the median involves dividing the upper and lower halves of a score distribution into equal parts. The median is the score with equal numbers of other scores above and below it. It is the middle score in a data set with an odd number of data points. If the total number of data points is even, researchers usually average the two middle scores. The mean is the average of all scores. It is derived by adding up all scores in a distribution and dividing the sum by the total number of scores."
 },
 {
  "id": 363,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain how frequency distributions are used in descriptive statistics, and describe how they can be rendered graphically.",
  "answer": "After researchers have collected data from an experiment—such as scores from a test or a questionnaire taken by participants—they want to obtain a clear picture of how these scores are distributed (in other words, how often each score occurs within each participant group). This way, they can compare groups. First, they rank the scores and numbers from highest to lowest. Then, they divide the ranked scores into smaller groups, or intervals. For example, 10 scores out of 100 might be included in each of the 10 intervals (0-10, 11-20, 21-30, and so on). They create a frequency distribution table showing the intervals from highest to lowest and the number of scores within each interval—the frequency. The table shows which intervals had the most scores (the highest frequency). When positive and negative scores are used, how far they deviated above or below zero (which indicates how strongly positive or negative they were) is also shown on the table. Once data are categorized in a table, they are made more visually understandable by line graphs; bar graphs; or histograms, which are bar graphs that use numerical categories instead of group names."
 },
 {
  "id": 364,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define standard deviation as it is used in descriptive statistics. Explain how it is calculated and what it indicates.",
  "answer": "The standard deviation is a measure of variability that shows the average difference between all scores in a distribution and their mean. To calculate standard deviation, both the mean of a score distribution and individual scores must be known. The mean is subtracted from each individual score, and the result is the deviation score. Each deviation score is squared to eliminate negative numbers. The deviation scores are added up, the sum is divided by the number of scores, and the square root is calculated to cancel out the previous squaring. Where SD=standard deviation; X=individual score; M=mean; N=number of scores; √=square root; and ∑=sum, the formula is: SD = √ ∑ (X-M)2 \/N. Standard deviation indicates how variable a group of scores is. The larger the standard deviation, the more spread out the scores are, and the less representative of the group the mean is. The smaller the standard deviation, the more closely clustered around the mean the scores are, and the more representative of the group the mean is."
 },
 {
  "id": 365,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define measures of variability as they relate to descriptive statistics. Explain how they inform data analysis using an example. Identify and briefly define two measures of variability.",
  "answer": "Measures of variability are statistics describing the distribution of scores around a measure of central tendency, most often the mean. By showing how much or little variation there is within a group of numbers, they inform subsequent plans. For example, if a teacher finds that students in one class all have similar proficiency in a given subject, the average (mean) score in that class is representative of the whole class, and the teacher can plan a relatively standard lesson for this class. In a class with high variability among students—some with high proficiency, and some with low proficiency—the mean, or average, proficiency score is not as representative of that class, and the teacher must plan a variety of lessons to address various student needs. The range is the simplest measure of variability, and is the difference between the highest and lowest values in a frequency distribution. The standard deviation is a variability measure showing the average difference between scores and their mean."
 },
 {
  "id": 366,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Discuss the concept of statistical significance in inferential statistics, including common p values.",
  "answer": "A difference between the mean scores of two sample groups can reflect true variation, or can result from chance. Chance variations have normal distributions (like if you flip a coin 1,000 times) represented by a normal “bell” curve. When comparing data from two groups randomly selected from the same population, the mean scores of each group are usually similar. One mean score being more than three standard deviations above or below the other is very unlikely, and would probably reflect a true difference. Using inferential statistics, one can estimate the probability that a difference was due to chance based on the size of the difference and how spread out the scores are. Psychologists generally associate a true, or statistically significant, difference with a probability (p) that is due to chance lower than 5 in 100, or p<.05. Sometimes, more stringent criteria are used. For example, chance might need to be less than 1 in 100 (p<.01), or even less than 1 in 1,000 (p<.001)."
 },
 {
  "id": 367,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Discuss the normal curve in inferential statistics. Describe central tendency measure values, provide an example, and discuss probability.",
  "answer": "Data from large numbers of individuals are distributed on a normal, bellshaped curve representing a normal frequency distribution. It is symmetrical. The highest number of scores are in the center, and the curve slopes down equally to the left and right of the center. In a normal curve, the values of the measures of central tendency—mean, median, and modeare all equal. For example, scores on the Stanford-Binet Intelligence Test have a mean of 100 and a standard deviation of 15. Roughly 68 percent of scores fall within one standard deviation from the mean, which means 68 percent of IQ scores are between 85 and 115. Another 27 percent of scores fall within one to two standard deviations from the mean. Associated score ranges for this 27 percent are between 115 and 130, and between 70 and 85. Less than 5 percent of scores fall within three standard deviations from the mean. Only around one-quarter of one percent of scores fall beyond three standard deviations from the mean. The probability of having an IQ score of 105 is greater than having one of 140, but having a score of 140 is more probable than having one of 35."
 },
 {
  "id": 368,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Explain the statistical research procedure known as meta-analysis, and outline some of its advantages.",
  "answer": "When a researcher reads the results of many studies to see overall findings on a given topic, and whether there is a consensus among most studies’ conclusions or mixed results, this is called a review of the literature. A meta-analysis is a literature review combined with a statistical analysis of the data in all the studies reviewed. This analysis is in addition to others already conducted by each individual researcher or team. This statistical procedure gives scientists a formal means of identifying general conclusions that are possible based on data obtained by multiple studies. An analogy can be made between participants within one study and studies within a meta-analysis. In other words, in one psychological experiment, the researcher wants to know whether the majority of participants showed the predicted outcomes. In a meta-analysis, the researcher wants to know whether the findings of the majority of studies analyzed showed the predicted outcomes. An advantage of meta-analysis is that it can be used to compare various studies’ results. It can also compensate for smaller sample sizes used in individual studies by analyzing larger total numbers of results."
 },
 {
  "id": 369,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Summarize the significance of a t-test in inferential statistics.",
  "answer": "Inferential statistics tell us which inferences we can legitimately make about experimental sample groups, and which conclusions we can draw about data obtained from them. It does this by estimating statistically significant differences versus differences due to chance. Depending on the research design, the type of data, and the size of sample groups, different statistical tests are used to estimate statistical significance. The t-test is one of the most common. The t-test uses mathematical calculations to determine a t-value, which is the size of the difference between score distributions in two sample groups. If the t-value is large, calculations that evaluate the difference between two groups’ mean (average) scores and numbers as a function of the variation around those two means will show that the probability of this large difference occurring by chance is very slim. For example, the chance might be less than 5 in 100, or p<.05. This probability means that the difference is statistically significant."
 },
 {
  "id": 370,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define the term validity in relation to research methodology. Identify several types of validity, and provide some general examples.",
  "answer": "In psychological research, whether a procedure or instrument measures what it is supposed to measure is defined as its validity. The simplest type of validity is face validity, meaning something simply appears to measure what it claims to. It is its face value. However, face validity alone is inadequate as it is not proven, but merely assumed. Criterion validity, also known as predictive validity, means that a measure predicts externally derived criteria. For example, if a personality rating scale showing levels of aggression has good criterion validity, it should predict which individuals will demonstrate aggressive behavior in addition to measuring aggressive traits. As another example, measures of conscientious personality characteristics with good predictive validity should predict which students will do homework and study for tests. When different measurements correlate highly, they have good convergent validity. For example, if an individual’s self-report of a characteristic, such as physical activity level, correlates strongly with peer reports of it and\/or with mechanized recordings of it, these measurements have convergent validity."
 },
 {
  "id": 371,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define reliability in relation to research methodology as a means of testing and validating study result data. Define three types of reliability and identify the general methods used to determine them.",
  "answer": "When psychological researchers conduct studies with participants to obtain quantitative results and data, they use various instruments to measure the quantities in which they are interested. They need to know how representative an instrument’s measurement is of the actual quantity or quality being investigated. This is the definition of reliability.\n\nFor example, if you gave a testing instrument to the same individual multiple times, and that individual achieved the same score every time, the test would have perfect reliability. One type of reliability is test-retest reliability.\n\nIf you administer a certain test to a group of individuals, repeat the administration at a later date, and discover individuals got similar scores both times, that instrument has high test-retest reliability. Another type of reliability is internal consistency. If you find high positive correlation among all items within one instrument, they all measure the same thing, meaning the instrument has high internal consistency. When measurements are based on observations by multiple raters, they have high inter-rater reliability if they correlate with each other. Inter-rater reliability is a third type of reliability."
 },
 {
  "id": 372,
  "topic": "Research Methods and Statistics",
  "question": "Define the concepts of construct validity and discriminant validity with respect to psychological research methodology. Contrast discriminant validity with convergent validity, and provide an example.",
  "answer": "Human variables, such as intelligence, extroversion, creativity, etc. are abstract concepts. In psychological theories, they are considered theoretical constructs. Construct validity subsumes convergent and discriminant validity, as well as face validity (something seems valid) and criterion validity (a measure of internal characteristics predicts external criteria). When a measurement has good construct validity, this generally means that it has validity (it measures what it is supposed to measure); convergent validity (it correlates well with other, related measurements); and discriminant validity (it does not correlate with other measurements that are different and separate, and can therefore be discriminated from them). Discriminant validity is the opposite of convergent validity. Measurements with convergent validity measure the same things; those with discriminant validity measure different things that can be distinguished from one another. For example, an individual might score low on an intelligence measure but high on a creativity measure. Intelligence and creativity are different constructs, and must be differentiated."
 },
 {
  "id": 373,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Provide a brief overview of the APA’s Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct (also known as the Ethics Code). Include a discussion of its components, what is and is not enforceable, applicability, inclusiveness, and some of the areas covered.",
  "answer": "The components of the APA Ethics Code are its introduction, preamble, five general principles, and specific ethical standards. The introduction covers the code’s intention, organization, procedural matters, and scope of application. The APA calls the preamble and general principles “aspirational goals” to motivate psychologists to try to act in accordance with psychology’s highest ideals. These are not enforceable rules, but guidelines for acting ethically. Enforceable rules are given in the ethical standards section. They are written generally to apply to a wide range of contexts in which psychologists practice; individual context may affect a standard’s application. The APA states these standards are “not exhaustive,” meaning a given behavior may be ethical or unethical even if a standard does not specifically address it. The code covers areas including, but not limited to: “the clinical, counseling, and school practice of psychology; research; teaching; supervision of trainees; public service; policy development; social intervention; development of assessment instruments; conducting assessments; educational counseling; organizational consulting; forensic activities; program design and evaluation; and administration.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 374,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize “Principle B: Fidelity and Responsibility,” one of the general principles in the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "“Principle B: Fidelity and Responsibility” states that psychologists establish trusting relationships with others in their work. They realize their scientific and professional responsibility to their communities, and to society. They take responsibility for their behavior, uphold professional conduct standards, make their professional duties and roles clear, and work to control conflicts of interest that could lead to harm or exploitation. To serve others’ best interests, psychologists cooperate with, consult with, or refer to other professionals and institutions as needed. Psychologists attend to their colleagues’ compliance with principles of scientific and ethical conduct. Psychologists also work to give a part of their professional time and attention for “little or no compensation or personal advantage.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 375,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize “Principle A: Beneficence and Nonmaleficence,” one of the general principles in the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "This principle says that psychologists seek to “do no harm,” something also stated in the Hippocratic Oath for physicians. The principle also says psychologists will attempt to benefit people with whom they work. Psychologists strive in their professional acts to protect the rights and wellbeing of the people they interact with and the animals they use for research. If psychologists’ duties and issues conflict, they resolve such conflicts responsibly to prevent or mitigate harm. They are aware of, and avoid, “personal, financial, social, organizational, or political factors” that could result in misusing their influence, because their professional and scientific judgments and activities can affect others’ lives. According to this first general ethical principle, psychologists also work to be cognizant of any potential effects that their own physical and mental health could have on their capacity to help people with whom they are working."
 },
 {
  "id": 376,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize “Principle D: Justice,” one of the general principles in the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "According to “Principle D: Justice,” professional psychologists should realize that justice and fairness mean that all individuals are entitled to have access to the things that psychology contributes to society, and to benefit from these things. Psychologists also acknowledge that all persons have the right to receive equal quality with respect to the services, procedures, and processes employed and provided by psychologists. This general ethical principle also states that psychologists must use reasonable judgment and take the necessary precautions to make sure that the limitations of their own expertise, the boundaries of their professional competence, and any possible biases they may possess will not condone practices that are unjust, and will not result in any unjust actions."
 },
 {
  "id": 377,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize “Principle C: Integrity,” one of the general principles in the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "“Principle C: Integrity,” one of the general principles of the APA ethics code, says that psychologists work to support honesty, accuracy, and being truthful in the practice, teaching, and science of psychology. In other words, psychologists do not intentionally misrepresent the facts in their professional activities; they do not cheat, steal, lie, or engage in fraud. They work to avoid commitments that are not prudent or whose nature is not clear. In specific circumstances where mitigating harm and optimizing benefit may ethically warrant the use of deception, psychologists are seriously obligated to think about the need for such deception, about its potential consequences, and about their own responsibility to rectify any harmful results and\/or mistrust that might proceed from their use of deceptive practices."
 },
 {
  "id": 378,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the first four of eight points under “Standard 1: Resolving Ethical Issues” in the ethical standards of the APA’s ethics code for psychologists.",
  "answer": "Under “Standard 1: Resolving Ethical Issues,” #1.01: “Misuse of Psychologists’ Work” says psychologists take reasonable actions to correct or mitigate the misuse or misrepresentation of their work if they discover it. The second point, #1.02: “Conflicts Between Ethics and Law, Regulations, or Other Governing Local Authority,” says if psychologists’ ethical commitments conflict with legal measures, they clarify the nature of the conflict; communicate their obligation to the Ethics Code; and take reasonable steps to resolve the conflict by applying the Ethics Code’s general principles and ethical standards. Point #1.02 further states that this standard must never be used to defend or justify any violation of human rights. The third point, #1.03: “Conflicts Between Ethics and Organizational Demands,” says that if an organization a psychologist works for or is affiliated with makes demands that conflict with the ethics code, the psychologist takes the same steps described in #1.02. The fourth point, #1.04: “Informal Resolution of Ethical Violations,” indicates that when psychologists believe another psychologist has violated ethics, they attempt informal resolution by bringing it up to the other psychologist, as long as it seems appropriate and does not violate confidentiality rights."
 },
 {
  "id": 379,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe “Principle E: Respect for People’s Rights and Dignity,” one of the general principles in the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "In the general principles of the APA’s ethics code, “Principle E: Respect for People’s Rights and Dignity” indicates that psychologists respect the value and dignity of all individuals; and that they respect all people’s rights to self-determination, privacy, and confidentiality. Psychologists recognize that to protect the rights of persons or communities with vulnerabilities that impede their ability to make decisions independently, specialized safeguards may be required. Psychologists realize and show respect for individual differences, cultural differences, and differences in roles. These include differences based on “age, gender, gender identity, race, ethnicity, culture, national origin, religion, sexual orientation, disability, language, and socioeconomic status.” When working with members of such diverse groups, psychologists consider these factors in their interactions. They strive to eradicate any effects of biases based on these factors on their work. Psychologists also do not consciously condone, or participate in, activities of others that are based on prejudices or biases."
 },
 {
  "id": 380,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the first three of six points under #2.01: “Boundaries of Competence,” which is found in “Standard 2: Competence” of the ethical standards section of the APA’s ethics code for psychologists.",
  "answer": "“Boundaries of Competence” states that (1) psychologists remain within the limits of their competence based on training, education, study, supervised or professional experience, or consultation when delivering services, teaching, and conducting research. It says that (2) when conducting effective services or research requires an understanding of factors related to “age, gender, gender identity, race, ethnicity, culture, national origin, religion, sexual orientation, disability, language, or socioeconomic status,” as shown by professional or scientific knowledge in the psychology discipline, psychologists possess or acquire the experience, training, consultation, or supervision needed to assure competent services. They can also make “appropriate referrals,” except in the case of emergencies. This is covered in Standard #2.02. It further states that (3) when psychologists plan to provide services, teach, or conduct research related to areas, technologies, techniques, or populations that are new to them, they pursue the pertinent training, education, study, supervised work experience, or consultation."
 },
 {
  "id": 381,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the last four of eight points under “Standard 1: Resolving Ethical Issues” in the ethical standards of the APA’s code of ethics for psychologists.",
  "answer": "The fifth point, #1.05: “Reporting Ethical Violations,” says that if an apparent violation of ethics has significantly harmed an individual or group (or is likely to do so), and the informal resolution advocated under Standard 1.04 is inappropriate (or was attempted and failed), psychologists take additional steps appropriate to the circumstances. These can include making referrals to the applicable institutional authorities, state licensure boards, or state or national professional ethics committees. Exceptions are when confidentiality rights would be violated, or when psychologists are hired to review another psychologist’s work for questionable conduct. The sixth point, #1.06: “Cooperating With Ethics Committees,” says psychologists cooperate with APA and its state affiliates in ethics investigations, proceedings, and ensuing requirements, while addressing confidentiality rights. “Failure to cooperate is itself an ethics violation.” The seventh point, #1.07: “Improper Complaints,” says psychologists do not encourage or file complaints with “reckless disregard” or “willful ignorance” of facts. The eighth point, #1.08: “Unfair Discrimination Against Complainants and Respondents,” says those who made or were the subject of ethics complaints are not denied employment, promotion, advancement, academic or other admissions, or tenure by psychologists on that basis alone."
 },
 {
  "id": 382,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe #2.02: “Providing Services in Emergencies,” #2.03: “Maintaining Competence,” and #2.04: “Bases for Scientific and Professional Judgments,” which are found in “Standard 2: Competence” of the ethical standards section of the APA’s ethics code for psychologists.",
  "answer": "The standard #2.02: “Providing Services in Emergencies” states that when other mental health services are not available to certain people, and a psychologist has not acquired the training relevant to their needs, the psychologist can provide services to such people temporarily so they are not denied services. Psychologists must discontinue such services as soon as the emergency is over or appropriate services are available. Standard #2.03: “Maintaining Competence” states that psychologists engage in continuing activities to maintain and further develop their professional competence. Standard #2.04: “Bases for Scientific and Professional Judgments” is a statement that psychologists base their work upon the established scientific and professional knowledge in the discipline of psychology. This standard includes cross-references to Standard #2.01e: “Boundaries of Competence” and Standard 10.01b: “Informed Consent to Therapy.”"
 },
 {
  "id": 383,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the last three of six points under #2.01: “Boundaries of Competence,” which is found in “Standard 2: Competence” of the ethical standards section of the APA’s ethics code for psychologists.",
  "answer": "“Boundaries of Competence” states in its fourth point that (4) if psychologists are asked to provide services for which they have not acquired the needed competence to people for whom appropriate mental health services are unavailable, psychologists with prior training or experience that is closely related to the services being requested may deliver these services to prevent such people from being denied service. This allowance is contingent upon psychologists making reasonable efforts to acquire the needed competence through pertinent study, training, research, or consultation. It says that (5) in new or emergent areas without generally accepted standards for preparation, psychologists take reasonable actions regardless to assure their competence and prevent harm to individual and organizational clients, supervisees, students, research participants, and others. This standard also states that (6) psychologists become reasonably acquainted with the administrative or judicial rules that will govern their conduct when they take on forensic roles, as in legal investigations."
 },
 {
  "id": 384,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify the bases of discrimination found unfair by Standard 3: Human Relations of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. Describe the definition given under this standard for sexual harassment from which it prohibits psychologists in engaging.",
  "answer": "In number 3.01 of Standard 3: Human Relations of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct, psychologists are enjoined not to engage in unfair discrimination in their work. Such unfair discrimination is defined there as being on bases of race, ethnicity, national origin, culture, gender, gender identity, sexual orientation, age, disability, socioeconomic status, “or any basis proscribed by law.” Number 3.02 of this standard prohibits psychologists from sexual harassment, defined as physical sexual advances; solicitation of sex; or behavior of a sexual nature, verbal or nonverbal. Moreover, such behavior takes place related to the psychologist’s work and is either unwanted, antagonistic, offends others, and the psychologist is aware or informed of it; or its intensity and\/or severity constitutes abusiveness within its context to a “reasonable person.” This definition includes both single acts and multiple or continuing behaviors. Standard 3.02 also cross-references Standard 1.08—Unfair Discrimination Against Complainants and Respondents."
 },
 {
  "id": 385,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe #2.05: “Delegation of Work to Others” and #2.06: “Personal Problems and Conflicts,” which are found in “Standard 2: Competence” of the ethical standards section of the APA’s ethics code for psychologists.",
  "answer": "According to #2.05: “Delegation of Work to Others,” when psychologists use others’ services (such as the services of interpreters) or delegate work to their teaching or research assistants, supervisees, or employees, they take reasonable actions to: (1) not delegate work to individuals who have multiple relationships with clients or patients, which would likely cause loss of objectivity or exploitation; (2) only delegate to others duties they can be expected to discharge with competence, either autonomously or with the degree of supervision given, based on their training, experience, or education; and (3) assure that those they delegate work to competently perform their duties. Standard #2.06: “Personal Problems and Conflicts” stipulates that (a) when psychologists know, or should know, that their personal problems are very likely to keep them from performing their work competently, they do not undertake such activity; and (b) when they realize personal problems may interfere with competent work, they take applicable measures, like seeking out professional help or consultation, and ascertain whether to terminate, suspend, or limit their work duties."
 },
 {
  "id": 386,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify three conditions named that constitute multiple relationships in Standard 3.05 of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. Explain how this standard distinguishes between multiple relationships that are or are not unethical.",
  "answer": "Standard 3.05 defines multiple relationships as meeting any of these three conditions: (1) the psychologist has a relationship with someone wherein the psychologist plays both a professional role and another, separate role; (2) the psychologist plays a professional role in a relationship with a person, and concurrently is in another relationship with someone having a close relation or association with the first person; or (3) the psychologist declares an intention or promise to become involved in a future relationship with somebody who has a close relation or association with a person who is in a professional relationship with the psychologist. This standard identifies multiple relationships that would be unethical as those that can interfere with the psychologist’s efficacy, competence, or objectivity in doing his or her duties as a psychologist, and\/or that carry risks of harming or exploiting the other party to a professional relationship. It defines multiple relationships that are not unethical as those not “reasonably” expected to cause or risk any such harm, exploitation, or impairment."
 },
 {
  "id": 387,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the content of Standards 3.03, Other Harassment, and 3.04, Avoiding Harm, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct.",
  "answer": "Under Standard 3: Human Relations, Standard 3.03, Other Harassment, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct states that psychologists are not to behave consciously in their work in ways that demean or harass people in their work interactions on such bases as the race, ethnicity, national origin, culture, gender, gender identity, sexual orientation, religion, language, disability, or socioeconomic status of those people. Standard 3.04, Avoiding Harm, says that psychologists take actions that are reasonable to keep from hurting the patients or clients they work with; as well as any students they teach or work with, supervisees they supervise, subjects who participate in research conducted by the psychologists, members of organizations that are clients, and any other people with whom the psychologists work. Avoiding harm in this standard also signifies that psychologists keep even inevitable and predictable harm to a minimum."
 },
 {
  "id": 388,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what is contained in Standard 3.06, Conflict of Interest, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. Also define what is prescribed by Standard 3.07, Third-Party Request for Services, of this code.",
  "answer": "Standard 3.06 addresses conflicts of interest. It specifies psychologists will not assume any professional capacity wherein they could “reasonably” expect their competence, effectiveness, or objectivity to be compromised by any other professional, scientific, legal, financial, personal, or other relationships and\/or interests. It also stipulates that psychologists not enter into any professional relationship that could expose the other person involved to any kind of exploitation or harm. Standard 3.07 states that whenever they are asked by a third party to provide an entity or individual with services, the psychologists initially try to make the nature of the relationship clear to all those involved. This includes defining the psychologist’s role, e.g., as an expert witness, consultant, diagnostician, or therapist. It also includes identifying the client, how the services will likely be utilized, what information will be acquired, and confidentiality limitations. Standard 3.07 cross-references Standard 3.05, Multiple Relationships, and Standard 4.02, Discussing the Limits of Confidentiality."
 },
 {
  "id": 389,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State what a psychologist is expected to do regarding the development of unethical multiple relationships according to Standard 3.05 of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct.",
  "answer": "This standard 3.05 under Standard 3, Human Relations, prescribes that if because of unexpected variables, a psychologist discovers that a multiple relationship has developed and it has the potential to cause harm, the psychologist takes “reasonable steps” to address this, keeping in mind both the involved person’s best interests and the psychologist’s complying with the Code of Ethics to the maximum extent possible. This standard also indicates that if a psychologist must play more than one role in administrative or judicial proceedings as mandated by legal requirements, policies of institutions, or “extraordinary circumstances,” that psychologist must first make clear what things are expected of each role they are required to play as well as the limits of the confidentiality required of them. They must also make these conditions clear anew as needed whenever anything changes them. This standard cross-references to Standard 3.04, Avoiding Harm, and Standard 3.07, Third-Party Requests for Services."
 },
 {
  "id": 390,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe #3.10: “Informed Consent” in “Standard 3: Human Relations” of the ethical standards section of the APA’s ethics code.",
  "answer": "Standard 3.10: “Informed Consent” stipulates that (a) when psychologists do research or provide services using electronic or other forms of transmission, they use language understood by the individuals involved to get their informed consent. Exceptions are government regulations and legal mandates to conduct these activities without consent, and any provisions otherwise in the Ethics Code. The standard also stipulates that (b) with persons unable to give informed consent, psychologists regardless (1) give an explanation; (2) request agreement; (3) consider the individual’s best interests and desires; and (4) when legally required or allowed, get permission or assent from a legally authorized proxy. When consent from such a legal substitute is not legally required or allowed, psychologists take reasonable actions to protect the well-being and rights of the individual. With court-ordered or mandated psychological services, psychologists inform the individual whether the expected services are courtordered or mandated, of any limits on confidentiality, and anything else relevant to the nature of the services before continuing (c). Finally, psychologists document oral or written consent appropriately, as well as permission and assent (d)."
 },
 {
  "id": 391,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify the examples of persons\/roles named in Standard 3.08, Exploitative Relationships, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. Also identify all of the other standards cross-referenced by this standard. In addition, state the content and cross-reference of Standard 3.09, Cooperation with Other Professionals.",
  "answer": "Standard 3.08 states that psychologists refrain from exploiting people they hold authority over, including such individuals as their supervisees, students, patients or clients, employees, and participants in their research. This standard cross-references the following other APA Standards: 3.05, Multiple Relationships; 6.04, Fees and Financial Arrangements; 6.05, Barter with Clients\/Patients; 7.07, Sexual Relationships with Students and Supervisees; 10.05, Sexual Intimacies with Current Therapy Clients\/Patients; 10.06, Sexual Intimacies with Relatives or Significant Others of Current Therapy Clients\/Patients; 10.07, Therapy with Former Sexual Partners; and 10.08, Sexual Intimacies with Former Therapy Clients\/Patients. Standard 3.09 states simply that psychologists will cooperate with other professionals in the interest of appropriately and effectively serving their patients or clients whenever such cooperation is appropriate professionally and is also indicated. This standard cross-references Standard 4.05, Disclosures of the same code."
 },
 {
  "id": 392,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the import of Standard 3.12, Interruption of Psychological Services, in the APA ethics code. Include the other standard it cross-references and briefly explain why.",
  "answer": "Under Standard 3, Human Relations of the APA Ethics code, standard 3.12, Interruption of Psychological Services, includes the exception “Unless otherwise covered by contract” and requires psychologists to establish plans whereby psychological services can still be provided in case of the psychologists’ own service provision should be ended or disrupted by their death, illness, retirement, relocation, or anything else that would make them unavailable; or by the financial constraints or the relocating of their patients or clients. This standard also cross-references Standard 6.02c, Maintenance, Dissemination, and Disposal of Confidential Records of Professional and Scientific Work. This is because if the psychologist’s services are ended or interrupted by any of the factors identified above, the confidential records of those services may need to be provided to other psychologists or professionals to continue or resume the needed services; or to be disposed of safely if those services by anybody are terminated instead."
 },
 {
  "id": 393,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe what is specified in Standard 3.11, Psychological Services Delivered to or Through Organizations, of the APA code of ethics.",
  "answer": "This standard specifies that when psychologists provide services to organizations or through organizations, they give certain information in advance to clients and anyone else whom the services would directly affect when appropriate. This includes information about the goals of the services and their nature; which people are meant to receive the services; who are clients among those people; what relationship the psychologist, the organization, and each individual involved will have; how the services will likely be utilized; what information will be acquired in the process; which persons will have access to the information acquired; and confidentiality limitations. Psychologists are also to inform the appropriate people with information about the outcomes of these services, and the conclusions they draw through the services, as soon as is practicable. This standard also specifies that if psychologists’ roles in an organization or any laws prohibit them from furnishing this information to any specific group(s) or individual persons, they notify those groups or individuals at the beginning of services."
 },
 {
  "id": 394,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Relate what is covered under Standard 4.02, Discussing the Limits of Confidentiality, of the APA’s ethical code, including a cross-reference.",
  "answer": "This standard specifies that when psychologists form professional or scientific relationships with groups and individuals—including insofar as is practicable with individuals legally judged incompetent to give their consent and those legally representing them—they discuss with those people (1) the confidentiality limitations that are pertinent; and (2) how the information that psychologists acquire via their work can be predicted to be utilized. The first section of this standard (a) cross-references Standard 3.10, Informed Consent, of the same code. This standard also states that such a discussion of confidentiality should take place at the beginning of the professional relationship, and subsequently as changing conditions may dictate, unless this is contraindicated or is not practicable. It moreover includes that when psychologists provide services, information, or products using electronic transmission methods, they must inform their patients or clients of the associated confidentiality limits and privacy risks."
 },
 {
  "id": 395,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify the main standard under which Standard 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality, falls in the APA ethics code and describe its meaning. Identify another standard that it cross-references and why.",
  "answer": "Standard 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality, falls under main Standard 4: Privacy and Confidentiality of the APA Ethics code. Standard 4.01 specifically expresses that it is a foremost duty of psychologists to take realistic measures for the protection of confidential material they have acquired through or saved “in any medium,” with the knowledge that laws, professional and scientific relationships, and\/or existing rules of institutions may regulate the degrees and constraints upon the confidentiality of that material. This standard also cross-references Standard 2.05, Delegation of Work to Others, because when psychologists delegate work to other parties it is often necessary for them to share confidential records with those delegated, especially if the work delegated involves counseling, therapy, interviewing, follow-up, consultation, or serving as an expert witness. Thus, the psychologist must both share confidential information, and also protect the confidentiality of that information beyond sharing it with the delegated other(s)."
 },
 {
  "id": 396,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what ethical principles are defined in APA Ethical Code Standard 4.05, Disclosures. Include a cross-reference to another standard in the same code.",
  "answer": "Standard 4.05, Disclosures, requires psychologists to obtain consent from individual patients or clients, their agents or representatives with legal authorization on the patient’s or client’s behalf; or from organizations that are their clients, to disclose any confidential information about them. The exception to this requirement is if such disclosure and\/or consent are illegal. This standard also specifies that psychologists can only disclose confidential information without client consent if a law mandates them to do so; if a law allows it for a valid reason, e.g., for giving necessary professional service, getting needed professional consults, protecting the patient or client, psychologist, and\/or others against harm, or collecting patient or client payment for services the psychologist has rendered. In these aforementioned circumstances, the standard specifies that such disclosure without consent must be the minimum needed for accomplishing its objective. This standard cross-references Standard 6.04e, Fees and Financial Arrangements."
 },
 {
  "id": 397,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the content of the APA ethical code’s Standard 4.03, Recording, including cross-references; and Standard 4.04, Minimizing Intrusions on Privacy.",
  "answer": "Standard 4.03, Recording, requires psychologists to get consent from all involved people whom they serve or their legal representatives before they record their images and\/or voices. This standard cross-references Standards: 8.03, Informed Consent for Recording Voices and Images in research; 8.05, Dispensing with Informed Consent for Research; and 8.07, Deception in Research. Standard 4.04, Minimizing Intrusions on Privacy, contains two requirements. The first (a) says that when psychologists make oral and written consultations and reports, they include only the information that is relevant to the purpose for which they are communicating through those consultations and\/or reports. The second (b) stipulates regarding confidential information that psychologists acquire in their work activities, that they only discuss this information with people whose concern with the material is obvious; and only for professional and\/or scientific reasons that are appropriate."
 },
 {
  "id": 398,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the conditions of Standard 5.01, Avoidance of False or Deceptive Statements, of the APA code of ethics.",
  "answer": "This standard defines “public statements” as not being limited to but including the following: curricula vitae or personal resumes; applications for licensure or other credentials; comments to be used in printed or electronic media; published materials; oral presentations given in public; statements made in legal proceedings; directory listings; brochures; printed materials; grant applications; product endorsements; and unpaid or paid advertising. The standard requires psychologists not to publicly make statements they know are untrue, fraudulent, or misleading about their practice, research, or other work or that of groups or individuals affiliated with them. Psychologists are also prohibited from making such statements about their own expertise, training, experience, credentials, academic degrees, affiliations with associations or institutions, services, clinical or scientific bases for outcomes of their services or the extent of their services’ success; fees, publications, or research findings. Additionally, psychologists can only cite their degrees as credentials for their services if the degrees came from regionally accredited educational institutions, or were bases for their state licensure to practice."
 },
 {
  "id": 399,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State what is covered in Standard 4.06, Consultations, and Standard 4.07, Use of Confidential Information for Didactic or Other Purposes, of the APA ethics code.",
  "answer": "Standard 4.06, Consultations, states that when psychologists consult with their colleagues, they must not share confidential information that could identify the patient or client, research subject, or any other individual or group in a confidential relationship with the psychologists, unless the group or person has previously given consent, or such disclosure is unavoidable. When they do make such disclosures, the standard further specifies that they disclose only as much information as is needed to meet the objectives of the consultation. This standard cross-references Standard 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality. Standard 4.07, Use of Confidential Information for Didactic or Other Purposes, prohibits psychologists from disclosing confidential information acquired through their work that could personally identify individual or organizational clients, patients, research participants, students, or other service recipients. This standard only allows such disclosure if psychologists disguise those who could be identified; or if those persons have given written consent; or if the psychologists are legally authorized to disclose the information."
 },
 {
  "id": 400,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify which responsibilities of psychologists are indicated in Standards 5.03, Descriptions of Workshops and Non-DegreeGranting Educational Programs; and 5.04, Media Presentations, of the APA ethical standards and code of conduct. Include the latter’s cross-referenced standard and the reason.",
  "answer": "Standard 5.03 charges psychologists with the responsibility, within their control, for assuring the accuracy of descriptions of the intended recipients, educational goals, presenters, and associated costs of educational programs, seminars, workshops, etc., that do not grant degrees in the advertisements, brochures, catalogs, or announcements that publicize such programs. Standard 5.04 assigns responsibility to psychologists for also assuring the accuracy of their own public comments, statements, or advice when they give these through print or electronic media. This includes seeing that such statements they make are consistent with their own professional experience, training, and\/or knowledge and with relevant psychological practices and literature; are congruent with the APA Ethics Code containing the standard; and do not show a professional relationship having been formed with whoever is\/are receiving their statements. Standard 5.04 also cross-references Standard 2.04, Bases for Scientific and Professional Judgments, as both pertain to the ethical consideration that psychologists’ judgments and statements be based in the professional and scientific knowledge of their discipline."
 },
 {
  "id": 401,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain the content of Standard 5.02, Statements by Others, of the APA ethical principles and code of conduct for psychologists, including its cross-reference to another standard. Give an example of the third\/last requirement of this standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 5.02 articulates that psychologists are professionally responsible for any statements made by others engaged by those psychologists to make or disseminate public statements to promote the psychologists’ professional practices, products, or actions. It also stipulates that if psychologists receive publicity from being included in news reports, articles, stories, etc., they do not give compensation to TV, radio, print, electronic, or other communications media employees in exchange for that publicity. This standard cross-references the same code’s Standard 1.01, Misuse of Psychologists’ Work, which relates to the same ethical issues. Standard 5.02 furthermore requires that psychologists must clearly identify or otherwise make clearly recognizable any paid advertisements of or related to the psychologists’ work as being a paid advertisement. For example, advertisements on TV, in print, or online for a psychologist’s services frequently include a line of small text at the bottom saying, “This is a paid advertisement for [psychologist name and degree or credentials]” or words to that effect."
 },
 {
  "id": 402,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Cite five purposes for which psychologists are tasked with managing records in their work, as identified by APA ethics code Standard 6.01, Documentation of Professional and Scientific Work and Maintenance of Records. Also summarize three aspects of confidential records management, as stated in Standard 6.02, Maintenance, Dissemination, and Disposal of Confidential Records of Professional and Scientific Work. Identify which standards are cross-referenced by each of these standards.",
  "answer": "Standard 6.01 requires psychologists to produce data and records related to their work and, insofar as they have control, to be responsible for disseminating, maintaining, retaining, storing, and disposing of these data and records. Five reasons cited for these are: (1) expediting subsequent service provision by them and\/or other professionals; (2) enabling research analyses and designs to be replicated; (3) fulfilling requirements of institutions; (4) making billing and payments accurate; and (5) complying with laws. This standard cross-references Standard 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality. Standard 6.02 adds that (1) in management of records—printed, electronic, or in other media—psychologists preserve their confidentiality.\n\nMoreover, if confidential information is input to records systems or databases, others can access without patient\/client consent, psychologists must (2) conceal patient\/client personal identities using coding, etc.; and (3) plan ahead for transferring records and preserving their confidentiality if they leave their practices or positions. Standard 6.02 cross-references: Standards 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality, as Standard 6.01 does; 6.01 itself; 3.12, Interruption of Psychological Services; and 10.09, Interruption of Therapy."
 },
 {
  "id": 403,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the import of Standards 5.05, Testimonials, and 5.06, In-Person Solicitation, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct, including their reasons and two exceptions to Standard 5.06.",
  "answer": "Standard 5.05, Testimonials, warns psychologists not to solicit any recommendations or testimonials about their services from their current patients or clients, because current patients or clients have greater vulnerability than others to being influenced unfairly by their therapists. This vulnerability is also the reason for Standard 5.06, In-Person Solicitation, which forbids psychologists to solicit existing or prospective patients or clients—directly or via others acting as their agents—to give the psychologists their business. There are two exceptions named in this second standard: (1) Psychologists may solicit persons to be ancillary contacts who would be of additional benefit to the psychologists’ existing patients or clients; and (2) psychologists may “solicit” business from clients to whom they will be delivering psychological services as a part of community outreach or disaster relief outreach services."
 },
 {
  "id": 404,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Sum up the content of Standards 6.05, Barter with Clients\/Patients; 6.06, Accuracy in Reports to Payors and Funding Sources; and 6.07, Referrals and Fees, including cross-referenced standards, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct.",
  "answer": "Standard 6.05 states that barter, i.e., trading services, goods, or other nonmoney forms of compensation, for services by psychologists is only allowed if (1) there is no clinical contraindication; and (2) a bartering agreement does not exploit either party. Standard 6.05 cross-references Standards 3.05, Multiple Relationships; and 6.04, Fees and Financial Arrangements. Standard 6.06 requires psychologists to assure that the nature of services delivered, research conducted; fees or payments; and provider identity, findings regarding patients\/clients, and diagnoses where these apply, are reported accurately. This standard cross-references Standards 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality; 4.04, Minimizing Intrusions on Privacy; and 4.05, Disclosures. Standard 6.07 stipulates that except for in employee-employer relationships, whenever psychologists are paid, pay, or split fees with other professionals, the payment each of them receives is not based on the referral, but on delivered services—consultative, administrative, clinical, or other. This standard cross-references Standard 3.09, Cooperation with Other Professionals."
 },
 {
  "id": 405,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize Standard 6.03, Withholding Records for Nonpayment of the APA ethical code; and Standard 6.04, Fees and Financial Arrangements, including which standards the latter cross-references.",
  "answer": "Standard 6.03 prohibits psychologists from withholding patient\/client records they control for nonpayment if these are needed for patient\/client emergency treatment. Standard 6.04 enjoins psychologists to make agreements with patients\/clients regarding billing and payment arrangements as soon as is practicable in the scientific or professional relationship. It also requires psychologists to use fee practices conforming to laws, and not to misrepresent their fees. Further, if psychologists expect limits on their services due to patient\/client financial limitations, this standard enjoins psychologists to discuss this with patients\/clients as soon as is practicable.\n\nThis requirement cross-references Standards 10.09, Interruption of Therapy, and 10.10, Terminating Therapy. This standard moreover states that if the patient\/client does not pay as agreed upon for the psychologist’s services and the psychologist then plans to use a collection agency, the psychologist must first notify the patient\/client of this and give the patient\/client a chance to pay promptly before initiating this measure. This requirement cross-references Standards 4.05, Disclosures; 6.03, Withholding Records for Nonpayment; and 10.01, Informed Consent to Therapy."
 },
 {
  "id": 406,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe what is required of psychologists by APA ethical code Standard 7.03, Accuracy in Teaching, what is allowed by it, and which other standard in this code it cross-references. Summarize Standard 7.04, Student Disclosure of Personal Information, in the same ethical code.",
  "answer": "Standard 7.03 requires teaching psychologists to make their course syllabi accurate concerning what subjects will be covered, the nature of experiences, and how student learning\/performance will be assessed. This standard allows psychologist instructors to change course requirements and\/or content as they see fit, providing they notify students of these changes such that the students are still able to satisfy the requirements. This part of the standard cross-references Standard 5.01, Avoidance of False or Deceptive Statements. Psychologists must also accurately present psychological information when training\/teaching. Standard 7.04 prohibits psychologists from requiring students or supervisees to disclose personal information about history of abuse and neglect, sexual history, relationships with family\/friends, or psychological treatment—either written or oral—in program-related\/course-related activity, with two exceptions: (1) the requirement was clearly stated in program and admissions materials; or (2) this information is needed for evaluating and\/or getting help for students whose personal issues could interfere with their conducting professional and\/or training activities competently, and\/or threaten themselves and\/or others."
 },
 {
  "id": 407,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what is covered by APA ethics code Standards 7.01, Design of Education and Training Programs, including a cross-referenced standard; and 7.02, Descriptions of Education and Training Programs.",
  "answer": "Standard 7.01 requires psychologists who are responsible for training and\/or educational programs to see that the design of these programs affords the experiences and knowledge needed by students, and satisfies the necessities for licensure, certification, other credentialing, and\/or other objectives the program claims to meet. This standard cross-references Standard 5.03, Descriptions of Workshops and Non-Degree-Granting Educational Programs. Standard 7.02 also addresses psychologists responsible for training and\/or educational programs, enjoining them to assure accurate descriptions of the content of such programs. This includes whether courses or programs require course-related participation in psychotherapy, counseling, experiential groups, community service, or consulting projects. Psychologists are also required to assure accuracy in the descriptions of training objectives and goals; of requirements that must be fulfilled to complete the programs satisfactorily; and of any benefits and stipends. In addition to making this information accurate, psychologists must also make it easily accessible by all those interested."
 },
 {
  "id": 408,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State the content of Standards 7.06, Assessing Student and Supervisee Performance, and 7.07, Sexual Relationships with Students and Supervisees, of the APA Ethical Principles of Psychologists and Code of Conduct. Include which standard is cross-referenced in Standard 7.07.",
  "answer": "Standard 7.06 advises psychologists who supervise students, interns, and employees to give them information about the supervision process at its outset; and to have created specific, timely processes for giving their supervisees and students feedback, which information they will give them when they begin the supervisory interactions. This standard also enjoins psychologists to use existing and pertinent program requirements as bases for evaluating their supervisees and students, and to make such evaluations based on the supervisees’ and\/or students’ actual performance. Standard 7.07 states that psychologists do not have sexual relationships with supervisees or students whom they have the authority to evaluate, or are likely to have such authority; or even those who are located in the same agency, training center, or department as the psychologists are. This standard cross-references Standard 3.05, Multiple Relationships, of the same ethical code, as such relationships constitute conflicts of interest."
 },
 {
  "id": 409,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify what is contained in APA Ethical Standard 7.05, Mandatory Individual or Group Therapy, including cross-references to other standards of this ethical code.",
  "answer": "Standard 7.05 of the ethical code stipulates that when an educational or training course or program for undergraduate or graduate students requires those students to participate in individual therapy or group therapy, the psychologists who are responsible for that course or program will give the students the choice of obtaining that therapy from practitioners who are or are not affiliated with the educational or training course or program in which the students are participating. This part of the standard cross-references Standard 7.02, Descriptions of Education and Training Programs, which requires teaching psychologists to make such course or program information accurate and accessible. The second part of Standard 7.05 stipulates that psychologists who are the faculty members responsible or likely to be responsible for assessing the academic performance of students taking courses that require attendance in therapy, those faculty psychologists must not also be the providers of that required therapy. This part cross-references Standard 3.05, Multiple Relationships, which addresses conflicts of interest, including this kind."
 },
 {
  "id": 410,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Enumerate eight points of which psychologists are to inform research participants according to the first of two parts of APA ethics code Standard 8.02, Informed Consent to Research; and three other standards in this code that this section cross-references.",
  "answer": "Section (a) of Standard 8.02 references Standard 3.10, Informed Consent, which requires obtaining it; and elaborates that psychologists must inform participants of the following: (1) the intent of research, how long it is expected to take, and what its procedures; (2) participant rights to decline participation, or withdraw from it after beginning; (3) what results can be predicted from declining or withdrawing; (4) things that can be foreseen to influence participation like discomfort, adverse effects, and\/or possible risks; (5) any benefits possible from research or participating in it; (6) confidentiality limits; (7) incentives if offered for participating in the research; and (8) who can be contacted to ask questions about the research and about the rights of research participants. Research psychologists are also to give participants opportunities to ask questions and have them answered. This section of the standard cross-references Standards 8.03, Informed Consent for Recording Voices and Images in Research; 8.05, Dispensing with Informed Consent for Research; and 8.07, Deception in Research."
 },
 {
  "id": 411,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State the content of the APA ethical code’s Standard 8.01, Institutional Approval; and of its Standard 8.03, Informed Consent for Recording Voices and Images in Research including a cross-referenced standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.01 specifies that when psychologists are required to obtain approval from an institution(s) for conducting research, they give correct information about their proposed investigations; acquire the necessary approval before doing their proposed research; and do it according to approved protocols. Standard 8.03 stipulates that psychologists get participants’ informed consent before they record their voices and\/or images for the purposes of collecting data. Exceptions to this rule are if: (1) naturalistic observations made in public locations comprise the data collection, and this recording of voices and images are not expected to be applied to identify participants personally or harm them; and (2) deception is a part of the research design, and the research includes debriefing during which consent to use the recordings is acquired. Standard 8.03 also cross-references Standard 8.07, Deception in Research, which is a part of the same ethical code."
 },
 {
  "id": 412,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State what two provisions are required of psychologists in APA ethics code Standard 8.04, Client\/Patient, Student, and Subordinate Research Participants; and what two provisions are required by Standard 8.06, Offering Inducements for Research Participation, including a cross-referenced standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.04a requires psychologists who will conduct research with participants who are their patients, clients, subordinates, or students, they protect these potential participants from any unfavorable consequences if they decline or withdraw from participating. Standard 8.04b requires that when psychologists make participating in research an opportunity to earn extra course credit or a requirement of a course, they also offer the potential participants choices of comparable activities as alternatives to research participation. Standard 8.06a enjoins psychologists not to offer monetary or other inducements that are inappropriate or overmuch and could constitute coercion to participate in research. Standard 8.06b provides that if psychologists offer professional services as incentives for participating in research, they must make clear the nature, limitations, risks, and obligations of the services offered. This section of the standard cross-references Standard 6.05, Barter with Clients\/Patients under the same APA ethical code."
 },
 {
  "id": 413,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Enumerate five points specified in the second of two parts of APA ethics code Standard 8.02, Informed Consent to Research, regarding information psychologists must provide to participants in research involving experimental treatments. Include another standard in the same code that this section cross-references.",
  "answer": "Section (b) of Standard 8.02 enjoins psychologists who conduct intervention research using experimental treatments to make clear to participants at the beginning of such studies the following points: (1) the fact that the treatment used is experimental in nature; (2) what services will and\/or will not be accessible to participants in control groups, when applicable; (3) how the researcher(s) will assign participants to control groups and treatment groups; (4) what alternatives to the experimental treatment will be available to individuals who do not want to participate in the research, or who want to withdraw from the study after it has started; and (5) any financial expenses for participating in the study and\/or any financial compensation for participating in it, including where applicable whether the researcher(s) will seek any reimbursement from participants or third-party payers. This second section of the standard also cross-references Standard 8.02a, Informed Consent to Research, which is the first section of the same standard."
 },
 {
  "id": 414,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain the import of APA ethical Standard 8.07, Deception in Research, including a cross-referenced standard of the same code.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.07a provides that psychologists do not use deception in their research studies unless they have previously ascertained that effective alternatives without deception are not practicable, and that the study will afford significant enough value educationally, scientifically, and\/or in application to warrant its use of deceptive procedures. Standard 8.07b provides that if they expect their research to cause physical or emotional pain, psychologists will not deceive potential participants about this. Standard 8.07c provides that whenever any kind of deception is an integral part of their experimental research design, psychologists will explain that deception to their participants as soon as possible; i.e., as soon as their participation is complete, which is preferable, and when data have been collected at the very latest; and that psychologists will also allow participants to withdraw their data at that time. This standard also cross-references the following Standard 8.08, Debriefing, which concerns information psychologists should give to research participants at the end of a study."
 },
 {
  "id": 415,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what is contained in APA ethical Standard 8.05, Dispensing with Informed Consent for Research.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.05 outlines the conditions under which psychologists are allowed to waive informed consent for research. One main category is as allowed by law, or by institutional or federal regulations. Another is if research is not expected to cause harm or distress. Under this category is further included the following conditions: (a) The research studies normal educational curricula, practices, or classroom management techniques that are performed in education settings; (b) The study protects participant confidentiality and uses only archival research, naturalistic observations, or anonymous questionnaires and participant responses would not risk damage to their reputations, employable status, or financial standing or risk civil or criminal liability; or (c) The research studies variables that are associated with organizational or job effectiveness, is conducted in organizational settings, places participants at no risks to their jobs or employability, and protects their confidentiality."
 },
 {
  "id": 416,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Report the content of the first three sections of APA ethical Standard 8.09, Humane Care and Use of Animals in Research, including a standard cross-referenced in the third section.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.09a provides that psychologists will comply with professional standards as well as with current federal, state, and local regulations and laws in the ways that they obtain, take care of, utilize, and dispose of animals in their research. Standard 8.09b provides that when laboratory animals are used in psychological research studies, all of the research procedures involving those laboratory animals are always supervised by psychologists who have training in methods of research and experience in how to care for laboratory animals; and that those qualified supervising psychologists are responsible for making sure that the humane treatment, health, and comfort of the animals is considered and ensured appropriately. Standard 8.09c requires psychologists to assure that all of the individuals whom they supervise and who work with animals have been instructed in research methods and in how to maintain, handle, and care for the species of animal(s) involved, to the degree(s) applicable to the research\/work roles of those individuals. This section cross-references Standard 2.05, Delegation of Work to Others."
 },
 {
  "id": 417,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe what psychologists are expected to do by APA ethical Standard 8.08, Debriefing.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.08 requires firstly that psychologists will timely give research participants opportunities for getting suitable information about the nature of the research, its results, and conclusions drawn by the researchers; and rectify any misunderstandings they know of that the participants may entertain. This ethical standard provides secondly that psychologists will take “reasonable” steps to minimize harm to research participants if any humane or scientific values should warrant the withholding or delaying of giving such information about the research to those participants. Thirdly, this standard provides that if psychologists ever find out that any of the procedures they have used in conducting their research have caused harm to any of the participants in their studies, they take “reasonable” actions to reduce such harm to the minimum amount that is possible."
 },
 {
  "id": 418,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State the provisions of APA ethical standards 8.10, Reporting Research Results; 8.11, Plagiarism; and 8.12, Publication Credit. Include any standards cross-referenced in any of these.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.10a prohibits psychologists from fabricating data, and cross-references Standard 5.01a, Avoidance of False or Deceptive Statements. Standard 8.10b provides if psychologists find significant mistakes in their published data, they retract or correct them, publish errata, or use other suitable publishing methods. Standard 8.11 prohibits psychologists from representing any of others’ data\/work as their own, including cited sources.\n\nStandard 8.12a requires psychologists take credit, including as authors, and responsibility only for work they significantly contributed to or performed; cross-referencing Standard 8.12b, which requires publication credits, including for principal authorship, to reflect correctly relative professional\/scientific contributions of involved individuals irrespective of status. Author credit is not warranted simply by department chairmanships or other institutional positions. Minor writing and\/or research contributions require suitable acknowledgements, e.g., in introductions, footnotes, etc. Standard 8.12c requires doctoral dissertations to name doctoral students as principal authors among multiple authors (with some unusual exceptions); and faculty advisors to discuss publishing credits with students early and throughout the process as suitable. 8.12c also cross-references 8.12b."
 },
 {
  "id": 419,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Indicate the provisions of the last four sections of APA ethical Standard 8.09, Humane Care and Use of Animals in Research.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.09d requires psychologists to keep to the minimum any pain, discomfort, illness, and infection in animals that they use in research. Standard 8.09e provides that psychologists will not subject animals they use for research to deprivation, stress, or pain except if no alternative procedures are available and the potential applied, educational, or scientific value of the goal of the research justifies it. Standard 8.09f requires psychologists to use suitable anesthesia when performing surgical procedures on animals, and to adhere to infection prevention and pain reduction techniques during and following surgeries. Standard 9.09g provides that when it has been deemed necessary or appropriate to terminate the life of an animal used in research, psychologists will make efforts to keep pain to a minimum for the animal, proceed quickly with the termination, and do so according to the procedures that are approved for doing so."
 },
 {
  "id": 420,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the provisions of APA ethical Standard 8.14, Sharing Research Data for Verification.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.14a provides that after psychologists have published the results of their research and other qualified professionals want to reanalyze the data the researchers used as bases for their research conclusions to confirm the “substantive” claims made by the publishing researchers—and will use those data for only that reason—the psychologists who published the research will not withhold those data. Though they may not withhold the data, psychologists are not prohibited from holding the other professionals responsible for the expenses related to providing it to them. Standard 8.14b provides that when psychologists ask other psychologists for data for the purpose of reanalyzing the data in order to confirm substantive claims, the requesting psychologists are allowed to use the data for only that purpose. This section of the standard also requires the psychologists requesting such data to acquire written consent in advance for using the data in any other way(s)."
 },
 {
  "id": 421,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Report what is required by APA ethical Standards 8.13, Duplicate Publication of Data, and 8.15, Reviewers.",
  "answer": "Standard 8.13, Duplicate Publication of Data, prohibits psychologists from publishing previously published data as original data. However, it is acceptable and is not prohibited for psychologists to republish existing data as long as they give the correct acknowledgments to the previous publishers of those data. Standard 8.15, Reviewers, requires that when psychologists review any material that has been submitted for approval to be presented, to be published, as part of a proposal of research, or in a proposal of research that is part of an application for a funding grant; those psychologists will observe the proprietary rights of the persons who have submitted the material, and they will also observe the confidentiality of the information that those persons have submitted."
 },
 {
  "id": 422,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what ethical principles are included under APA Standard 9.02, Use of Assessments.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.02a tells psychologists that when they administer assessment instruments, tests, interviews, or techniques; adapt these, score them, interpret, or otherwise use them, they must do so for goals and in ways that are suitable considering the evidence of and\/or research into evidence of their correct application and utility. Standard 9.02b instructs psychologists to utilize assessment instruments that have been found to be reliable and valid when used with members of the normative or representative population(s); or when assessment instruments do not have established reliability and validity, to communicate the limitations and strengths of the results and interpretation of these instruments. Standard 9.02c advises psychologists to employ methods of assessment that are congruent with the linguistic competence and language preference of the individuals being tested, unless using a different language is pertinent to assessment concerns [e.g., with ESL\/ELL\/TOEFL, etc.]."
 },
 {
  "id": 423,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the import of APA ethical Standard 9.01, Bases for Assessments. Include any standards within the same code that are cross-referenced in this standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.01a requires that when psychologists give forensic testimony, evaluations, diagnoses, reports, or recommendations, they base their opinions therein on methods and information adequate to corroborate them. This section cross-references Standard 2.04, Bases for Scientific and Professional Judgments. Standard 9.01b, noting 9.01c as an exception, requires psychologists to conduct adequately supporting examinations of individuals before making conclusions or statements about their psychological characteristics. When such examination is not feasible, this standard requires psychologists to document their attempts and the outcomes; make clear the expected effects of their limited information on the validity and reliability of their opinions; and limit accordingly the degree and character of the recommendations or conclusions they make. This section cross-references Standards 2.01, Boundaries of Competence; and 9.06, Interpreting Assessment Results. Standard 9.06c provides that when giving supervision or consultation, or doing records reviews, and their opinions do not require individual examinations, psychologists explain that and provide the information sources that are the bases for their recommendations and\/or conclusions."
 },
 {
  "id": 424,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the content of APA ethical Standard 9.04, Release of Test Data, including a cross-referenced standard from the same code.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.04a defines “test data” as responses of patients or clients to stimuli or test questions; raw scores; scaled scores; and psychologists’ recordings and notes about patient or client behavior and statements they have made during examinations by the psychologists. It allows psychologists to give such test data to patients or clients, or identified others, if the patient or client has executed a release of this information. It also allows psychologists to protect patients or clients or others from harm and\/or misrepresentation or misuse of data or tests by refusing to release such data, adding that under such conditions, the release of such confidential information is often regulated by laws. Standard 9.04a also cross-references Standard 9.11, Maintaining Test Security. Standard 9.04b states that psychologists will only furnish test data as mandated by court order or by law when there is no patient\/client release of information."
 },
 {
  "id": 425,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the provisions of APA Standard 9.03, Informed Consent in Assessments, including other standards in the same code that it references or cross-references.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.03a requires psychologists to get informed consent for diagnostic, assessment, or evaluation services, referencing Standard 3.10, Informed Consent. Exceptions are if: (1) laws or government regulations mandate testing; (2) routine organizational\/institutional\/educational procedures, as for job applications, imply informed consent; (3) assessing decision-making ability is part of testing. Explaining the purpose and nature of assessment, third-party involvement, fees, confidentiality limits, and adequate opportunities to ask and have questions answered are included under informed consent. 9.03b requires psychologists testing persons with dubious capacity to consent, and\/or when government regulations or laws mandate testing, to inform those to be tested of the purpose and nature of assessment, using language understandable to them. 9.03c requires psychologists to get informed consent to use interpreter services; preserve test security and confidentiality of test results; and include any data limitations in their testimony, reports, evaluative or diagnostic statements, or recommendations. 9.03c cross-references 2.05, Delegation of Work to Others; 4.01, Maintaining Confidentiality; 9.01, Bases for Assessments; 9.06, Interpreting Assessment Results; and 9.07, Assessment by Unqualified Persons."
 },
 {
  "id": 426,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the content of APA ethical Standards 9.07, Assessment by Unqualified Persons; and 9.08, Obsolete Tests and Outdated Test Results. Include a cross-referenced standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.07 prohibits psychologists from advancing the utilization of psychological testing methods by people who are unqualified to do so. The only exception to this rule is during appropriately supervised training, as when psychologists supervise and\/or train students, interns, or employees in conducting psychological assessments. This standard cross-references APA ethical Standard 2.05, Delegation of Work to Others. Standard 9.08a prohibits psychologists from making recommendations or decisions about interventions or assessments on the bases of test results or data that are out of date relative to the current purposes for such intervention or assessment recommendations or decisions. Standard 9.08b adds that psychologists will not use tests and measurements that are “...obsolete and not useful for the current purpose” as the bases for their recommendations or decisions."
 },
 {
  "id": 427,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify what is prescribed in APA ethical Standards 9.05, Test Construction; and 9.06, Interpreting Test Results.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.05 requires psychologists who create assessment methods or instruments, including tests, to utilize current professional or scientific knowledge and applicable psychometric practices for designing the tests, validating them; standardizing the tests; eliminating or reducing biases in the tests; and making recommendations for using them. Standard 9.06 requires that when psychologists interpret test results, including the use of automated interpretations, they will keep in mind the reasons for the testing; the variables within the test; the characteristics of the individual being tested, including linguistic, cultural, situational, and personal differences, test-taking abilities, etc., that could decrease the veracity of the psychologists’ interpretations or influence their judgments. Psychologists are also directed to communicate any significant ways in which their interpretations of assessments are limited. This standard also cross-references Standards 2.01b and 2.01c under 2.01, Boundaries of Competence; and Standard 3.01, Unfair Discrimination."
 },
 {
  "id": 428,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Summarize the content of APA ethical Standards 9.10, Explaining Assessment Results, and 9.11, Maintaining Test Security, including a cross-reference to an associated standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.10 enjoins psychologists to see that explanations of test results are communicated to the person(s) tested or their designated representative(s), irrespective of whether the psychologists score and interpret these tests or others do. Exceptions to providing explanations of test results include forensic evaluations, security screenings, preemployment screenings, and some organizational consulting, wherein the nature of the interaction prohibits explaining test results; in which case they must explain this prohibition clearly to individuals being tested before testing. Standard 9.11 defines the term “test materials” as stimuli, test questions, protocols, instruments, and manuals. It states that “test materials” do not include “test data” as defined in Standard 9.04, Release of Test Data, which is cross-referenced herein. Standard 9.11 obliges psychologists to preserve the integrity of assessment methods including test materials according to contractual requirements and laws, and in ways allowing compliance with the APA Ethics Code containing these standards."
 },
 {
  "id": 429,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "State what is included in APA ethical Standard 9.09, Test Scoring and Interpretation Services, including a cross-referenced standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 9.09a specifies that that when psychologists provide or offer their services for testing or test-scoring to other professionals, they will correctly depict the procedures used; any special requirements for using them; their purposes; their norms; their validity and reliability; and their applications. Standard 9.09b requires psychologists to choose services for scoring and interpretation, including automated ones, based on evidence that the procedures and programs involved in those services are valid, and based on other applicable factors. Standard 9.09b also cross-references Standards 2.01b and 2.01c under 2.01, Boundaries of Competence, of the same ethical code. Standard 9.09c assigns to psychologists the responsibility for correctly using, applying, and interpreting assessment instruments. This responsibility is applicable regardless of whether the psychologists themselves do the scoring and interpretation of the tests, or they use other services including automated services for test scoring and interpretation."
 },
 {
  "id": 430,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe the import of APA ethical Standard 10.02, Therapy Involving Couples or Families, including cross-referenced ethical standards.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.02a stipulates that when psychologists have agreed to serve several related individuals—e.g., parents and children, married couples, siblings, or significant others—they will make reasonable efforts at the beginning to make clear who among these individuals is\/are the patients\/clients, and what relationship each individual involved will have with the therapist. This includes the role of the psychologist, and how the information acquired and\/or the services given will probably be used. 10.02a cross-references Standard 4.02, Discussing the Limits of Confidentiality. Standard 10.02b clarifies that if psychologists find they will be asked to assume roles that could conflict with one another—for example, providing marriage counseling to a couple and subsequently being asked to be a witness for one member of the couple during divorce proceedings—the psychologists will take realistic actions either to change their roles, make them clear, or withdraw from them as is indicated. This section of the standard cross-references Standard 3.05c, Multiple Relationships."
 },
 {
  "id": 431,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what is covered under APA ethical Standard 10.01, Informed Consent to Therapy, including any cross-references.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.01a requires psychologists, when acquiring informed consent to therapy, to inform patients\/clients as early in the therapeutic relationship as possible about the therapy’s expected course, nature, third-party involvement, and confidentiality limits; and give them adequate opportunities for asking and having their questions answered. 10.01a cross-references Standards 3.10, Informed Consent; 4.02, Discussing the Limits of Confidentiality; and 6.04, Fees and Financial Arrangements. 10.01b requires that psychologists who request informed consent for treatment wherein “generally recognized techniques and procedures” are not yet established inform patients\/clients of this, including possible associated risks, available alternative treatments, and the fact that their participation is voluntary. 10.01b cross-references Standards 2.01e, Boundaries of Competence, and (again) 3.10, Informed Consent. 10.01c includes in the informed consent procedure that patients\/clients be informed if their therapist is in training and the trainee’s supervisor is legally responsible for the treatment; and that they be given the supervisor’s name."
 },
 {
  "id": 432,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Report the provisions of APA ethical Standards 10.05, Sexual Intimacies with Current Therapy Clients\/Patients; 10.06, Sexual Intimacies with Relatives or Significant Others of Current Therapy Clients\/Patients; and 10.07, Therapy with Former Sexual Partners. Briefly explain the reasons for these.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.05 forbids psychologists from engaging in sexual intimacy with their current therapy patients or clients. Standard 10.06 likewise forbids psychologists from engaging in sexual intimacies with people they know are significant others, guardians, or close relatives of their current therapy patients\/clients. It also forbids psychologists from terminating therapy to enable them to engage in such intimacies. Standard 10.07 informs psychologists that they will not accept individuals with whom they have formerly engaged in sexual intimacies to be their therapy patients\/clients. The reason for all these standards is that having sexual relationships—past or present—and also therapeutic relationships with the same person(s) constitutes a clear conflict of interest. The patient\/client is more vulnerable to manipulation or influencing by the therapist; the therapist’s objectivity is undermined; and neither therapist nor patient\/client can focus objectively on therapeutic goals or gain new insights when their relationship is not exclusively professional and therapeutic, but includes personal and sexual elements."
 },
 {
  "id": 433,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Explain what is covered in APA ethical Standards 10.03, Group Therapy; and 10.04, Providing Therapy to Those Served by Others.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.03 requires psychologists providing therapy to a group that at the beginning of therapy they identify the limits of confidentiality and the responsibilities and roles of all individuals involved. Standard 10.04 warns psychologists that when they consider providing or offering their services to individuals who are already recipients of other mental health services, their decisions should be informed by careful contemplation of the prospective patient’s or client’s well-being, as well as of any other treatment concerns. This standard further advises psychologists to talk about these concerns with the patient or client, or with their legally authorized representative, for the purposes of eliminating or reducing conflicts and\/or confusion; to consult as is indicated with other providers of services; and to employ sensitivity to therapeutic issues and caution as they proceed."
 },
 {
  "id": 434,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Identify the provisions of APA ethical Standards 10.09, Interruption of Therapy, including a cross-referenced standard; and 10.10, Terminating Therapy.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.09 provides that psychologists make realistic attempts to arrange for fitting means of resolving their responsibility for the care of the patient\/client when they establish contractual or employment relationships, in case those relationships should be ended in the future. Their primary concern according to this standard is the patient\/client’s welfare. This standard cross-references APA ethical Standard 3.12, Interruption of Psychological Services. Standard 10.10a provides that (a) psychologists will terminate a course of therapy when they realize (i.e., “when it becomes reasonably clear”) that the patient\/client will probably not benefit anymore from the therapy; does not need the therapy anymore; or is being harmed by continuing the therapy. Standard 10.10b provides that if the patient\/client, or another individual who has a relationship with the patient\/client, threatens or endangers the psychologist. Standard 10.10c provides that psychologists will give pre-termination counseling and suggest other service providers as is applicable. The exception stated is if the actions of the patient\/client or a third-party payer prevent the psychologist from providing these."
 },
 {
  "id": 435,
  "topic": "Ethical\/Legal\/Professional Issues",
  "question": "Describe what is provided by APA ethical Standard 10.08, Sexual Intimacies with Former Therapy Clients\/Patients, including a cross-reference to a related ethical standard.",
  "answer": "Standard 10.08a proscribes the engagement of psychologists in sexual interactions with former patients\/clients for a minimum of two years after therapy termination. Standard 10.08b elaborates that even after two years psychologists should not be sexually intimate with former patients\/clients “except in the most unusual circumstances.” The burden of proof that they have not exploited the former patient\/client resides with the psychologists who do engage in such intimacy. This proof includes the following pertinent factors: (1) how much time has elapsed since therapy termination; (2) how long and how intense the therapy was, and its specific nature; (3) the conditions under which therapy was terminated; (4) the personal history of the patient\/client; (5) the current mental status of the patient\/client; (6) the probability that the interaction could have unfavorable impacts on the patient\/client; and (7) anything the therapist may have done or said during therapy that offered or suggested the potential of a romantic or sexual relationship between therapist and patient\/client following therapy termination. 10.08b cross-references Standard 3.05, Multiple Relationships."
 }
]